<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../graphicstext.dtd" >

<section id="introduction.3" title="Hardware and Software">

<p1>We will be using OpenGL as the primary basis for 3D graphics programming.
The original version of OpenGL was released in 1992 by a company named
Silicon Graphics, which was known for its graphics workstations&mdash;powerful,
expensive computers designed for intensive graphical applications.  (Today,
you probably have more graphics computing power on your smart phone.)  OpenGL
is supported by the graphics hardware in most modern computing devices, including
desktop computers, laptops, and many mobile devices.  This section will give
you a bit of background about the history of OpenGL and about the graphics 
hardware that supports it.</p1>

<p>In the first desktop computers, the contents of the screen were managed
directly by the <word>CPU</word>.  For example, to draw a line segment on the screen, the CPU
would run a loop to set the color of each pixel that lies along the line.
Needless to say, graphics could take up a lot of the CPU's time.  And graphics
performance was very slow, compared to what we expect today.  So what has changed?
Computers are much faster in general, of course, but the big change is that
in modern computers, graphics processing is done by a specialized component
called a <newword>GPU</newword>, or Graphics Processing Unit.  A GPU includes processors
for doing graphics computations; in fact, it can include a large number of such
processors that work in parallel to greatly speed up graphical operations.  
It also includes its own dedicated memory for storing things like images and 
lists of coordinates.  GPU processors have very fast
access to data that is stored in GPU memory&mdash;much faster than their access to data
stored in the computer's main memory.</p>

<p>To draw a line or perform some other graphical operation, the CPU simply has to
send commands, along with any necessary data, to the GPU, which is responsible
for actually carrying out those commands.  The CPU offloads most of the graphical
work to the GPU, which is optimized to carry out that work very quickly.
The set of commands that the GPU understands make up the <word>API</word>
of the GPU.  OpenGL is an example of a graphics API, and most GPUs support
OpenGL in the sense that they can understand OpenGL commands, or at least
that OpenGL commands can efficiently be translated into commands that the
GPU can understand.</p>

<p>OpenGL is not the only graphics API.  The best-known alternatives are probably
the proprietary APIs used by Apple and Microsoft.  Apple's MacOS uses an API known
as Metal, while Microsoft Windows uses Direct3D.  Nevertheless, OpenGL
can currently still be used on MacOS and Windows.  Furthermore, a newer open API named
Vulkan has been defined as a replacement for OpenGL itself.
Vulkan is a complex, low-level
API designed more for speed and efficiency rather than ease-of-use, and it will likely
not completely replace OpenGL for some time, if ever.  Metal, Direct3D, and Vulkan
are not covered in this textbook.  We are using OpenGL since it provides an easier
introduction to 3D graphics and because it is still the basis for 3D graphics in
Web browsers. </p>

<break/>

<p>I have said that OpenGL is an API, but in fact it is a series of APIs that have
been subject to repeated extension and revision.  The current version, in 2021,
is 4.6, which was first released in 2017.  It is very different from the 1.0 version from 1992.
Furthermore,
there is a specialized version called OpengGL&nbsp;ES for "embedded systems" such
as mobile phones and tablets.  And there is also WebGL, for use in Web browsers,
which is basically a port of OpenGL ES.  It will be useful to know something
about how and why OpenGL has changed.</p>

<p>First of all, you should know that OpenGL was designed as a "client/server"
system.  The server, which is responsible for controlling the computer's
display and performing graphics computations, carries out commands issued by the
client.  Typically, the server is a GPU, including its graphics processors and memory.
The server executes OpenGL commands.  The client is the CPU in the same computer, along 
with the application program that it is running. OpenGL commands come from the
program that is running on the CPU.  However,
it is actually possible to run OpenGL programs remotely over a network.  That
is, you can execute an application program on a remote computer (the OpenGL client), while
the graphics computations and display are done on the computer that you are
actually using (the OpenGL server).</p>

<p>The key idea is that the client and the server are separate components, and there
is a communication channel between those components.  OpenGL commands and the
data that they need are communicated from the client (the CPU) to the server (the GPU)
over that channel.  The capacity of the channel can be a limiting factor in graphics
performance.  Think of drawing an image onto the screen.  If the GPU can draw the
image in microseconds, but it takes milliseconds to send the data for the image
from the CPU to the GPU, then the great speed of the GPU is irrelevant&mdash;most of
the time that it takes to draw the image is communication time.</p>

<p>For this reason, one of the driving factors in the evolution of OpenGL has been
the desire to limit the amount of communication that is needed between the CPU and
the GPU.  One approach is to store information in the GPU's memory.  If some data
is going to be used several times, it can be transmitted to the GPU once and
stored in memory there, where it will be immediately accessible to the GPU.
Another approach is to try to decrease the number of OpenGL commands that must
be transmitted to the GPU to draw a given image.</p>

<p>OpenGL draws <word term="geometric primitive">primitives</word> such as triangles.
Specifying a primitive means specifying <word term="coordinate system">coordinates</word>
and <word term="attribute">attributes</word> for each of its <word term="vertex">vertices</word>.  In the
original OpenGL&nbsp;1.0, a separate command was used to specify the coordinates of each vertex,
and a command was needed each time the value of an attribute changed.  To draw a single 
triangle would require three or more commands.  Drawing a complex object made up of
thousands of triangles would take many thousands of commands.  Even in OpenGL&nbsp;1.1,
it became possible to draw such an object with a single command instead of thousands.  All the data
for the object would be loaded into arrays, which could then be sent in a single
step to the GPU.  Unfortunately, if the object was going to be drawn more than
once, then the data would have to be retransmitted each time the object was drawn.
This was fixed in OpenGL&nbsp;1.5 with <newword term="VBO">Vertex Buffer Objects</newword>.
A VBO is a block of memory in the GPU that can store the coordinates or attribute values for
a set of vertices.  This makes it possible to reuse the data without having to retransmit it
from the CPU to the GPU every time it is used.</p>

<p>Similarly, OpenGL 1.1 introduced <newword term="texture object">texture objects</newword>
to make it possible to store several images on the GPU for use as <word term="texture">textures</word>.
This means that texture images that are going to be reused several times can be loaded once
into the GPU, so that the GPU can easily switch between images without having to reload them.</p>

<break/>

<p>As new capabilities were added to OpenGL, the API grew in size.  But the growth was still
outpaced by the invention of new, more sophisticated techniques for doing graphics.  Some
of these new techniques were added to OpenGL, but
the problem is that no matter how many features you add, there will always be demands for 
new features&mdash;as well as complaints that all the new features are making things too 
complicated! OpenGL was a giant machine, with new pieces always being tacked onto it, 
but still not pleasing everyone. The real solution was to make the machine <b>programmable</b>.
With OpenGL 2.0, it became possible to write programs to be executed as part of the
graphical computation in the GPU.  The programs are run on the GPU at GPU speed.
A programmer who wants to use a new graphics technique can write a program to 
implement the feature and just hand it to the GPU.  The OpenGL API doesn't have to
be changed.  The only thing that the API has to support is the ability to send programs
to the GPU for execution.</p>

<p>The programs are called <newword term="shader">shaders</newword> (although the term doesn't
really describe what most of them actually do).  The first shaders to be introduced were
<newword term="vertex shader">vertex shaders</newword> and <newword term="fragment shader">fragment shaders</newword>.
When a <word term="geometric primitive">primitive</word> is drawn, some work has to be done at each vertex of the primitive,
such as applying a <word>geometric transform</word> to the vertex coodinates or
using the <word term="attribute">attributes</word> and global <word>lighting</word> environment
to compute the color of that vertex.  A vertex shader is a program that can take over the
job of doing such "per-vertex" computations.  Similarly, some work has to be done for each
pixel inside the primitive.  A fragment shader can take over the job of performing such
"per-pixel" computations.  (Fragment shaders are also called pixel shaders.)</p>

<p>The idea of programmable graphics hardware was very successful&mdash;so successful that
in OpenGL&nbsp;3.0, the usual per-vertex and per-fragment processing
was deprecated (meaning that its use was discouraged). 
And in OpenGL&nbsp;3.1, it was removed from
the OpenGL standard, although it is still present as an optional extension.  In practice,
all the original features of OpenGL are still supported in desktop versions of OpenGL and will
probably continue to be available in the future.  On the embedded system side, however,
with OpenGL&nbsp;ES&nbsp;2.0 and later, the use of shaders is mandatory, and a large part
of the OpenGL&nbsp;1.1 API has been completely removed.
WebGL, the version of OpenGL for use in web browsers, 
is based on OpenGL&nbsp;ES, and it also requires shaders to get anything at all done.
Nevertheless, we will begin our study of OpenGL with version 1.1.  Most of the concepts and
many of the details from that version are still relevant, and it offers an easier entry point
for someone new to 3D graphics programming.</p>

<p>OpenGL shaders are written in <newword>GLSL</newword> (OpenGL Shading Language).  Like
OpenGL itself, GLSL has gone through several versions. We will spend some time later in the
course studying GLSL&nbsp;ES, the version used with WebGL and
OpenGL&nbsp;ES.  GLSL uses a syntax similar to the C programming language.</p>

<break/>

<p>As a final remark on GPU hardware, I should note that the computations that are done for
different vertices are pretty much independent, and so can potentially be done in parallel.
The same is true of the computations for different fragments.  In fact, GPUs can
have hundreds or thousands of processors that can operate in parallel.  Admittedly, the
individual processors are much less powerful than a CPU, but then typical per-vertex
and per-fragment computations are not very complicated.  The large number of processors,
and the large amount of parallelism that is possible in graphics computations, makes
for impressive graphics performance even on fairly inexpensive GPUs.</p>

</section>

