<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../graphicstext.dtd" >

<section title="3D Coordinates and Transforms" id="gl1geom.2">

<p1>In <localref href="graphics2d"/>, we looked fairly closely at 
<word term="coordinate system">coordinate systems</word> and 
<word term="geometric transform">transforms</word> 
in two-dimensional computer graphics.  In this section and the
<localref href="gl1geom.3">next</localref>, we will move that 
discussion into 3D.  Things are more complicated in three
dimensions, but a lot of the basic concepts remain the
same.</p1>

<subsection title="3D Coordinates" id="gl1geom.2.1">

<p>A coordinate system is a way of assigning numbers to points.
In two dimensions, you need a pair of numbers to specify a
point.  The coordinates are often referred to as <i>x</i> and
<i>y</i>, although of course, the names are arbitrary.  More than that,
the assignment of pairs of numbers to points is itself arbitrary to
a large extent.  Points and objects are real things, but
coordinates are just numbers that we assign to them so that
we can refer to them easily and work with them mathematically.
We have seen the power of this when we discussed transforms, 
which are defined mathematically in terms of coordinates but which have
real, useful physical meanings.</p>

<p>In three dimensions, you need three numbers to specify a point.
(That's essentially what it means to be three dimensional.)
The third coordinate is often called <i>z</i>.  The <i>z</i>-axis
is perpendicular to both the <i>x</i>-axis and the <i>y</i>-axis.</p>


<demo src="c3/axes3D.html" width="350" height="370">
<p><web>This demo</web><tex>This image</tex> illustrates a 3D coordinate
system.  The positive directions of the <i>x</i>, <i>y</i>,
and <i>z</i> axes are shown as big arrows.  The <i>x</i>-axis is green,
the <i>y</i>-axis is blue, and the <i>z</i>-axis is red. <web>You can</web><tex>The
on-line version of this section has a demo version of this image in
which you</tex> drag on the axes to rotate the image.</p>
</demo>
<texdiv><img tex="axes3D.eps" texscale="0.6"/></texdiv>

<p>This example is a 2D image, but it has a 3D look.  (The illusion is
much stronger if you <tex>can </tex>rotate the image.)  Several things
contribute to the effect.  For one thing, objects that are farther
away from the viewer in 3D look smaller in the 2D image.  This is
due to the way that the 3D scene is "projected" onto 2D.  We will
discuss projection in the <localref href="gl1geom.3">next section</localref>.
Another factor is the "shading" of the objects.  The objects are shaded
in a way that imitates the interaction of objects with the light that
illuminates them.  We will put off a discussion of lighting until
<localref href="gl1light"/>.  In this section, we will concentrate on
how to construct a scene in 3D&mdash;what we have referred to as
<word term="modeling transformation">modeling</word>.</p>

<p>OpenGL programmers usually think in terms of a coordinate system in which
the <i>x</i>- and <i>y</i>-axes lie in the plane of the screen, and the <i>z</i>-axis is perpendicular
to the screen with the positive direction of the <i>z</i>-axis pointing <b>out
of</b> the screen towards the viewer.   Now, the default
coordinate system in OpenGL, the one that you are using if you
apply no transformations at all, is similar but has the positive direction of the <i>z</i>-axis
pointing <b>into</b> the screen.  This is not a contradiction:  The coordinate
system that is actually used is arbitrary.  It is set up by a transformation.
The convention in OpenGL is to work with a coordinate system in which the
positive <i>z</i>-direction points toward the viewer and the negative
<i>z</i>-direction points away from the viewer.  The transformation into
default coordinates reverses the direction of the <i>z</i>-axis.</p>

<p>This conventional arrangement of the axes produces a 
<newword>right-handed coordinate system</newword>.  This means that if
you point the thumb of your right hand in the direction of the positive
<i>z</i>-axis, then when you curl the fingers of that hand, they will curl
in the direction from the positive <i>x</i>-axis towards the positive <i>y</i>-axis.
If you are looking at the tip of your thumb, the curl will be in the counterclockwise
direction.  Another way to think about it is that if you curl the figures of your
right hand from the positive <i>x</i> to the positive <i>y</i>-axis, then your
thumb will point in the direction of the positive <i>z</i>-axis.
The default OpenGL coordinate system (which, again, is hardly ever used)
is a left-handed system.  You should spend some time trying to visualize
right- and left-handed coordinates systems.  Use your hands!</p>

<p>All of that describes the natural coordinate system from the viewer's point of view,
the so-called "eye" or "viewing" coordinate system.
However, these <newword>eye coordinates</newword> are not necessarily the natural coordinates on the world.
The coordinate system on the world&mdash;the coordinate system in
which the scene is assembled&mdash;is referred to as
<newword>world coordinates</newword>.</p>

<p>Recall that objects are not usually specified directly in world coordinates.
Instead, objects are specified in their own coordinate system,
known as <word>object coordinates</word>, and then <word term="modeling transformation">modeling transforms</word>
are applied to place the objects into the world, or into more complex objects.
In OpenGL, object coordinates are the numbers that are used in the
<i>glVertex*</i> function to specify the vertices of the object.  However,
before the objects appear on the screen, they are usually subject to a sequence
of transformations, starting with a modeling transform.</p>

</subsection>

<subsection title="Basic 3D Transforms" id="gl1geom.2.2">

<p>The basic transforms in 3D are extensions of the basic transforms that
you are already familiar with from 2D:  <word>rotation</word>, 
<word>scaling</word>, and <word>translation</word>.  We will look at
the 3D equivalents and see how they affect objects when applied as
modeling transforms.  We will also discuss how to use the transforms
in OpenGL.</p>

<p>Translation is easiest.  In 2D, a translation adds some number onto each coordinate.  The
same is true in 3D; we just need three numbers, to specify the amount of motion
in the direction of each of the coordinate axes.  A translation by (<i>dx,dy,dz</i>)
transforms a point (<i>x,y,z</i>) to the point (<i>x+dx,&nbsp;y+dy,&nbsp;z+dz</i>).
In OpenGL, this translation would be specified by the command</p>

<pre>glTranslatef( dx, dy, dz );</pre>

<np>or by the command</np>

<pre>glTranslated( dx, dy, dz );</pre>

<np>The translation will affect any drawing that is done after the command is given.
Note that there are two versions of the command.  The first, with a name ending in "f",
takes three <ptype>float</ptype> values as parameters.  The second, with a name ending in "d",
takes parameters of type <ptype>double</ptype>.  As an example,</np>

<pre>glTranslatef( 0, 0, 1 );</pre>

<np>would translate objects by one unit in the <i>z</i> direction.</np>

<p>Scaling works in a similar way: Instead of one scaling factor, you need three.  The
OpenGL command for scaling is <i>glScale*</i>, where the "*" can be either "f" or "d".
The command</p>

<pre>glScalef( sx, sy, sz );</pre>

<np>transforms a point (<i>x,y,z</i>) to (<i>x*sx,&nbsp;y*sy,&nbsp;z*sz</i>).  That is,
it scales by a factor of <i>sx</i> in the <i>x</i> direction, <i>sy</i> in the <i>y</i>
direction, and <i>sz</i> in the <i>z</i> direction.  Scaling is about the origin;
that is, it moves points farther from or closer to the origin, (0,0,0).  For
uniform scaling, all three factors would be the same.  You can use scaling by
a factor of minus one to apply a reflection.  For example,</np>

<pre>glScalef( 1, 1, -1 );</pre>

<np>reflects objects through the <i>xy</i>-plane by reversing the sign of the <i>z</i>
coordinate.  Note that a reflection will convert a right-handed coordinate system into
a left-handed coordinate system, and <i>vice versa</i>.  Remember
that the left/right handed distinction is not a property of the world, just
of the way that one chooses to lay out coordinates on the world.</np>

<p>Rotation in 3D is harder.  In 2D, rotation is rotation about a point, which is usually
taken to be the origin.  In 3D, rotation is rotation about a line, which is called
the <newword>axis of rotation</newword>.  Think of the Earth rotating
about its axis.  The axis of rotation is the line that passes through the North Pole 
and the South Pole.  The axis stays fixed as the Earth rotates around it,
and points that are not on the
axis move in circles about the axis.  Any line can be an axis of rotation, but
we generally use an axis that passes through the origin.  The most
common choices for axis of rotation are the coordinates axes, that is,
the <i>x</i>-axis, the <i>y</i>-axis, or the <i>z</i>-axis.  Sometimes,
however, it's convenient to be able to use a different line
as the axis.</p>

<p>There is an easy way to specify a line that
passes through the origin:  Just specify one other
point that is on the line, in addition to the origin.   That's how things are
done in OpenGL:  An axis of rotation is specified by three numbers,
(<i>ax,ay,az</i>), which are not all zero.  The axis is the line
through (0,0,0) and (<i>ax,ay,az</i>).  To specify a rotation transformation in 3D,
you have to specify an axis and the angle of rotation about that axis.</p>

<p>We still have to account for the difference between positive and negative
angles.  We can't just say clockwise or counterclockwise.  If you look down on
the rotating Earth from above the North pole, you see a counterclockwise rotation; if you
look down on it from above the South pole, you see a clockwise rotation.
So, the difference between the two is not well-defined.  To define the
direction of rotation in 3D, we use the <newword>right-hand rule</newword>, which
says:  Point the thumb of your right hand in the direction of the
axis &mdash; from the point (0,0,0) towards the point (<i>ax,ay,az</i>) that determines the
axis. Then the direction of rotation for positive angles is given by the
direction in which your fingers curl. I should emphasize that the right-hand rule
only works if you are working in a right-handed coordinate system.  If you have
switched to a left-handed coordinate system, then you need to use a
left-hand rule to determine the positive direction of rotation.</p>

<demo src="c3/rotation-axis.html" width="600" height="375">
<p><web>You can use the following demo to help you understand rotation about an
axis in three-dimensional space.  Use the buttons labeled "+X", "-X", and so on to
make the cube rotate about the coordinate axes, or enter any (<i>x,y,z</i>) point
and click "Set".  Drag your mouse on the image to rotate the 
scene.</web><tex>The demo <demoref href="c3/rotation-axis.html"/>
can help you to understand rotation in three-dimensional space.</tex></p>
</demo>

<p>The rotation function in OpenGL is <i>glRotatef</i>(<i>r,ax,ay,az</i>).
You can also use <i>glRotated</i>.
The first parameter specifies the angle of rotation, measured in degrees.
The other three parameters specify the axis of rotation, which is the line
from (0,0,0) to (<i>ax,ay,az</i>).</p>

<p>Here are a few examples of scaling, translation, and scaling in OpenGL:</p>

<pre>glScalef(2,2,2);        // Uniform scaling by a factor of 2.

glScalef(0.5,1,1);      // Shrink by half in the x-direction only.

glScalef(-1,1,1);       // Reflect through the yz-plane.
                        // Reflects the positive x-axis onto negative x.

glTranslatef(5,0,0);    // Move 5 units in the positive x-direction.

glTranslatef(3,5,-7.5); // Move each point (x,y,z) to (x+3, y+5, z-7.5).

glRotatef(90,1,0,0);    // Rotate 90 degrees about the x-axis.
                        // Moves the +y axis onto the +z axis
                        //    and the +z axis onto the -y axis.
                        
glRotatef(-90,-1,0,0);  // Has the same effect as the previous rotation.

glRotatef(90,0,1,0);    // Rotate 90 degrees about the y-axis.
                        // Moves the +z axis onto the +x axis
                        //    and the +x axis onto the -z axis.
                        
glRotatef(90,0,0,1);    // Rotate 90 degrees about the z-axis.
                        // Moves the +x axis onto the +y axis
                        //    and the +y axis onto the -x axis.
                        
glRotatef(30,1.5,2,-3); // Rotate 30 degrees about the line through
                        //    the points (0,0,0) and (1.5,2,-3).</pre>
                        
<np>Remember that transforms are applied to objects that are drawn after
the transformation function is called, and that transformations apply to
objects in the opposite order of the order in which they appear in the code.</np>

<p>Of course, OpenGL can draw in 2D as well as in 3D.  For 2D drawing in OpenGL,
you can draw on the <i>xy</i>-plane, using zero for the <i>z</i> coordinate.
When drawing in 2D, you will probably want to apply 2D versions of rotation, scaling,
and translation.  OpenGL does not have 2D transform functions, but you can just use
the 3D versions with appropriate parameters:</p>

<ul>
<li>For translation by (<i>dx,dy</i>) in 2D, use <i>glTranslatef</i>(<i>dx,&nbsp;dy,&nbsp;0</i>).
The zero translation in the <i>z</i> direction means that the transform doesn't change
the <i>z</i> coordinate, so it maps the <i>xy</i>-plane to itself.  (Of course, you
could use <i>glTranslated</i> instead of <i>glTranslatef</i>.)</li>
<li>For scaling by (<i>sx,sy</i>) in 2D, use <i>glScalef</i>(<i>sx,&nbsp;sy,&nbsp;1</i>), which
scales only in the <i>x</i> and <i>y</i> directions, leaving the <i>z</i> coordinate
unchanged.</li>
<li>For rotation through an angle <i>r</i> about the origin in 2D, use <i>glRotatef</i>(<i>r,&nbsp;0,&nbsp;0,&nbsp;1</i>).
This is rotation about the <i>z</i>-axis, which rotates the <i>xy</i>-plane into itself.
In the usual OpenGL coordinate system, the <i>z</i>-axis points out of the screen, 
and the right-hand rule says that rotation by a positive angle will be in the counterclockwise 
direction in the <i>xy</i>-plane.  Since the <i>x</i>-axis points to the right and the
<i>y</i>-axis points upwards, a counterclockwise rotation rotates the positive <i>x</i>-axis
in the direction of the positive <i>y</i>-axis.  This is the same convention that we have
used previously for the positive direction of rotation.</li>
</ul>

</subsection>


<subsection title="Hierarchical Modeling" id="gl1geom.2.3">

<p>Modeling transformations are often used in <word>hierarchical modeling</word>,
which allows complex objects to be built up out of simpler objects.  See
<localref href="graphics2d.4"/>.  To review briefly:  In hierarchical modeling, an object can
be defined in its own natural coordinate system, usually using (0,0,0) as a reference
point.  The object can then be scaled, rotated, and translated to place it into
world coordinates or into a more complex object.  To implement this, we need
a way of limiting the effect of a modeling transformation to one object or to
part of an object.  That can be done using a stack of transforms.  Before
drawing an object, push a copy of the current transform onto the stack.  After drawing
the object and its sub-objects, using any necessary temporary transformations,
restore the previous transform by popping it from the stack.</p>

<p>OpenGL 1.1 maintains a stack of transforms and provides functions for
manipulating that stack.  (In fact it has several transform stacks, for different
purposes, which introduces some complications that we will postpone to the 
<localref href="gl1geom.3">next section</localref>.)  Since transforms are
represented as <word term="matrix">matrices</word>, the stack is actually a stack of matrices.
In OpenGL, the functions for operating on the stack are named <i>glPushMatrix</i>() and
<i>glPopMatrix</i>().</p>

<p>These functions do not take parameters or return a value.  OpenGL keeps track of
a current matrix, which is the composition of all transforms that have been applied.
Calling a function such as <i>glScalef</i> simply modifies the current matrix.  When
an object is drawn, using the <i>glVertex*</i> functions, the coordinates that were specified
for the object are transformed by the current matrix.  There is another function
that affects the current matrix:  <i>glLoadIdentity</i>().  Calling
<i>glLoadIdentity</i> sets the current matrix to be the <word>identity transform</word>,
which represents no change of coordinates at all and is the usual starting point for
a series of transformations.</p>

<p>When the function <i>glPushMatrix</i>() is called, a copy of the current matrix is
pushed onto the stack.  Note that this does not change the current matrix; it just
saves a copy on the stack.  When <i>glPopMatrix</i>() is called, the matrix on the
top of the stack is popped from the stack, and that matrix replaces the current matrix.
Note that <i>glPushMatrix</i> and <i>glPopMatrix</i> must always occur in
corresponding pairs; <i>glPushMatrix</i> saves a copy of the current matrix, and a corresponding
call to <i>glPopMatrix</i> restores that copy.  Between a call to <i>glPushMatrix</i> and
the corresponding call to <i>glPopMatrix</i>, there can be additional calls of these
functions, as long as they are properly paired.  Usually, you will call <i>glPushMatrix</i>
before drawing an object and <i>glPopMatrix</i> after finishing that object.  In between,
drawing sub-objects might require additional pairs of calls to those functions.</p>

<p>As an example, suppose that we want to draw a cube.  It's not hard to draw each
face using glBegin/glEnd, but let's do it with transformations.  We can start with
a function that draws a square in the position of the front face of the cube.
For a cube of size 1, the front face would sit one-half unit in front of the screen,
in the plane <i>z</i>&nbsp;=&nbsp;0.5, and it would have vertices at
(-0.5,&nbsp;-0.5,&nbsp;0.5), (0.5,&nbsp;-0.5,&nbsp;0.5), (0.5,&nbsp;0.5,&nbsp;0.5), and (-0.5,&nbsp;0.5,&nbsp;0.5).
Here is a function that draws the square.  The function's parameters are floating 
point numbers in the range 0.0 to 1.0
that give the <word>RGB color</word> of the square:</p>

<pre>void square( float r, float g, float b ) {
    glColor3f(r,g,b);  // Set the color for the square.
    glBegin(GL_TRIANGLE_FAN);
    glVertex3f(-0.5, -0.5, 0.5);
    glVertex3f(0.5, -0.5, 0.5);
    glVertex3f(0.5, 0.5, 0.5);
    glVertex3f(-0.5, 0.5, 0.5);
    glEnd();
}</pre>

<np>To make a red front face for the cube, we just need to call <i>square</i>(1,0,0).
Now, consider the right face, which is perpendicular to the <i>x</i>-axis, in the plane
<i>x</i>&nbsp;=&nbsp;0.5.  To make a right face, we can start with a front face and rotate
it 90 degrees about the <i>y</i>-axis.  Think about rotating the front face (red) to the position
of the right face (green) in this illustration by rotating the red square about the <i>y-axis</i>:</np>

<img src="rotate-cube-side.png" width="188" height="178" bordered="true" tex="rotate-cube-side.eps" texscale="0.8"/>

<np>So, we can draw a green right face for the cube with</np>

<pre>glPushMatrix();
glRotatef(90, 0, 1, 0);
square(0, 1, 0);
glPopMatrix();</pre>

<np>The calls to <i>glPushMatrix</i> and <i>glPopMatrix</i> ensure that the rotation that
is applied to the square will not carry over to objects that are drawn later.
The other four faces can be made in a similar way, by rotating the front face about the
coordinate axes.  You should try to visualize the rotation that you need in each case.
We can combine it all into a function that draws a cube.  To make it more interesting,
the size of the cube is a parameter:</np>

<pre>void cube(float size) {  // Draws a cube with side length = size.

    glPushMatrix();  // Save a copy of the current matrix.
    glScalef(size,size,size); // Scale unit cube to desired size.
    
    square(1, 0, 0); // red front face
    
    glPushMatrix();
    glRotatef(90, 0, 1, 0);
    square(0, 1, 0); // green right face
    glPopMatrix();
    
    glPushMatrix();
    glRotatef(-90, 1, 0, 0);
    square(0, 0, 1); // blue top face
    glPopMatrix();
    
    glPushMatrix();
    glRotatef(180, 0, 1, 0);
    square(0, 1, 1); // cyan back face
    glPopMatrix();
    
    glPushMatrix();
    glRotatef(-90, 0, 1, 0);
    square(1, 0, 1); // magenta left face
    glPopMatrix();
    
    glPushMatrix();
    glRotatef(90, 1, 0, 0);
    square(1, 1, 0); // yellow bottom face
    glPopMatrix();
    
    glPopMatrix(); // Restore matrix to its state before cube() was called.

}</pre>

<np>The sample program <sourceref href="glut/unlit-cube.c"/> uses this function to
draw a cube, and lets you rotate the cube by pressing the arrow keys.
A Java version is <sourceref href="jogl/UnlitCube.java"/>, and a web version is
<sourceref href="glsim/unlit-cube.html"/>.  Here is an image of the cube, rotated
by 15 degrees about the <i>x</i>-axis and -15 degrees about the <i>y</i>-axis to make
the top and right sides visible:</np>

<img src="unlit-cube.png" width="180" height="175" tex="unlit-cube.eps" texscale="0.8"/> 

<p>For a more complex example of hierarchical modeling with <i>glPushMatrix</i> and
<i>glPopMatrix</i>, you can check out an OpenGL equivalent of the "cart and windmills"
animation that was used as an example in <localref href="graphics2d.4.1"/>.  
The three versions of the example are:
<sourceref href="glut/opengl-cart-and-windmill-2d.c"/>,
<sourceref href="jogl/CartAndWindmillJogl2D.java"/>, and
<sourceref href="glsim/opengl-cart-and-windmill.html"/>.
This program is an example of hierarchical 2D graphics in OpenGL.</p>

<break/>

<p>Keep in mind that transformation and matrix functions such as <i>glRotated</i>() and
<i>glPushMatrix</i>() are old-fashioned OpenGL.  In WebGL and other modern graphics APIs,
you will be responsible for managing transforms and matrices on your own.  You are quite
likely to do that using a software library that provides functions very similar to those
that are built into OpenGL&nbsp;1.1.</p>

</subsection>


</section>
