<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../graphicstext.dtd" >

<section title="Using GLUT and JOGL" id="gl1geom.6">

<p1>OpenGL is an <word>API</word> for graphics only, with no support for things like
windows or events.  OpenGL depends on external mechanisms to
create the drawing surfaces on which it will draw.  Windowing APIs
that support OpenGL often do so as one library among many others that
are used to produce a complete application.  We will look at
two cross-platform APIs that make it possible to use OpenGL
in applications, one for C/C++ and one for Java.</p1>

<p>For simple applications written in C or C++, one possible
windowing API is <newword>GLUT</newword> (OpenGL Utility Toolkit).  GLUT is a small
API.  It is used to create windows that serve as
simple frames for OpenGL drawing surfaces.  It has support for
handling mouse and keyboard events, and it can do basic animation.
It does not support controls such as buttons or input fields,
but it does allow for a menu that pops up in response to
a mouse action.  The original version of GLUT is no longer actively
supported, and a version called freeglut (<a href="http://freeglut.sourceforge.net/">http://freeglut.sourceforge.net/</a>)
is recommended instead.  For example, the version included in Linux is actually freeglut.
For details of the freeglut API, see</p>

<p align="center"><a href="http://freeglut.sourceforge.net/docs/api.php">http://freeglut.sourceforge.net/docs/api.php</a></p>

<p><newword>JOGL</newword> (Java OpenGL) is a collection of classes that make it
possible to use OpenGL in Java applications.  JOGL is integrated
into Swing and AWT, the standard Java graphical user interface APIs.
With JOGL, you can create Java GUI components on which
you can draw using OpenGL.  These OpenGL components can be
used in any Java application, in much the same way that you
would use a <classname>Canvas</classname>
or <classname>JPanel</classname> as a drawing surface.
Like many things Java, JOGL is immensely complicated.  We will use it
only in fairly simple applications.
JOGL is not a standard part of Java.  It's home web site is</p>

<p align="center"><a href="http://jogamp.org/jogl/www/">http://jogamp.org/jogl/www/</a></p>

<p>This section contains information to get you started using GLUT and JOGL, assuming
that you already know the basics of programming with C and Java.  It also briefly
discusses <i>glsim.js</i>, a JavaScript library that I have written to simulate the subset
of OpenGL 1.1 that is used in this book.</p>


<subsection title="Using GLUT" id="gl1geom.6.1">


<p>To work with GLUT, you will need
a C compiler and copies of the OpenGL and GLUT (or freeglut)
development libraries.  I can't tell you exactly that means on
your own computer.  On my computer, which runs Linux Mint, for example,
the free C compiler gcc is already available.  To do OpenGL
development, I installed several packages, including
<i>freeglut3-dev</i> and <i>libgl1-mesa-dev</i>.
(Mesa is a Linux implementation of OpenGL.)  If <i>glutprog.c</i> contains
a complete C program that uses GLUT, I can compile it using a command such as
</p>

<pre>gcc -o glutprog glutprog.c -lGL -lglut</pre>

<np>The "-o glutprog" tells the compiler to use "glutprog" as the
name of its output file, which can then be run as a normal executable file;
without this option, the executable file would be named "a.out".
The "-lglut" and "-lGL" options tell the compiler to link the program with the GLUT and OpenGL libraries.
(The character after the "-" is a lower case "L".)
Without these options, the linker won't recognize any GLUT or OpenGL functions.  If the program
also uses the <word>GLU</word> library, compiling it would require the option "-lGLU, and if it uses
the math library, it would need the option "-lm".  If a program requires additional .c files,
they should be included as well.  For example, the sample program
<sourceref href="glut/color-cube-of-spheres.c"/> depends on <i>camera.c</i>, and it
can be compiled with the Linux gcc compiler using the command:</np>

<pre>gcc -o cubes color-cube-of-spheres.c camera.c -lGL -lglut -lGLU -lm</pre>

<p>The sample program <sourceref href="glut/glut-starter.c"/> can be used as a starting
point for writing programs that use GLUT.  While it doesn't do anything except open a
window, the program contains the framework needed to do OpenGL drawing, including doing
animation, responding to mouse and keyboard events, and setting up a menu.  The source
code contains comments that tell you how to use it.</p>

<p><b>On Windows</b>, you might consider installing the WSL, or Windows Subsystem for Linux,
(<a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/wsl/">https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/wsl/</a>),
which as I write this should soon include the ability to work with GUI programs.
WSL is an official Microsoft system lets you install a version of Linux inside Windows.
Another option is the older open source project, Cygwin (<a href="https://cygwin.com/">https://cygwin.com/</a>).
(Using Cygwin, I installed the packages gcc-core, xinit, xorg-server, libglut-devel, libGLU-devel,
and libGL-devel.  After starting the X11 window system with the startxwin command, I was able to 
compile and run OpenGL examples from this textbook in a Cygwin terminal window using the same
commands that I would use in Linux.)</p>

<p><b>For MacOS</b>, the situation is more complicated, because OpenGL has been deprecated
in favor of Metal, Apple's own proprietary API.  However, as I write this, OpenGL can still be
used on MacOS with Apple's XCode developer tools.  The examples from this textbook require
some modification to work with XCode tools, since the OpenGL and GLUT libraries are not loaded
in the same way on Mac as they are on Linux.  Modified programs for use on MacOS can be found in the
source folder <sourceref href="glut/glut-mac"/>.  See the README.txt file in that folder
for more information.</p>

<break/>

<p>The GLUT library makes it easy to write basic OpenGL applications in&nbsp;C.  GLUT
uses event-handling functions.  You write functions to handle events that occur
when the display needs to be redrawn or when the user clicks the mouse or presses a key
on the keyboard.</p>

<p>To use GLUT, you need to include the header file <i>glut.h</i> (or <i>freeglut.h</i>)
at the start of any source code file that uses it, along with the general OpenGL header file,
<i>gl.h</i>.  The header files should be installed in a standard location, in a folder named <i>GL</i>.
(But note that the folder name could be different, or omitted entirely.)
So, the program usually begins with something like</p>

<pre>#include &lt;GL/gl.h&gt;
#include &lt;GL/glut.h&gt;</pre>

<np>On my computer, saying <i>#include &lt;GL/glut.h&gt;</i> actually includes the subset
of FreeGLUT that corresponds to GLUT.  To get access to all of FreeGLUT, I would
substitute <i>#include&nbsp;&lt;GL/freeglut.h&gt;</i>.  Depending on the features that it uses,
a program might need other header files, such as <i>#include&nbsp;&lt;GL/glu.h&gt;</i> 
and <i>#include&nbsp;&lt;math.h&gt;</i>.</np>

<p>The program's <i>main</i>() function must contain some code to initialize GLUT, to
create and open a window, and to set up event handling by registering the functions that
should be called in response to various events.  After this setup, it must
call a function that runs the GLUT event-handling loop.  That function
waits for events and processes them by calling the functions that have been registered
to handle them.  The event loop runs until the program ends, which happens when
the user closes the window or when the program calls the standard <i>exit</i>() function.</p>

<p>To set up the event-handling functions,
GLUT uses the fact that in C, it is possible to pass a function name as a parameter
to another function.  For example, if <i>display</i>() is the function that 
should be called to draw the content of the window, then the
program would use the command</p>

<pre>glutDisplayFunc(display);</pre>

<np>to install this function as an event handler for
display events. A display event occurs when the contents of the window need to be redrawn, including
when the window is first opened.
Note that <i>display</i> must have been previously defined, as a function with no parameters:</np>

<pre>void display() {
   .
   .  // OpenGL drawing code goes here!
   .
}</pre>

<np>Keep in mind that it's not the name of this function that makes it an OpenGL display
function.  It has to be set as the display function by calling <i>glutDisplayFunc</i>(<i>display</i>).
All of the GLUT event-handling functions work in a similar way (except many of them do need
to have parameters).</np>

<p>There are a lot of possible event-handling functions, and I will only cover some of
them here.  Let's jump right in and look at a possible <i>main</i>() routine for a GLUT
program that uses most of the common event handlers:</p>


<pre>int main(int argc, char** argv) {
    glutInit(&amp;argc, argv);  // Required initialization!
    glutInitDisplayMode(GLUT_DOUBLE | GLUT_DEPTH);
    glutInitWindowSize(500,500);        // size of display area, in pixels
    glutInitWindowPosition(100,100);    // location in screen coordinates
    glutCreateWindow("OpenGL Program"); // the parameter is the window title  

    glutDisplayFunc(display);       // called when window needs to be redrawn
    glutReshapeFunc(reshape);       // called when size of the window changes
    glutKeyboardFunc(keyFunc);      // called when user types a character
    glutSpecialFunc(specialKeyFunc);// called when user presses a special key
    glutMouseFunc(mouseFunc);       // called for mousedown and mouseup events
    glutMotionFunc(mouseDragFunc);  // called when mouse is dragged
    glutIdleFunc(idleFun);          // called when there are no other events

    glutMainLoop(); // Run the event loop!  This function never returns.
    return 0;  // (This line will never actually be reached.)
}</pre>



<np>The first five lines do some necessary initialization, the next seven lines install event
handlers, and the call to <i>glutMainLoop</i>() runs the GLUT event loop.  I will discuss all of
the functions that are used here.  The first GLUT function call must be <i>glutInit</i>,
with the parameters as shown.  (Note that <i>argc</i> and <i>argv</i>
represent command-line arguments for the program.  Passing them to <i>glutInit</i> allows
it to process certain command-line arguments that are recognized by GLUT.  I won't discuss those
arguments here.)  The functions <i>glutInitWindowSize</i> and <i>glutInitWindowPosition</i>
do the obvious things; size is given in pixels, and 
window position is given in terms of pixel coordinates on the computer
screen, with (0,0) at the upper left corner of the screen.  The function <i>glutCreateWindow</i>
creates the window, but note that nothing can happen in that window until <i>glutMainLoop</i>
is called.  Often, an additional, user-defined function is called in <i>main</i>() to do
whatever initialization of global variables and OpenGL state is required by the program.
OpenGL initialization can be done after calling <i>glutCreateWindow</i> and before
calling <i>glutMainLoop</i>.  Turning to the other functions used in <i>main</i>(),</np>

<p><codedef>glutInitDisplayMode(GLUT_DOUBLE | GLUT_DEPTH)</codedef> &mdash; Must be called to
define some characteristics of the OpenGL drawing context.  The parameter specifies
features that you would like the OpenGL context to have.  The features are represented by
constants that are OR'ed together in the parameter.  <i>GLUT_DEPTH</i> says that a depth buffer
should be created; without it, the depth test won't work.  If you are doing 2D graphics, you
wouldn't include this option.  <i>GLUT_DOUBLE</i> asks for <newword>double buffering</newword>, 
which means that drawing is actually done off-screen, and the
off-screen copy has to copied to the screen to be seen.  The copying is done by
<codedef>glutSwapBuffers()</codedef>, which <b>must</b> be called at the end of the display function.
(You can use <i>GLUT_SINGLE</i> instead of <i>GLUT_DOUBLE</i> to get <newword>single buffering</newword>; 
in that case, you have to call <i>glFlush</i>() at the end of the display function instead
of <i>glutSwapBuffers</i>().  However, all of the examples in this book use <i>GLUT_DOUBLE</i>.)</p>

<p><codedef>glutDisplayFunc(display)</codedef> &mdash; The display function
should contain OpenGL drawing code that can completely redraw the scene.  This is
similar to <i>paintComponent</i>() in the Java Swing API.
The display function can have any name, but it must be declared as a void
function with no parameters: <i>void&nbsp;display</i>().</p>

<p><codedef>glutReshapeFunc(reshape)</codedef> &mdash; The reshape function
is called when the user changes the size of the window.  Its parameters tell the
new width and height of the drawing area:</p>

<pre>void reshape( int width, int height )</pre>

<np>For example, you might use this method to set up the projection transform, if the
projection depends only on the window size.  A reshape function is not required, but
if one is provided, it should always set the
OpenGL <word>viewport</word>, which is the part of the window that
is used for drawing.  Do this by calling</np>

<pre>glViewport(0,0,width,height);</pre>

<np>The viewport is set automatically if no reshape function is specified.</np>

<p><codedef>glutKeyboardFunc(keyFunc)</codedef> &mdash; The keyboard function is
called when the user types a character such as 'b' or 'A' or a space.  It is not called
for special keys such as arrow keys that do not produce characters when pressed.
The keyboard function has a parameter of type <ptype>unsigned char</ptype> which
represents the character that was typed.  It also has two <i>int</i> parameters 
that give the location of the mouse when the key was pressed, in pixel coordinates
with (0,0) at the upper left corner of the display area.  So, the definition of
the key function must have the form:</p>

<pre>void keyFunc( unsigned char ch, int x, int y )</pre>

<np>Whenever you make any changes to the program's data that require the display to be redrawn,
you should call <i>glutPostRedisplay</i>().  This is similar to calling <i>repaint</i>() in
Java.  It is better to call <i>glutPostRedisplay</i>()
than to call the display function directly.  (I also note that it's possible to
call OpenGL drawing commands directly in the event-handling functions, but it probably only makes
sense if you are using single buffering; if you do this, call <i>glFlush</i>()
to make sure that the drawing appears on the screen.)</np>

<p><codedef>glutSpecialFunc(specialKeyFunc)</codedef> &mdash; The "special"
function is called when the user presses certain special keys, such as an arrow
key or the Home key.  The parameters are an integer code for the key that was pressed, plus the
mouse position when the key was pressed:</p>

<pre>void specialKeyFunc( int key, int x, int y )</pre>

<np>GLUT has constants to represent the possible key codes, including
<i>GLUT_KEY_LEFT</i>, <i>GLUT_KEY_RIGHT</i>, <i>GLUT_KEY_UP</i>, and <i>GLUT_KEY_DOWN</i>
for the arrow keys and <i>GLUT_KEY_HOME</i> for the Home key. For example,
you can check whether the user pressed the left arrow key by testing
<code>if</code>&nbsp;<code>(key&nbsp;==&nbsp;GLUT_KEY_LEFT)</code>.</np>

<p><codedef>glutMouseFunc(mouseFunc)</codedef> &mdash; The mouse function is
called both when the user presses and when the user releases a button on the mouse, with a parameter to tell
which of these occurred.  The function will generally look like this:</p>

<pre>void mouseFunc(int button, int buttonState, int x, int y) {
   if (buttonState == GLUT_DOWN) {
        // handle mousePressed event
   }
   else { // buttonState is GLUT_UP
        // handle mouseReleased event
   }
}</pre>

<np>The first parameter tells which mouse button was pressed or released; its
value is the constant <i>GLUT_LEFT_BUTTON</i> for the left, <i>GLUT_MIDDLE_BUTTON</i> for the 
middle, and <i>GLUT_RIGHT_BUTTON</i> for the right mouse button.  The other
two parameters tell the position of the mouse.  The mouse position
is given in pixel coordinates with (0,0) in the top left corner of the display area and
with y increasing from top to bottom.</np>

<p><codedef>glutMotionFunc(mouseDragFunc)</codedef> &mdash; The motion function
is called when the user moves the mouse while dragging, that is, while a mouse button
is pressed.  After the user presses the mouse in the OpenGL window, this function will
continue to be called even if the mouse moves outside the window, and the mouse
release event will also be sent to the same window.  The function has two parameters
to specify the new mouse position:</p>

<pre>void mouseDragFunc(int x, int y)</pre>

<p><codedef>glutIdleFunc(idleFunction)</codedef> &mdash; The idle function is called by the
GLUT event loop whenever there are no events waiting to be processed.  The
idle function has no parameters.  It is called as often as possible, not at
periodic intervals.  GLUT also has a timer function, which schedules some function to be
called once, after a specified delay.  To set a timer, call</p>

<pre><codedef>glutTimerFunc(delayInMilliseconds, timerFunction, userSelectedID)</codedef></pre>

<np>and define <i>timerFunction</i> as</np>

<pre>void timerFunction(int timerID) { ...</pre>

<np>The parameter to <i>timerFunction</i> when it is called will be the same integer that was passed as
the third parameter to <i>glutTimerFunc</i>.  If you want to use <i>glutTimerFunc</i>
for animation, then <i>timerFunction</i> should end with another call to <i>glutTimerFunc</i>.</np>

<break/>

<p>A GLUT window does not have a menu bar, but it is possible to add a hidden popup menu to the window.
The menu will appear in response to a mouse click on the display.  You can set whether it
is triggered by the left, middle, or right mouse button.</p>

<p>A menu is created using the function <i>glutCreateMenu(menuHandler)</i>,
where the parameter is the name of a function that will be called when the user
selects a command from the menu.  The function must be defined with a parameter of
type <ptype>int</ptype> that identifies the command that was selected:</p>

<pre>void menuHandler( int commandID ) { ...</pre>

<p>Once the menu has been created, commands are added to the menu by calling the function
<i>glutAddMenuEntry</i>(<i>name,commandID</i>).  The first parameter is the string that
will appear in the menu.  The second is an <ptype>int</ptype> that identifies the
command; it is the integer that will be passed to the menu-handling function when
the user selects the command from the menu.</p>

<p>Finally, the function <i>glutAttachMenu</i>(<i>button</i>) attaches the menu to the
window.  The parameter specifies which mouse button will trigger the menu.  Possible
values are <i>GLUT_LEFT_BUTTON</i>, <i>GLUT_MIDDLE_BUTTON</i>, and <i>GLUT_RIGHT_BUTTON</i>.
As far as I can tell, if a mouse click is used to trigger the popup menu, than the same
mouse click will <b>not</b> also produce a call to the mouse-handler function.</p>

<p>Note that a call to <i>glutAddMenuEntry</i> doesn't mention the menu, and a
call to <i>glutAttachMenu</i> doesn't mention either the menu or the window.
When you call <i>glutCreateMenu</i>, the menu that is created becomes the "current
menu" in the GLUT state.  When <i>glutAddMenuEntry</i> is called, it adds a command
to the current menu.  When <i>glutAttachMenu</i> is called, it attaches the current
menu to the current window, which was set by a call to <i>glutCreateWindow</i>.
All this is consistent with the OpenGL "state machine" philosophy, where functions
act by modifying the current state.</p>

<p>As an example, suppose that we want to let the user set the background color for
the display.  We need a function to carry out commands that we will add to the menu.  For example,
we might define</p>

<pre>function doMenu( int commandID ) {
    if ( commandID == 1)
        glClearColor(0,0,0,1);  // BLACK
    else if ( commandID == 2)
        glClearColor(1,1,1,1);  // WHITE
    else if ( commandID == 3)
        glClearColor(0,0,0.5,1);  // DARK BLUE
    else if (commandID == 10)
        exit(0);  // END THE PROGRAM
    glutPostRedisplay();  // redraw the display, with the new background color
}</pre>

<np>We might have another function to create the menu.  This function would be called
in <i>main</i>(), after calling <i>glutCreateWindow</i>:</np>

<pre>function createMenu() {
    glutCreateMenu( doMenu );  // Call doMenu() in response to menu commands.
    glutAddMenuEntry( "Black Background", 1 );
    glutAddMenuEntry( "White Background", 2 );
    glutAddMenuEntry( "Blue Background", 3 );
    glutAddMenuEntry( "EXIT", 10 );
    glutAttachMenu(GLUT_RIGHT_BUTTON); // Show menu on right-click.
}</pre>

<p>It's possible to have submenus in a menu.  I won't discuss the procedure here, but you can look
at the sample program <sourceref href="glut/ifs-polyhedron-viewer.c"/> for an example of using submenus.</p>

<break/>
   
<p>In addition to window and event handling, GLUT includes some functions for drawing basic 3D shapes
such as spheres, cones, and <word term="regular polyhedron">regular polyhedra</word>.  
It has two functions for each shape, a "solid" version that draws
the shape as a solid object, and a <newword>wireframe</newword> version that draws 
something that looks like it's made of wire mesh.  (The wireframe is produced by drawing 
just the outlines of the polygons that make up the object.)  For example, the function</p>

<pre>void glutSolidSphere(double radius, int slices, int stacks)</pre>

<np>draws a solid sphere with the given radius, centered at the origin.  Remember that this is
just an approximation of a sphere, made up of polygons.  For the approximation, the sphere is divided by
lines of longitude, like the slices of an orange, and by lines of latitude, like a stack of disks.
The parameters <i>slices</i> and <i>stacks</i> tell how many subdivisions to use.  Typical values
are 32 and 16, but the number that you need to get a good approximation for a sphere depends on the
size of the sphere on the screen.  The function <i>glutWireframeSphere</i> has the same parameters but
draws only the lines of latitude and longitude.  Functions for a cone, a cylinder, 
and a <newword>torus</newword> (doughnut) are similar:</np>
 
<pre>void glutSolidCone(double base, double height,
                                       int slices, int stacks)

void glutSolidTorus(double innerRadius, double outerRadius,
                                       int slices, int rings)
                                    
void glutSolidCylinder(double radius, double height,
                                       int slices, int stacks)
   // NOTE: Cylinders are available in FreeGLUT and in Java,
   // but not in the original GLUT library.</pre>

<np>For a torus, the <i>innerRadius</i> is the size of the doughnut hole.  The function</np>

<pre>void glutSolidCube(double size)</pre>

<np>draws a cube of a specified size.
There are functions for the other regular polyhedra that have no parameters and draw the 
object at some fixed size:  <i>glutSolidTetrahedron</i>(), <i>glutSolidOctahedron</i>(),
<i>glutSolidDodecahedron</i>(), and <i>glutSolidIcosahedron</i>().
There is also <i>glutSolidTeapot</i>(<i>size</i>) that draws a famous object that is often used as an
example.  Here's what the teapot looks like:</np>

<img src="teapot.png" width="359" height="234" tex="teapot.eps" texscale="0.6"/>

<np>Wireframe versions of all of the shapes are also available.  For example,
<i>glutWireTeapot</i>(<i>size</i>) draws a wireframe teapot.  Note that 
GLUT shapes come with <word term="normal vector">normal vectors</word> that
are required for lighting calculations.  However, except for the teapot, they do
not come with <word>texture coordinates</word>, which are required for applying
textures to objects. </np>

<p>GLUT also includes some limited support for drawing text in an OpenGL drawing
context.  I won't discuss that possibility here.  You can check the API
documentation if you are interested, and you can find an example in the
sample program <sourceref href="glut/color-cube-of-spheres.c"/>.</p>

</subsection>


<subsection title="Using JOGL" id="gl1geom.6.2">

<p>JOGL is a framework for using OpenGL in Java programs.  It is a large and complex API that
supports all versions of OpenGL, but it is fairly easy to use for basic applications.
You should use JOGL&nbsp;2.4 or later.  Version 2.4.0 is still under development, but I have
used it to run the sample programs from this textbook without any problems.  The previous
version, Jogl&nbsp;2.3.2, has some problems with modern versions of Java, but it might work
for you.</p>

<p>The sample program <sourceref href="jogl/JoglStarter.java"/> can be used as a starting
point for writing OpenGL programs using JOGL. While it doesn't do anything except open a
window, the program contains the framework needed to do OpenGL drawing, including doing
animation, responding to mouse and keyboard events, and setting up a menu.  The source
code contains comments that tell you how to use it.</p>

<p>To use JOGL, you will need two .jar files containing the Java classes for JOGL:
<i>jogl-all.jar</i> and <i>gluegen-rt.jar</i>.  In addition, you will
need two native library files.  A native library is
a collection of routines that can be called from Java but are not written in Java.  Routines
in a native library will work on only one kind of computer; you need a different native library
for each type of computer on which your program is to be used.  The native libraries for
JOGL are stored in additional .jar files, which are available in several versions for
different computers.  For example, for 64-bit Linux on Intel or AMD CPUs, you need
<i>jogl-all-natives-linux-amd64.jar</i> and <i>gluegen-rt-natives-linux-amd64.jar</i>.
It is unfortunate that there are different versions for different platforms, since
many people don't know exactly which one they are using.  However, if you are in doubt, you can get
more than one version; JOGL will figure out which one to use.</p>

<p>JOGL software can be found at <a href="https://jogamp.org/">https://jogamp.org/</a>.
You can download the jar files from the most recent release, which
can be found at the very end of the list at</p>

<p align="center">
<a href="https://jogamp.org/deployment/archive/rc/">https://jogamp.org/deployment/archive/rc/</a>
</p>

<np>I downloaded the files from the release <i>v2.4.0-rc-20210111</i>.  Click on the
release name, then click on the <i>jar/</i> link to see the full list of jar files.
Find and download <i>jogl-all.jar</i> and <i>gluegen-rt.jar</i> and the corresponding
native library files.  I have also made jogl-all.jar and gluegen-rt.jar available on
my own web site, along with the native libraries for some of the most common platforms, at</np>

<p align="center">
<a href="http://math.hws.edu/eck/cs424/jogl_2_4_support/">http://math.hws.edu/eck/cs424/jogl_2_4_support/</a>
</p>

<np>JOGL is open-source, and the files are freely redistributable, according to their
license.</np>

<p>To do JOGL development, you should create a directory somewhere on your computer to hold the jar
files.  Place the two JOGL jar files in that directory, along with the two native library jar files
for your platform.  (Having extra native library jar files doesn't hurt, as long as you have
the ones that you need.)</p>

<p>It is possible to do JOGL development on the command line.  You have to tell the
<i>javac</i> command where to find the two JOGL jar files. You do that in the
classpath ("-cp") option to the <i>javac</i> command.  For example, if you are working
in Linux or MacOS, and if the jar
files happen to be in the same directory where you are working, you might say:</p>

<pre>javac  -cp  jogl-all.jar:gluegen-rt.jar:.  MyOpenGLProg.java</pre>

<np>It's similar for Windows, except that the classpath uses a ";" instead of a ":" to
separate the items in the list:</np>

<pre>javac  -cp  jogl-all.jar;gluegen-rt.jar;.  MyOpenGLProg.java</pre>

<np>There is an essential period at the end of the classpath, which makes it possible for Java to
find .java files in the current directory.
If the jar files are not in the current directory,
you can use full path names or relative path names to the files.  For example,</np>

<pre>javac  -cp  ../jogl/jogl-all.jar:../jogl/gluegen-rt.jar:.  MyOpenGLProg.java</pre>

<np>Running a program with the <i>java</i> command is exactly similar. For example:</np>

<pre>java  -cp  jogl-all.jar:gluegen-rt.jar:.  MyOpenGLProg</pre>

<np>Note that you don't have to explicitly reference the native library jar files.
They just have to be in the same directory with the JOGL jar files.</np>

<break/>

<p>I do most of my Java development using the Eclipse IDE (<a href="http://eclipse.org">http://eclipse.org</a>).
To do development with JOGL in Eclipse, you will have to configure Eclipse
with information about the jar files.  To do that, start up Eclipse.  You want to
create a "User Library" to contain the jar files:
Open the Eclipse Preferences window, and select "Java" / "Build&nbsp;Path" / "User&nbsp;Libraries"
on the left.  Click the "New" button on the right.  Enter "JOGL" (or any name you like) as the
name of the user library.  Make sure that the new user library is selected in the
list of libraries, then click the "Add External Jars" button.  In the file selection box,
navigate to the directory that contains the JOGL jar files, and select the two jar files that
are needed for JOGL, <i>jogl-all.jar</i> and <i>gluegen-rt.jar</i>.  
(Again, you do not need to add the native libraries; they just need to be in the same directory
as the JOGL jar files.)  Click "Open."  The selected
jars will be added to the user library. (You could also add them one at a time, if you don't
know how to select multiple files.)  It should
look something like this:</p>

<img src="jogl-user-library.png" width="686" height="503" tex="jogl-user-library.eps" texscale="0.5"/>

<np>Click "OK."  The user library has been created. You will only have to do this
once, and then you can use it in all of your JOGL projects.</np>

<p>Now, to use OpenGL in a project, create a new Java project as usual in Eclipse.
(If you are asked whether you want to create a module-info.java file for the project, say "Don't Create".
Sample programs for this textbook do not use Java modules.) 
Right-click the new project in the Project Explorer view, and select "Build&nbsp;Path" /
"Configure&nbsp;Build&nbsp;Path" from the menu.  You will see the project Properties
dialog, with "Java Build Path" selected on the left.  (You can also access this through the
"Properties" command in the "Project" menu.)  Select the "Libraries" tab at the top of the
window, and then click on "Class&nbsp;Path" in the "Libraries" tab to select it.
Click the "Add&nbsp;Library" button, on the right.  In the popup window, select "User&nbsp;Library"
and click "Next."  In the next window, select your JOGL User Library and click "Finish."
Finally, click "Apply and Close" in the main Properties window.  Your project should now be set up
to do JOGL development.  You should see the JOGL User Library listed as part of the
project in the Project Explorer.  Any time you want to start a new JOGL project, you can go through
the same setup to add the JOGL User Library to the build path in the project.</p>

<break/>
   
<p>With all that setup out of the way, it's time to talk about actually
writing OpenGL programs with Java.  With JOGL,
we don't have to talk about mouse and keyboard handling or animation, since that can be done
in the same way as in any Java Swing program.  You will only need to know about a few classes from
the JOGL API.</p>

<p>First, you need a GUI component on which you can draw using OpenGL.  For that, you
can use <classname>GLJPanel</classname>, which is a subclass of <classname>JPanel</classname>.
(<classname>GLJPanel</classname> is for use in programs based on the Swing API; an alternative
is <classname>GLCanvas</classname>, which is a subclass of the older AWT class
<classname>Canvas</classname>.)  The class is defined in the package <i>com.jogamp.opengl.awt</i>.
All of the other classes that we will need for basic OpenGL programming 
are in the package <i>com.jogamp.opengl</i>.</p>

<p>JOGL uses Java's event framework to manage OpenGL drawing contexts, and it defines a
custom event listener interface, <classname>GLEventListener</classname>, to manage
OpenGL events.  To draw on a <classname>GLJPanel</classname> with OpenGL, you need to
create an object that implements the <classname>GLEventListener</classname> interface, and
register that listener with your <classname>GLJPanel</classname>.  The <classname>GLEventListener</classname>
interface defines the following methods:
</p>

<pre>public void init(GLAutoDrawable drawable)

public void display(GLAutoDrawable drawable)

public void dispose(GLAutoDrawable drawable)

public void reshape(GLAutoDrawable drawable,
                           int x, int y, int width, int height)</pre>

<np>The <i>drawable</i> parameter in these methods tells which OpenGL drawing surface
is involved.  It will be a reference to the <classname>GLJPanel</classname>.
(<classname>GLAutoDrawable</classname>  is an interface that is implemented by
<classname>GLJPanel</classname> and other OpenGL drawing surfaces.)
The <i>init</i>() method is a place to do OpenGL initialization.  (According to the
documentation, it can actually be called several times, if the OpenGL context
needs to be recreated for some reason. So <i>init</i>() should not be used to
do initialization that shouldn't be done more than once.) The 
<i>dispose</i>() method will be called to give you a chance to
do any cleanup before the OpenGL drawing context is destroyed.
The <i>reshape</i>() method is called when the window first opens and
whenever the size of the <classname>GLJPanel</classname> changes.
OpenGL's <i>glViewport</i>() function is called automatically before <i>reshape</i>()
is called, so you won't need to do it yourself.  Usually, you won't need to write
any code in <i>dispose</i>() or <i>reshape</i>(), but they have to be there to
satisfy the definition of the <classname>GLEventListener</classname> interface.</np>

<p>The <i>display</i>() method is where the actual drawing is done and where you
will do most of your work.  It should ordinarily clear the drawing area and completely redraw the scene.
Take a minute to study an outline for a minimal JOGL program.  It creates a
<classname>GLJPanel</classname> which also serves as the
<classname>GLEventListener</classname>:</p>



<pre>import com.jogamp.opengl.*;
import com.jogamp.opengl.awt.GLJPanel;

import java.awt.Dimension;
import javax.swing.JFrame;

public class JOGLProgram extends GLJPanel implements GLEventListener {

    public static void main(String[] args) {
        JFrame window = new JFrame("JOGL Program");
        JOGLProgram panel = new JOGLProgram();
        window.setContentPane(panel);
        window.pack();
        window.setLocation(50,50);
        window.setDefaultCloseOperation(JFrame.EXIT_ON_CLOSE);
        window.setVisible(true);
    }

    public JOGLProgram() {
        setPreferredSize( new Dimension(500,500) );
        addGLEventListener(this);
    }
    
    // ---------------  Methods of the GLEventListener interface -----------

    public void init(GLAutoDrawable drawable) {
            // called when the panel is created
        GL2 gl = drawable.getGL().getGL2();
        // Add initialization code here!
    }

    public void display(GLAutoDrawable drawable) {    
            // called when the panel needs to be drawn
        GL2 gl = drawable.getGL().getGL2();
        // Add drawing code here!
    }

    public void reshape(GLAutoDrawable drawable,
                              int x, int y, int width, int height) {
        // called when user resizes the window
    }

    public void dispose(GLAutoDrawable drawable) {
        // called when the panel is being disposed
    }

}</pre>

<break/>
   
<p>At this point, the only other thing you need to know is how to use OpenGL
functions in the program.  In JOGL, the OpenGL&nbsp;1.1 functions are collected into
an object of type <classname>GL2</classname>.  (There are different classes
for different versions of OpenGL;  <classname>GL2</classname> contains
OpenGL&nbsp;1.1 functionality, along with later versions that are compatible with 1.1.)
An object of type <classname>GL2</classname> is an OpenGL graphics context,
in the same way that an object of type <classname>Graphics2D</classname>
is a graphics context for ordinary Java 2D drawing.  The statement
</p>

<pre>GL2 gl = drawable.getGL().getGL2();</pre>

<np>in the above program obtains the drawing context for
the <classname>GLAutoDrawable</classname>, that is, for the
<classname>GLJPanel</classname> in that program.  The name of the
variable could, of course, be anything, but <i>gl</i> or <i>gl2</i> is conventional.</np>

<p>For the most part, using OpenGL functions in JOGL is the same as in C,
except that the functions are now methods in the object <i>gl</i>.  For example,
a call to <i>glClearColor</i>(<i>r,g,b,a</i>) becomes</p>

<pre>gl.glClearColor(r,g,b,a);</pre>

<np>The redundant "gl.gl" is a little annoying, but you get used to it.  OpenGL constants
such as <i>GL_TRIANGLES</i> are static members of <classname>GL2</classname>, so that, for
example, <i>GL_TRIANGLES</i> becomes <i>GL2.GL_TRIANGLES</i> in JOGL.
Parameter lists for OpenGL functions
are the same as in the C API in most cases.  One exception is for functions such as <i>glVertex3fv</i>()
that take an array/pointer parameter in C.  In JOGL, the parameter becomes an ordinary
Java array, and an extra integer parameter is added to give the position of the data in
the array.  Here, for example, is how one might draw a triangle in JOGL, with all the
vertex coordinates in one array:</np>

<pre>float[] coords = { 0,0.5F, -0.5F,-0.5F, 0.5F,-0.5F };

gl.glBegin(GL2.GL_TRIANGLES);
gl.glVertex2fv(coords, 0);     // first vertex data starts at index 0
gl.glVertex2fv(coords, 2);     // second vertex data starts at index 2
gl.glVertex2fv(coords, 4);     // third vertex data starts at index 4
gl.glEnd();</pre>

<p>The biggest change in the JOGL API is the use of <word term="nio buffer">nio buffers</word>
instead of arrays in functions such as <i>glVertexPointer</i>.  This is discussed
in <localref href="gl1geom.4.3"/>.  We will see in <localref href="gl1light.3.9"/> that texture images also get special
treatment in JOGL.</p>

<break/>

<p>The JOGL API includes a class named <classname>GLUT</classname> that makes GLUT's
shape-drawing functions available in Java.  (Since you don't need GLUT's window or event functions
in Java, only the shape functions are included.)  Class <classname>GLUT</classname>
is defined in the package <i>com.jogamp.opengl.util.gl2</i>.
To draw shapes using this class, you need
to create an object of type GLUT.  It's only necessary to make one of these for use in a program:</p>

<pre>GLUT glut = new GLUT();</pre>

<np>The methods in this object include all the shape-drawing functions from the GLUT C API,
with the same names and parameters.  For example:</np>

<pre>glut.glutSolidSphere( 2, 32, 16 );
glut.glutWireTeapot( 5 );
glut.glutSolidIcosahedron();</pre>

<np>(I don't know why these are instance methods in an object rather than
static methods in a class; logically, there is no need for the object.)</np>
 
 <p>The GLU library is available through the class <i>com.jogamp.opengl.glu.GLU</i>,
 and it works similarly to GLUT.   That is, you have to create an object of type
 <classname>GLU</classname>, and the GLU functions will be available as methods
 in that object.  We have encountered GLU only for the functions <i>gluLookAt</i>
 and <i>gluPerspective</i>, which are discussed in <localref href="gl1geom.3"/>.
 For example,</p>
 
 <pre>GLU glu = new GLU();
 
glu.gluLookAt( 5,15,7, 0,0,0, 0,1,0 );</pre>

</subsection>


<subsection title="About glsim.js" id="gl1geom.6.3">

<p>The JavaScript library <i>glsim.js</i> was written to accompany and support this textbook.
It implements the subset of OpenGL 1.1 that is discussed in <localref href="gl1geom"/> and
<localref href="gl1light"/>, except for display lists (<localref href="gl1geom.4.4"/>).
It is used in the demos that appear in<tex> the on-line versions of</tex>
those chapters.  Many of the sample programs that are discussed in those chapters are available
in JavaScript versions that use glsim.js.</p>

<p>If you would like to experiment with OpenGL 1.1, 
but don't want to go through the trouble of setting up a C or Java environment that supports 
OpenGL programming, you can consider writing your programs as web pages using glsim.js.
Note that glsim is meant for experimentation and practice only, not for serious applications.</p>

<p>The OpenGL API that is implemented by glsim.js is essentially the same as the C API, although 
some of the details of semantics are different.  Of course the techniques for creating a
drawing surface and an OpenGL drawing context are specific to JavaScript and differ from
those used in GLUT or JOGL.</p>

<p>To use glsim.js, you need to create an <word>HTML</word> document with a &lt;canvas&gt; element
to serve as the drawing surface.  The HTML file has to import the script; if glsim.js is in the
same directory as the HTML file, you can do that with</p>

<pre>&lt;script src="glsim.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</pre>

<np>To create the OpenGL drawing context, use the JavaScript command</np>

<pre>glsimUse(canvas);</pre>

<np>where <i>canvas</i> is either a string giving the <i>id</i> of the &lt;canvas&gt; element or
is the JavaScript <word>DOM</word> object corresponding to the &lt;canvas&gt; element. Once you
have created the drawing context in this way, any OpenGL commands that you give will apply to
the canvas.  To run the program, you just need to open the HTML document in a web browser that
supports <word>WebGL</word>&nbsp;1.0.</np>

<p>The easiest way to get started programming is to modify a program that already exists.
The sample program <sourceref href="glsim/first-triangle.html"/>, from <localref href="gl1geom.1.2"/>
is a very minimal example of using glsim.js.
The sample web page <sourceref href="glsim/glsim-starter.html"/> can be used as a starting
point for writing longer programs that use glsim.js.  It provides a framework for doing OpenGL drawing,
with support for animation and mouse and keyboard events.  The code contains comments that tell 
you how to use it.  Some documentation for the glsim.js library can be found in
<sourceref href="glsim/glsim-doc.html"/>.<tex> All of these files are part of the web site
for this textbook and can be found in the web site download in a folder named <i>glsim</i>
inside the <i>source</i> folder.</tex></p>

</subsection>

</section>
