<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../graphicstext.dtd" >

<section title="Blender Animation" id="blender.3">

<p1>Blender can be used to create <word term="animation">animations</word> and videos.
We will look at basic keyframe animation in Blender as well as a couple kinds of 
animation that can't be done with simple keyframes.  At the end of the section,
I will explain how to render an animation in Blender.</p1>


<subsection title="Keyframe Animation and F-Curves" id="blender3.1">

<p>Blender uses "<word>keyframe animation</word>."  That is, you set the value of a property,
such as location or scale, in several
"key" frames in the animation, and Blender will compute a value for other frames by
interpolating between the values for the key frames.  Exactly 
how the interpolation is done is determined by a set of "F-curves," which you can
edit to completely control the interpolation (and extrapolation beyond the key frames).</p>

<p>There is Timeline area at the bottom of the default Blender window that contains
some information about animations and lets you control them:</p>

<img src="blender-timeline.png" width="736" height="81" tex="blender-timeline.eps" texscale="0.5"/>

<np>The timeline shows the starting frame number, the end frame, and the current
frame of the animation (1, 250, and 12 in the picture).  The current frame number specifies the frame
that is displayed in the 3D View.  These are numerical input
buttons that you can edit. 
To the left of the frame number inputs is a set of playback controls,
which run the animation in the 3D View window.  You can also start and stop playing the animation
by pressing the spacebar.  The start and end frames determine
the range of frames that are displayed when the animation is played.  
They also determine what frames will be included when you
render an animation.  Note that the default 250 frames make a rather short animation when viewed at
a typical frame rate of about 30 frames per second.</np>

<p>Below the frame number inputs and playback controls is the timeline itself, with the frame number
running along an axis from left to right.  The blue tab marks
the current frame on the timeline. You can drag the blue tab or click on the timeline to set the current frame.
The orange and white diamond shapes mark frames that have been set as key frames
for the object that is currently selected in the 3D&nbsp;View (if any).
You can drag a diamond to move the key to a different frame, and you can select
groups of diamonds. (The orange ones are the ones that are selected).  If you right-click the timeline,
you get a popup menu; the "Interpolation Mode" submenu can be used to set how interpolation
between the selected (orange) keys is computed.  (Try the "Elastic" Dynamic Effect.)</p>

<p>To animate an object, you need to enter values for one or more of its properties for
at least two key frames.  Select the frame number for which you want to enter a key value,
by clicking in the timeline or entering the value in the current frame input.
Select the object and hit the "I"&nbsp;key to insert a key value for that
object in the current frame. (The mouse cursor must be in the 3D View for this to work.)
A popup menu will allow you to select the property or properties for which you want to insert key values.
For example, to store values for both the current location and the current rotation of the
object, select "Location Rotation" from the menu.</p>

<p>After inserting one key frame, change the current frame number,
move or rotate or scale the object to the values that you want for the new keyframe,
and use the I&nbsp;key again.  Then, when you drag the blue tab in the timeline back and forth, 
you can see how the  object animates.</p>

<p>To delete a key from an object, go to the frame from which you want to delete
the value, select the object, and hit ALT-I.  You will asked to confirm that you
want to delete the key.</p>

<p>You can also animate many properties in the Properties Editor panel.  For example,
to animate the color of the object, set the frame number, point the mouse at the Base Color in the
Material Properties, and hit the I&nbsp;key.  Change the current frame number and repeat, and so on.
You can also insert a key frame by right-clicking a property in the Properties Editor and selecting
"Insert Keyframe" from the popup; if a key frame already exists, the popup has an entry
for deleting it.</p>

<break/>

<p>As you get into keyframe animation, you might find that you need more control.
You get some control using the Timeline popup menu.
But interpolation between keyframes is ultimately controlled by functions called
F-curves.  You can see the F-curves and edit them in the Graph Editor,
which is not shown by default.  One way to use it is in the animation screen 
that you get by clicking the "Animation" button at the top of the Blender window.
The bottom of that screen has a "Dope Sheet" that shows keyframe markers for all
animated properties.  In the Dope Sheet "View" menu, there
is a "Toggle Graph Editor" command that will replace the Dope Sheet with a
Graph Editor.  Alternatively, you can change the editor in any area of
the window to a Graph Editor by selecting it from the popup menu in the top-left
corner of the area.</p>

<p>The Graph Editor shows F-curves
for the object that is selected in the 3D View.
Here is the Graph editor showing some F-curves for an animated object
that has key frame values for the location and rotation:
</p>

<img src="blender-graph-editor.png" width="566" height="339" tex="blender-graph-editor.eps" texscale="0.7"/>

<np>Each curve controls one animated property, plotting the value of the property on the
vertical axis against the frame number on the horizontal axis.
The curves are  Bezier curves by default.
In the picture, the Rotation curves have been hidden (by clicking the "eyes" next to the
curve names), and the three visible curves and all their Bezier handles have been
selected (by hitting the "A" key while the mouse is over the graphs).

The dots on the curves mark key frame values.  You can select and move them using the "G"&nbsp;Key; 
hit the "Y"&nbsp;key after the "G" key to force the dot to stay in the same frame.
Any changes that you make will immediately affect the 3D View.  You can select and
move the control points on the Bezier curve handles to change the shape of the curve.</np>

<p>You can change the scale on the graphs using the
scroll wheel on the mouse.  Or you can control-middle-mouse drag on the graphs;  drag vertically to change the vertical scale,
horizontally to change the horizontal scale.  Without the Control key, dragging
the middle mouse button will translate the graphs.  An easy way to nicely fit the scale
to the graphs is to hit the "Home" key, with the mouse over the graphs.</p>


<break/>

<p>Let's say that you want an object to rotate through one complete 360-degree rotation about the
<i>y</i>-axis as the frame number goes from 1 to 60.  You can start with an unrotated object
in frame 1 and insert a Rotation keyframe using the I&nbsp;Key.  Then move to frame 60.  
You want the rotation in frame 60 to
be 360 degrees about the <i>y</i>-axis, but that means that object will look exactly the
same as it did at the beginning!  How do you set the value for the rotation keyframe at
frame 60? Hit the "N" key with the mouse in the 3D&nbsp;View to reveal the Transform
controls, including numerical inputs for the Location, Rotation, and Scale
that are applied to the object.  You can use those inputs to set the value numerically.
Change the Y-rotation value to 360, and then use the I&nbsp;Key to insert the keyframe. </p>

<p>Now, as the frame changes from 1 to 60, you should see the object go through a complete rotation.
If you click the playback button starting in frame&nbsp;0, you will notice that the
rotation starts out slow, speeds up, then slows down again at the end.  This might be reasonable
for an object that starts out at rest, then goes through one rotation, and stops at the
end.  But suppose you really want a constant speed of rotation?  This is a question
of interpolation between keyframes.  There is also the issue of what happens before the
first keyframe and after the last keyframe.  That is a question of extrapolation.</p>

<p>To get a constant speed of rotation, you want linear interpolation.  To get that,
you can select the start and end keys &mdash; either on an F-curve, in the Dope Sheet, or
in a Timeline &mdash; and then choose "Linear" Interpolation Mode, which you can find
in the "Key" menu or in the popup menu that you get by right-clicking.</p>

<p>To control extrapolation of the selected properties in the Dope Sheet or Graph Editor, 
you can use the "Extrapolation Mode" submenu of the "Channel" menu.
"Constant" extrapolation, which is the default, means that the property does not change
after the last keyframe. "Linear" extrapolation means that the property continues to 
change after the last keyframe with the same rate of change. "Make Cyclic" means that
the entire animation will loop forever after the last keyframe.</p>

<p>For our rotation example, "Make Cyclic" extrapolation will make the full 360-degree
rotation repeat forever.  Here's what the F-curve for the y-rotation looks like with
"Linear"" interpolation and "Make Cyclic" extrapolation:</p>

<img src="blender-cyclic-f-curve.png" width="464" height="318" tex="blender-cyclic-f-curve.eps" texscale="0.6"/>

<np>You should have perpetual rotation at a constant speed.
Admittedly, this is more complicated than it should be.  But hopefully if you work
through this exercise, it will give you some idea of how F-curves can be used.</np>

</subsection>



<subsection title="Tracking" id="blender.3.3">

<p>Recall that you can "parent" one object to another (<localref href="blender.1.6"/>).
"Tracking"" is a kind of parenting.  When one object tracks another, the
rotation of the first object is always set so that it faces the object that
it is tracking.  To set up a tracking relation, click the object that
you want to do the tracking, then shift-click the object that you
want it to track.  Go to the "Track" submenu of the "Object" menu in the 3D&nbsp;View,
and select "Damped Track Constraint" or "Track To Constraint."
 The first, "Damped Track Constraint" seems
to work well in general, but "Track To Constraint" seems to work better
when it's a camera that's doing the tracking.  (You can clear tracking by selecting
the object that is doing the tracking and using the "Clear Track" command in
the same menu.)</p>

<p>Tracking is in fact a "constraint",
and after you set it up you will find it listed in the "Constraint Properties" in the
Properties Editor when the tracking object is selected.    In the Constraint Properties, 
you can set which axis of the
tracking object points towards the object that is being tracked.
(Tracking is only one kind of "constraint."
You can use the Constraint controls in the properties editor panel
to set and clear various constraints in addition to tracking. "Stretch To" is
interesting, and we will look at "Follow Path" later in this section.)</p>

<p>Tracking works especially well for cameras and spotlights.  You can make
them track moving objects, so that the camera or light is always pointed
at the object.  This is a place where
using an "Empty" object can make sense: You can point the camera or spotlight at
a location without having an actual object there, by making it track an
Empty.  You can move the Empty to direct
the spotlight, and by animating the Empty, you
can make the camera or spotlight pan across the scene.  Or if the camera or light
is animated, you can set it to track a stationary Empty
to keep it pointed at the same location even as it moves around.</p>


</subsection>



<subsection title="Path Animation" id="blender.3.4">

<p>Path animation can be used to move an object along a curve.  Any Bezier or NURBS
curve will work.  For example, you can get circular motion by moving an object
along a Bezier circle.  For path animation, if you want the motion to be restricted to two dimensions, 
remember to set the curve to be 2D (<localref href="blender.2.2"/>).</p>

<p>Curves of type "Path" are often used for path animation.
A "Path" in Blender is a kind of NURBS curve for which the endpoints of the
curve are constrained to lie at the first and last control point of the curve,
which makes it easier to control where the curve begins and ends.
To add a path to a scene, use Add / Curve / Path.  (The path might be
almost invisible, since it is a straight line.  I suggest going immediately
into Edit Mode by hitting the Tab key, so that you can see it better.
You will probably want to be in Edit Mode in any case.)
Initially, the path is a straight line with four control points.
Recall that you can extend a non-closed path by going into Edit Mode, selecting one
of the endpoints, and using control-right-click to add points.  You can also add
points in the middle of the curve by selecting a pair of consecutive control points
and hitting "Subdivide" in the 3D&nbsp;View popup menu.
You can close the path by hitting ALT-C key while in Edit Mode.  And, of course,
you can select control points and move, scale, or rotate them.</p>

<p>There are two ways to make an object follow a curve.  The easiest way
treats path animation as a kind of parenting: Click the object, shift-click the curve,
hit Control-P, and select "Follow Path" from the popup menu. You will notice that the
object does not actually jump onto the curve.  To make it do that, select the object
that is following the path, go to the
"Clear" submenu in the "Object" menu, and select the "Clear Origin" command.
You should now have a path animation in which the object moves along the
path between frame number&nbsp;0 and frame number&nbsp;100, with linear extrapolation
after frame&nbsp;100.  To change the number of frames, go to the Object Properties
for the curve, in the Properties Editor, and change the value of "Frames" under
"Path Animation." Remember that 100 frames is only about 4 seconds!
Also, make sure Path Animation is checked there, or you won't
see any animation.  Checking the "Clamp" checkbox will change the extrapolation mode
to constant, so that the object will stop at the end of the path.  
The "Follow" checkbox makes the object rotate to keep a constant heading
as it moves along the curve.</p>

<img src="blender-path-anim-easy.png" width="227" height="142" tex="blender-path-anim-easy.eps" texscale="0.7"/>


<p>In many cases, this is as much control as you need.
But for more control, you can do path animation by using a "Follow Path"
constraint.  To do that, make sure that you know the name of the curve that
you want to use.  Select the object that you want to move along the curve,
and go to the Constraint Properties in the Properties Editor.
Click the "Add Object Constraint" button and select "Follow Path" under the "Relationship"
section of the popup menu. This will add the constraint and give you a set of
controls for configuring it:</p>


<img src="blender-path-anim.png" width="224" height="268" tex="blender-path-anim.eps" texscale="0.7"/>

<np>You will need to use the "Target" menu to select the name of the curve that you want the
object to follow.  To get the object to actually jump onto the curve, you will need to
clear it's Location, not its Origin. (Select the object and use ALT-G, or use the
"Location" command in the "Clear" submenu of the "Object" menu.)</np>

<p>Use the "Forward&nbsp;Axis" setting in the constraint controls to say which axis of the object
points along the curve. You need to check the "Follow Curve" checkbox for that
to actually happen.  Make sure "Up Axis" is different from "Forward Axis,"
or you will get strange behavior. Now, if you leave "Fixed Position" unchecked and click "Animate Path,"
you will get exactly the same kind of path animation that was discussed previously.  If instead,
however, you check "Fixed Position," you will be able to completely control the animation
by animating the "Offset Factor" control, and maybe editing the F-curve for the Offset Factor.
A value of the Offset factor between 0.0 and 1.0
specifies distance traveled along the curve as a fraction of the length of the curve.
Values less than 0.0 or greater than 1.0 correspond to extrapolated positions beyond the curve
or further along the curve if the curve is closed.</p>

<p>For example, insert a keyframe for Offset Factor with value 0.0 at frame&nbsp;0, and 
a keyframe value 2.0 at frame 100.  The object will traverse the entire curve for the first
50 frames, but then continue moving for the next 50, with values for "Offset Factor" that
are greater than&nbsp;1.0.</p>

<p>The nice thing is that you can start and end the animation at any time.
You can choose the interpolation and extrapolation modes.  And you can edit the F-curve
for full control of the animation along the path.  For example, you can vary its speed and even
make it move backwards</p>

<p>Note that path animation is not just for visible objects!  You can move a Camera
or Light along a path.  You can combine path animation with tracking.
For example, set up a spotlight to track an Empty and move
the Empty along a path to tell the spotlight where to point.  Or do the
same thing with a camera.</p>

</subsection>



<subsection title="Rendering an Animation" id="blender.3.6">

<p>There is a command for rendering an animation in Blender's "Render" menu,
but you shouldn't simply jump into using it&mdash;if you do, it will dump several
hundred individual image files with names like 0001.png, 0002.png, &dots;, somewhere
on your hard drive. Before rendering an animation, you should use the Output Properties
in the Property Editor to set up the image size, file format, and output location of the rendered animation.
Note that's it's not possible to render an animation without saving the result, but you
don't get any kind of dialog box when you use the Render Animation command &mdash; it just
automatically uses the settings in the Output Properties.  Here are the relevant properties:
</p>

<img src="blender-render-output.png" width="653" height="376" tex="blender-render-output.eps" texscale="0.85"/>

<np>The Output Properties control rendering of individual images as well as animations.
The "Resolution" section controls the
size of the image that will be produced.  You can specify the
X and Y dimensions, in pixels, and also a percentage; the stated dimensions are
multiplied by the percentage to get the actual image size (presumably
to make it easy to make small size test runs).  The "Frame Range"
duplicates the animation start and end frames from the timeline at the bottom of the Blender window.
Note that the "Frame Step" lets you render just a subset of the
frames.  For example, set it to 2 to render every other frame; again,
this can be used to speed things up for test runs.</np>

<p>Also important is a section labeled "Output" near the bottom of the 
Output Properties, shown on the right in the above image. 
This section is for controlling the output destination and file format of animations.
(It also sets the default file format for single images, but you can also select the 
file type when you save the rendered image.)  When you render an animation, 
you will see each frame being rendered
on the screen.  As each frame is rendered, it is saved to disk.
You have to set the output destination and format <b>before</b>
rendering the animation.</p>

<p>To set the output destination, 
enter a file path in the box just below the word "Output".
If the destination is a directory name ending in a slash, blender will make up the
file name, using frame numbers and an appropriate file extension.
If there is no slash at the end, then the part after the last slash is 
the file name, possibly with an added file extension if needed.</p>

<p>The default format for the output is PNG, which is good for single images
and could also be used for animations.  When you 
use a single-image format for an animation, Blender will save each frame
in a separate file.  The file names will include the frame numbers.
This is something that is often done to allow further processing, but you probably
want to use a video file format such as  AVI&nbsp;JPEG or H.264.
I suggest using "H.264&nbsp;in&nbsp;MP4,"
since it is widely supported and can be used on web pages in almost
all web browsers.  For that, you have to set the file format to 
FFMpeg&nbsp;Video.  This will add an "Encoding" section to the output properties,
and you can select "H.264&nbsp;in&nbsp;MP4" from the menu.
If you write your own web pages, here is an example of the HTML code that you
can include to embed your animation on a web page:</p>

<pre>&lt;video width="640" height="480" controls&gt;
      &lt;source src="myAnimation.mp4" type="video/mp4"&gt;
      &lt;b style="color:red"&gt;Sorry, but your browser can't show this video.&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;</pre>


<p>It can take some time to render an animation, since each frame
must be rendered as a separate image. For experimentation, I suggest
using a short animation, a small image size, and the Eevee renderer.  The
Cycles renderer will generally take much longer.  
You will see each frame as it is being rendered.  
You can abort the rendering with the Escape key.</p>


<break/>

<p>There are a few more controls that affect rendering.  
You can use the "Add" menu to add extra cameras to a scene,
just like you add other objects.
In the Scene Properties, you can select the camera that
is used for rendering images.  When you render an image, the scene is rendered from
the point of view of the camera that is currently selected in the Scene Properties.  
This is useful for making
images and animations that show the same scene from several different points of view.
You can also change the rendering camera by selecting the camera in
the 3D&nbsp;View and hitting Control-Numpad-0.</p>


<p>Finally, I'll note that you can set the clip range, projection type, and other
properties of a camera in the Object Data Properties for the camera.
Like OpenGL, Blender will only render objects that are within a certain
range of distances from the camera.  The limits are given by "Clip Start" and "End"
in the camera properties, with defaults of 0.1 and 100.
If an object is farther from the camera than the camera's
"End" clipping value, or closer than the "Start" clipping value,
then the object is not seen by the camera.
If you have a problem with faraway objects disappearing,
check the camera clipping range.</p>

</subsection>

</section>
