<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../graphicstext.dtd" >

<section title="More on Light and Material" id="blender.4">

<p1>Blender has extensive support for <word term="lighting">light</word>
and <word term="material">materials</word>, and we only scratched the
surface in <localref href="blender.1.4"/>.  In this section, we will
go into a little more depth, but of course this is still only an
introduction.  In particular, we will look at the Shader Editor,
which offers complete control over the design of materials.
</p1>

<subsection title="Lighting" id="blender.4.1">

<p>You can add lighting a scene by adding objects of type light, from 
the "Light" submenu of the "Add" menu.  Note that correct lighting 
effects are only shown in the 3D&nbsp;View
if you set it to use the rendered view style.</p>

<p>When a light object is selected in the 3D&nbsp;View, you can
view and edit its properties in the Light Properties tab of the
Properties Editor, in the lower right corner of the default screen.
You can actually change the basic type of light: Point, Sun, Spot,
or Area.  Every light has a "Color" property, which determines the
color of the light, and a "Power" or "Strength" property, which
determines how bright it is.  By default, lights cast shadows, but
there is a checkbox in the Light Properties that you can turn off
if you want to add light to a scene without adding shadows.
(You can make an object that doesn't cast any shadows at all, by
setting the "Shadow Mode" property of its material to "None" in
the "Settings" section of the object's Material Properites.)</p>

<p>An Area light has a shape and size. Larger area lights produce 
softer (not hard-edged) shadows.  But a Point or Spot light also has a 
size, and you can make it produce soft shadows by increasing
its size.  (A Sun can never make soft shadows.)  For a Spot light,
you can set the angle for the cone of light, under the "Spot Shape"
section of the Light Properties.</p>

<p>Furthermore, you can add <word>emission color</word> to the material
of an object.  For example, there is an "Emission" input in the
default material to set the emission color.  Unlike in OpenGL,
an object that has a non-black emission color does not just
look brighter; it actually emits light that affects other lights
in the scene.</p>

<p>But lighting in Blender is also affected by the background
of the scene.  You can set the background in the World Properties
tab of the Properties Editor.  The default background is a
dark gray color, which adds something like a bit of ambient
light to a scene.  But the implementation in this case is that
the background is actually considered to emit light of the given color.
Note that the background is visible by default in rendered images, but you 
can get a rendering that includes only actual objects in the scene by turning
on the "Transparent" option under the "Film" section of the
Render Properties.</p>

<p>The background color does not have to be constant; it can be given
by a texture.  Usually, you want to use an image texture that wraps nicely
around a sphere like the <sourceref href="webgl/textures/Earth-1024x512.jpg">Earth image</sourceref>
that I have used in several examples in this textbook.  You will want a fairly
large image for a nicely detailed background.  To use such
an image as a background, go to the World Properties, and set the
"Color" to be an Environment Texture.  (Click the yellow dot to the left
of the color input, and select "Environment Texture" from the "Texture" section
of the popup menu.)  Then click the "Open" button to select the image.</p>

<p>With an appropriate background image, it is possible to light a scene entirely
with the background, with no Light objects or emissive objects in the scene.
Here is an example of a rendered scene lit only by a background image:</p>

<img src="blender-cycles-hdr.png" width="576" height="420" tex="blender-cycles-hdr.eps" texscale="0.7"/>

<np>The background image for this scene is a 4096-by-2048 pixel image
from <a href="https://polyhaven.com">polyhaven.com</a>,
a source for fully free <word term="HDR image">HDR</word> images, as well as 3D models and
realistic textures.  (An .hdr image has more detailed color information than the usual
.png or .jpeg.  Depending on the software you have, you might not be able to open the image file
on your computer, but Blender can use it.)  The light for the scene
comes mostly from the bright windows in the background image.</np>

<p>The scene shows a checkerboard-patterned platform with several objects standing on it or
floating over it.  The object on the bottom left is a highly reflective sphere ("Metalic" proprety
set to 1.0 and "Roughness" property set to 0.0 in the Material Properties for the sphere).
It reflects the background, but the sphere does not use an <word term="environment mapping">environment map</word>,
like we did for <word>three.js</word> in <localref href="threejs.3.5"/>; 
the background is part of the scene, and Blender lighting can handle reflections correctly,
even of the background.</p>

<p>The file <sourceref href="Blender-hdri-background-example.zip"/>, which can be
found in the <i>source</i> folder of the web site download of this textbook,
is a compressed archive file that
contains the Blender project that produced this image.  (The project in the archive uses a jpg 
version of the much larger hdr background image file.  This gives a poorer rendered image,
but it makes the file size more reasonable.)</p>

</subsection>

<subsection title="Eevee versus Cycles" id="blender.4.2">

<p>The above image was rendered by the Cycles renderer, one of two realistic
renderers available in Blender.  (You can select the renderer in the
Render Properties tab of the Properties Editor.)  Blender's default 
editor, Eevee, can produce similar, but not identical, images.
And with the default settings, the Eevee image will lack certain essential
features: the lens won't refract light, and objects in the scene won't
show reflections of other objects. </p>

<p>Cycles uses a physically correct <word>global illumination</word>
algorithm called <word>path tracing</word> (see <localref href="advanced.2"/>).
Eevee is a faster renderer that needs to use some tricks to simulate
some effects that happen automatically in Cycles.  Because some of
those tricks can significantly increase the rendering time, they
are not enabled by default.  They can be enabled in the Render Properties
tab of the Propeties editor.  Also, for certain kinds of material,
you need to change some settings in the Materials Properties for
the objects that use those materials.  Note that none of these
properties are even available if you are using Cycles.
Here are the changes you need to make to cover the examples
used in this textbook:</p>

<img src="blender-eevee-settings.png" width="527" height="326" tex="blender-eevee-settings.eps" texscale="0.7"/>

<np>Note, however, that there are some things that will
work in one of the renderers but not in the other.</np>

</subsection>

<subsection title="The Shader Editor" id="blender.4.3">

<p>So far, for configuring materials, we have only looked at using a
"Principled Shader" in the Materials Properties.  And in fact, it's
possible to do all material configuration in the Propreties Editor.
However, as materials become more complex, it's much easier to use
an editor that lets you visualize the relationships among the
various aspects of the configuration.  For that, Blender has
the Shader Editor (sometimes called the "Node Editor" because it lets
you visually manipulate nodes that represent steps in the computation that defines the
material). You can change any area of a Blender window into a Shader
Editor, using the popup menu in a corner of the area.  If you 
click the "Shader" button at the very top of the window, the window
changes to the Shader screen, which has
a Shader Editor at the bottom and a 3D&nbsp;View at the top.
The Shader Editor should show the material nodes for whatever
object is currently selected in the 3D&nbsp;View. 
(But note that there is a selection menu in the top left corner of the Shader Editor that must
be set to "Object" for this to be true.  The menu is there because
the Shader Editor can be used to edit other things besides materials.)
 If the selected
object does not yet have an assigned material, there will be 
a "New" button in the header at the top of the Shader Editor.</p>

<p>The Shader Editor visualizes a material as a network of rectangular
nodes.  A node can have inputs on the left and outputs on the right.
An output of one node can be connected to an input of another node (or to
inputs of several nodes).  The network represents the computation that
is used to create the material, and connections represent data flow 
within that computation. Inputs and outputs are color coded to show
the type of data that they represent: gray for numbers, yellow for colors,
green for shaders, and blue for vectors.  In general, an output should only
be connected to an input of the same color, but there are some exceptions.
For example, if you connect a color output to a numerical input, then the
grayscale equivalent of the color value will be used as the numerical input.
</p>

<p>There must be a "Material Output" node, which represents the final
material that will be applied to the object.  The "Surface" input of the
"Material Output" represents the appearance of the surface of the object.
The "Surface" input must be attached to the output of a node that
computes the material for the surface.  There is also a "Volume" input, which I will not 
discuss at all, and a "Displacement" input which we will look at briefly below.</p>

<p>There is an "Add" menu in the Shader Editor that can be used to add
new nodes.  You can also hit Shift-A, with the mouse over the Shader Editor,
to call up the Add menu.  You can set up a connection between two nodes by dragging
from an output of one node to an input of another node.  You can
delete a connection by clicking the output to which it is connected
and dragging away from the output before releasing the mouse.  Or you
can drag to a different input to change the destination of the data.</p>

<p>Here is an example of a node network for a fairly simple material.
This combination of "Diffuse" and "Glossy" is the sort of thing that 
was often done to make basic materials before the Principled Shader
existed, and it can still be a lot less intimidating.  
</p>

<img src="blender-glossy-and-diffuse.png" width="478" height="287" tex="blender-glossy-and-diffuse.eps" texscale="0.7"/>

<np>To make this material, I started with a New material, and deleted the Principled Shader
that was added by default to a new material, because I wanted 
to use a different shader to compute
the "Surface" input for the "Material Output" node.  Shader nodes can be found in the
"Shader" submenu of the Add menu.  I could have just used a "Diffuse BSDF" shader node,  which would
have produced a fully diffuse color.  Or I could have just used a "Glossy BSDF," which
would have produced a shiny, metal-like material.  But I wanted a mixture of the two
types of color, so I added a "Mix Shader," which can combine the outputs from two
other shaders.  I then added a "Diffuse BSDF" and a "Glossy BSDF" and connected their
outputs to the two inputs of the Mix Shader.  The "Fac," or "Factor," input of the
Mix Shader determines how much of each shader input goes into the mix.  I set it to
0.75, which means that 25% of the Mix Shader output comes from the Diffuse BSDF and
75% comes from the Glossy BSDF.  I also set the colors for the Diffuse and Glossy
shaders (by clicking their color samples next to the word "Color").</np>

<p>To show what the material looks like, I added a picture of a torus that uses 
it to the illustration &mdash; this is <b>not</b> something that would 
be shown in the actual Shader Editor.</p>

<break/>

<p>A numerical input like the "Fac" input of a Mix shader can be set by hand,
or its value can come from another node. If you connect the input to an output
from another node, you can get a value that varies from point-to-point on
a surface.   Here is an example where the degree of mixing between two
colors comes from a texture, giving a color that varies from point to point on
an object.</p>

<img src="blender-color-mix-nodes.png" width="733" height="405" tex="blender-color-mix-nodes.eps" texscale="0.6"/>

<np>I could have done this example using another Mix Shader, but I decided to use the
default Principled Shader and connect its Base Color input to the output from a color
mixer node.  The node that does the color mixing is of type "MixRGB," which can
be found in the "Color" submenu of the "Add" menu.  The colors for the mix are set here
as constant values, but the "Fac" input comes from a Wave Texture node (found in the
"Texture" submenu of the "Add" menu).  With the settings shown for the Wave texture,
this gives a marble-like pattern of color.  I tried connecting the output from the
Wave texture directly to the "Fac" input, but I wanted the bands of red color
in the material to be narrower.  To make that happen, I inserted a
"Math" node &mdash; from the "Converter" submenu of the "Add" menu &mdash; between
the Wave Texture node and the Mix node.  The Math node has a selection menu to
say which mathematical operation it performs on its two inputs.  I selected "Power," so the
math node computes the output from the wave texture raised to the power 5.000.
(I should have used the "Fac" output of the Wave Texture rather than the "Color" output, 
but the Fac output just
gives the grayscale level of the Color output, which is the same thing that you
get when you connect a color output to a numerical input. So the two outputs
are actually equivalent for this example.)</np>

<break/>

<p>In the next example, the base color of the material comes from an image
texture.  In the sample render that is shown in the following illustration,
the texture is applied to a smooth-shaded isosphere.  The texture is
represented by an "Image Texture" node, from the "Texture" submenu of the
Add menu.  We already saw in
<localref href="blender.1.4"/> how to apply a texture to an object.  The problem
here is that the default mapping of the texture to the isosphere isn't
correct, so I needed to add another node to change the mapping.  The
"Vector" input of the Image Texture node sets the 
texture coordinates for mapping. I
added a "Texture Coordinates" node, from the "Input" submenu of the Add menu,
and connected the "Generated" output from the Texture Coordinate node to
the Vector input of the Image Texture node. I also had to change the center
selection menu in the Image Texture node from the default "Flat" to "Sphere."
That gave the correct mapping in this case.</p>

<img src="blender-image-texture-node.png" width="727" height="284" tex="blender-image-texture-node.eps" texscale="0.6"/>

<np>It turns out that the texture would work fine on a UVSphere with no
extra nodes.  The default texture mapping uses the UV texture coordinates
of the object.  A UVSphere comes with textures coordinates that map the texture
once around the sphere, which is what I wanted here.  You could get exactly the
same result by adding a Texture Coordinate node and connecting the UV output from
that node to the Vector input of the Image Texture node.  For the Icosphere,
however, the default UV coordinates were not correct.</np>

<p>The "Generated" output of the Texture Coordinates node means that the
output value is given by the object coordinates of the object
to which the material is applied.  (Generated texture coordinates are discussed in
<localref href="webgl3d.3.2"/>.)  The central select menu in the Image Texture node,
which is set to Sphere in the example, determines an extra function that is applied
to the 3D Vector input, to map it to the 2D coordinate space of the image. 
The default, "Flat," means that the third component of the vector input is simply dropped.</p>

<p>By the way, you might want to apply a <word>texture transformation</word> to the
texture coordinates, to fit the texture better to the object.  (See <localref href="gl1light.3.4"/>.)
For that, you can insert a computation between the Texture Coordinate node and
the Texture Image node.  You can use a "Vector Math" node, from the "Converter" submenu of
the Add menu, to add an offset to the texture coordinates or to multiply them by
scaling factors.  If you want to do both, you can use two Vector Math nodes.
There is also a "Mapping" node in the "Vector" submenu that can apply a combined
scale, rotate, and translate.</p>

<break/>

<p>Next, we look at an example that uses the "Displacement" input of the Material
Output node.  We saw in <localref href="blender.2.5"/> that a Displace constraint
can be used in Blender to do <word>displacement mapping</word>.  It turns out
that you can also do displacement mapping in the Shader Editor, using
a Displacement Node attached to the Displacement input of the Material Output node.
The "Height" input of the Displacement node gives the amount of displacement,
which would ordinarily come from a texture node.</p>

<p>In <localref href="webgl3d.3.4"/>, we looked at <word term="bumpmapping">bump mapping</word>, which 
makes it look as if the orientation of a surface is changing from point to point
by adjusting its <word term="normal vector">normal vectors</word>.
bump mapping is basically the cheap version of displacement mapping.  When you use
displacement in a material, the Eevee renderer will actually do bump mapping.
The Cycles rendered can do either bump mapping or displacement mapping, but it
will do bump mapping by default.  To get Cycles to do actual displacement mapping
based on the material, you have to go to the "Settings" section of the
Material Properties and change the "Displacement" input from "Bump Only"
to "Displacement Only."  But note that you will still see
actual displacement <b>only</b> in a rendered view!</p>

<p>The sample render for my example uses displacement mapping on an icosphere.
You can see that the actual geometry has been modified:</p>

<img src="blender-displacement-node.png" width="566" height="299" tex="blender-displacement-node.eps" texscale="0.7"/>

<p>For displacement mapping to work, the surface must be finely subdivided.
For the icosphere in the example, I used 4 subdivisions when I created it, 
and then I added a Subdivision Surface modifier with three levels of subdivision to 
divide it even more finely.</p>  


<break/>

<p>Transparent materials that refract light, like glass, can be modeled easily
in Blender. The lens in the image at the start of this section was made entirely
in a Principled Shader simply by setting the "Transmission" value to 1.0 and
the "Roughness" value to 0.0.  (I also set the <word>IOR</word> in the shader to
0.5, which is not at all physically realistic.  But I liked how it looked.)
Remember that to see the effect when using the Eevee renderer, you need to
adjust render and material properties as shown in the illustration earlier in this section.
</p>

<p>Note that even though the lens transmits 100% of light, it is not simply invisible, 
since it bends light that passes through it.  Simple
transparency, without bending of light, can be done with <word>alpha blending</word>,
where the alpha component of the color determines the degree of opaqueness.
The Principled Shader has an "Alpha" input that represents the alpha value for
the material color.  Setting the value to zero would make the object completely
invisible.  Setting it to a value between 0.0 and 1.0 makes the object translucent.
(Again, if you want to see the effect in Eevee, you need to change the "Blend Mode"
in the material settings; refer back to the above illustration.)</p>

<p>You can also control transparency using a Transparent Shader in the Shader Editor.
For no good reason, I decided to make a material in which the alpha component
varies from point to point, with the degree of transparency coming from a wave texture.
  In the sample render, the material is used
on a cylinder.  I put an orange inside the cylinder so that you can see the
transparency (so to speak).  You can even see the shadows of the opaque parts on the orange. 
Here is the node setup that I used:</p>

<img src="blender-partial-transparent-nodes.png" width="596" height="311" tex="blender-partial-transparent-nodes.eps" texscale="0.7"/>



</subsection>

</section>
