<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../graphicstext.dtd" >

<section title="HTML Canvas Graphics" id="graphics2d.6">

<p1>Most modern web browsers support a 2D graphics <word>API</word> that can be used
to create images on a web page.  The API is implemented using <word>JavaScript</word>, the client-side programming 
language for the web.  I won't cover the JavaScript language in this section.  To understand the 
material presented here, you don't need to know much about it.  Even if you
know nothing about it at all, you can learn something about its 2D graphics API and
see how it is similar to, and how it differs from, the Java API presented in the
<localref href="graphics2d.5">previous section</localref>.  (For a short introduction
to JavaScript, see <localref href="proglang.3"/> in <localref href="proglang"/>.)</p1>

<subsection title="The 2D Graphics Context" id="graphics2d.6.1">

<p>The visible content of a web page is made up of "elements" such
as headlines and paragraphs.  The content is specified using the <word>HTML</word> language.
A "canvas" is an HTML element. It appears on the page as a blank rectangular area which can
be used as a drawing surface by what I am calling the "<word>HTML canvas</word>" graphics API.
In the source code of a web page, a canvas element is created with code of the form</p>

<pre>&lt;canvas width="800" height="600" id="theCanvas"&gt;&lt;/canvas&gt;</pre>

<np>The <i>width</i> and <i>height</i> give the size of the drawing area, in pixels.  The
<i>id</i> is an identifier that can be used to refer to the canvas in JavaScript.</np>

<p>To draw on a canvas, you need a graphics context.  A graphics context is an object that
contains functions for drawing shapes.  It also contains variables that record the current graphics 
state, including  things like the current drawing color, transform, and font.  Here, I will 
generally use <i>graphics</i> as the name of the variable that refers to the graphics context, 
but the variable name is, of course, up to the programmer.  This graphics context plays the same role in 
the canvas API that a variable of type <classname>Graphics2D</classname> plays in Java.
A typical starting point is
</p>

<pre>canvas = document.getElementById("theCanvas");
graphics = canvas.getContext("2d");
</pre>

<np>The first line gets a reference to the canvas element on the web page, using its <i>id</i>.
The second line creates the graphics context for that canvas element.  (This code will
produce an error in a web browser that doesn't support canvas, so you might add some error
checking such as putting these commands inside a <code>try..catch</code> statement.)</np>

<p>Typically, you will store the canvas graphics context in a global variable
and use the same graphics context throughout your program.  This is in contrast
to Java, where you typically get a new <classname>Graphics2D</classname> context
each time the <i>paintComponent</i>() method is called, and that new context
is in its initial state with default color and stroke
properties and with no applied transform.  When a graphics 
context is global, changes made to the state in one function
call will carry over to subsequent function calls, unless you do something to limit
their effect.  This can actually lead to a fairly common type of bug: For example, 
if you apply a 30-degree rotation in a function, those rotations will <b>accumulate</b>
each time the function is called, unless you do something to undo the previous rotation
before the function is called again.</p>

<p>The rest of this section will be mostly concerned with describing what you can do with
a canvas graphics context.  But here, for the record, is the complete source code for
a very minimal web page that uses canvas graphics:
</p>

<pre>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
&lt;head&gt;
&lt;title&gt;Canvas Graphics&lt;/title&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    let canvas;    // DOM object corresponding to the canvas
    let graphics;  // 2D graphics context for drawing on the canvas
    
    function draw() {
           // draw on the canvas, using the graphics context
        graphics.fillText("Hello World", 10, 20);
    }

    function init() {
        canvas = document.getElementById("theCanvas");
        graphics = canvas.getContext("2d");
        draw();  // draw something on the canvas
    }
    
    window.onload = init;
    
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;
&lt;body&gt;
    &lt;canvas id="theCanvas" width="640" height="480"&gt;&lt;/canvas&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</pre>

<np>For a more complete, though still minimal, example, you can look at the sample page
<sourceref href="canvas2d/GraphicsStarter.html"/>.  (You should look at the page
in a browser, but you should also read the source code.)  This example shows
how to draw some basic shapes using canvas graphics, and you can use it as
a basis for your own experimentation.  There are also three more advanced
"starter" examples:  <sourceref href="canvas2d/GraphicsPlusStarter.html"/> adds
some utility functions for drawing shapes and setting up a coordinate system;
<sourceref href="canvas2d/AnimationStarter.html"/> adds animation and includes
a simple <word>hierarchical modeling</word> example; and
<sourceref href="canvas2d/EventsStarter.html"/> shows how to respond to keyboard
and mouse events.</np>


</subsection>


<subsection title="Shapes" id="graphics2d.6.2">

<p>The default coordinate system on a canvas is the usual: The unit of measure is one pixel;
(0,0) is at the upper left corner; the <i>x</i>-coordinate increases to the right;
and the <i>y</i>-coordinate increases downward.   The range of <i>x</i> and <i>y</i>
values is given by the <i>width</i> and <i>height</i> properties of the <tag>canvas</tag>
element.  The term "pixel" here for the unit of measure is not really correct.  
Probably, I should say something like "one nominal pixel."
The unit of measure is one pixel at typical desktop resolution with no magnification.
If you apply a magnification to a browser window, the unit of measure gets stretched.
And on a high-resolution screen, one unit in the default coordinate system might 
correspond to several actual pixels on the display device.</p>

<p>The canvas API supports only a very limited set of basic shapes. In fact, the
only basic shapes are rectangles and text.  Other shapes must be created as paths.
Shapes can be <word term="stroking a shape">stroked</word> and 
<word term="filling a shape">filled</word>.  That includes text: When you stroke a string of
text, a pen is dragged along the outlines of the characters; when you fill a string,
the insides of the characters are filled.  It only really makes sense to stroke text
when the characters are rather large.  Here are the functions for drawing
rectangles and text, where <i>graphics</i> refers to the object that represents
the graphics context:</p>

<ul>
<li><codedef>graphics.fillRect(x,y,w,h)</codedef> &mdash; draws a filled rectangle with corner
at (<i>x,y</i>), with width <i>w</i> and with height&nbsp;<i>h</i>. If the width or
the height is less than or equal to zero, nothing is drawn.</li>
<li><codedef>graphics.strokeRect(x,y,w,h)</codedef> &mdash; strokes the outline of the same
rectangle.</li>
<li><codedef>graphics.clearRect(x,y,w,h)</codedef> &mdash; clears the rectangle by filling
it with fully transparent pixels, allowing the background of the canvas to show.
The background is determined by the properties of the web page on which the canvas appears.
It might be a background color, an image, or even another canvas.</li>
<li><codedef>graphics.fillText(str,x,y)</codedef> &mdash; fills the characters in the string <i>str</i>.
The left end of the baseline of the string is positioned at the point (<i>x,y</i>).</li>
<li><codedef>graphics.strokeText(str,x,y)</codedef> &mdash; strokes the outlines of the characters 
in the string.</li>
</ul>

<p>A path can be created using functions in the graphics context.  The context keeps track of
a "current path."  In the current version of the API, paths are not represented by objects,
and there is no way to work with more than one path at a time or to keep a copy of a path
for later reuse.  Paths can contain lines, <word term="Bezier curve">Bezier curves</word>, and circular arcs.
Here are the most common functions for working with paths:</p>

<ul>
<li><codedef>graphics.beginPath()</codedef> &mdash; start a new path.  Any previous path is discarded,
and the current path in the graphics context is now empty.  Note that the graphics context
also keeps track of the current point, the last point in the current path.  After calling
<i>graphics.beginPath</i>(), the current point is undefined.</li>
<li><codedef>graphics.moveTo(x,y)</codedef> &mdash; move the current point to (<i>x,y</i>), without
adding anything to the path.  This can be used for the starting point of the path or to
start a new, disconnected segment of the path.</li>
<li><codedef>graphics.lineTo(x,y)</codedef> &mdash; add the line segment
starting at current point and ending at (<i>x,y</i>) to
the path, and move the current point to (<i>x,y</i>).</li>
<li><codedef>graphics.bezierCurveTo(cx1,cy1,c2x,cy2,x,y)</codedef> &mdash; add a cubic Bezier curve to the
path.  The curve starts at
the current point and ends at (<i>x,y</i>).  The points (<i>cx1,cy1</i>) and (<i>cx2,cy2</i>) are 
the two <word term="control point">control points</word> for
the curve.   (Bezier curves and their control points were discussed in 
<localref href="graphics2d.2.3"/>.)</li>
<li><codedef>graphics.quadraticCurveTo(cx,cy,x,y)</codedef> &mdash; adds a quadratic Bezier curve
from the current point to (<i>x,y</i>), with control point (<i>cx,cy</i>).</li>
<li><codedef>graphics.arc(x,y,r,startAngle,endAngle)</codedef> &mdash; adds an arc of the
circle with center (<i>x,y</i>) and radius&nbsp;<i>r</i>.  The next two parameters give the
starting and ending angle of the arc.  They are measured in radians.  The arc extends in the
positive direction from the start angle to the end angle.  (The positive rotation direction is
from the positive x-axis towards the positive y-axis; this is clockwise in the default coordinate
system.)  An optional fifth parameter can be set to <i>true</i> to get an arc that extends in the
negative direction.  After drawing the arc, the current point is at the end of the arc.  If there is a current point before
<i>graphics.arc</i> is called, then before the arc is drawn, a line is added to the path that extends from the
current point to the starting point of the arc.  (Recall that immediately after <i>graphics.beginPath</i>(),
there is no current point.)</li>
<li><codedef>graphics.closePath()</codedef> &mdash; adds to the path a line from the current point
back to the starting point of the current segment of the curve.  (Recall that you start
a new segment of the curve every time you use <i>moveTo</i>.)</li>
</ul>

<np>Creating a curve with these commands does not draw anything.  To get something visible
to appear in the image, you must fill or stroke the path.</np>

<p>The commands <i>graphics.fill</i>() and <i>graphics.stroke</i>() are used to fill
and to stroke the current path.  If you fill a path that has not been closed, the fill
algorithm acts as though a final line segment had been added to close the path.
When you stroke a shape, it's the center of the virtual pen that moves along the path.
So, for high-precision canvas drawing, it's common to
use paths that pass through the centers of pixels rather than through their corners.
For example, to draw a line that extends from the pixel with coordinates (100,200) to
the pixel with coordinates (300,200), you would actually stroke the geometric line
with endpoints (100.5,200.5) and (100.5,300.5).  We should look at some examples.
It takes four steps to draw a line:</p>

<pre>graphics.beginPath();          // start a new path
graphics.moveTo(100.5,200.5);  // starting point of the new path
graphics.lineTo(300.5,200.5);  // add a line to the point (300.5,200.5)
graphics.stroke();             // draw the line</pre>

<np>Remember that the line remains as part of the current path until the
next time you call <i>graphics.beginPath</i>().  Here's how to draw a filled,
regular octagon centered at (200,400) and with radius 100:</np>

<pre>graphics.beginPath();
graphics.moveTo(300,400);
for (let i = 1; i &lt; 8; i++) {
    let angle = (2*Math.PI)/8 * i;
    let x = 200 + 100*Math.cos(angle);
    let y = 400 + 100*Math.sin(angle);
    graphics.lineTo(x,y);
}
graphics.closePath();
graphics.fill();</pre>


<p>The function <i>graphics.arc</i>() can be used to draw a circle, with a start 
angle of 0 and an end angle of <i>2*Math.PI</i>.  Here's a filled circle with radius 
100, centered at 200,300:</p>

<pre>graphics.beginPath();
graphics.arc( 200, 300, 100, 0, 2*Math.PI );
graphics.fill();</pre>

<p>To draw just the outline of the circle, use <i>graphics.stroke</i>()
in place of <i>graphics.fill</i>().  You can apply both operations to the same path.
If you look at the details of <i>graphics.arc</i>(),
you can see how to draw a wedge of a circle:</p>

<pre>graphics.beginPath();
graphics.moveTo(200,300);   // Move current point to center of the circle.
graphics.arc(200,300,100,0,Math.PI/4);  // Arc, plus line from current point.
graphics.lineTo(200,300);  // Line from end of arc back to center of circle.
graphics.fill();  // Fill the wedge.</pre>

<np>There is no way to draw an oval that is not a circle, except by using 
transforms.  We will cover that later in this section.  But JavaScript has
the interesting property that it is possible to add new functions and 
properties to an existing object.  The sample program
<sourceref href="canvas2d/GraphicsPlusStarter.html"/> shows how to
add functions to a graphics context for drawing lines, ovals, and
other shapes that are not built into the API.</np>

</subsection>


<subsection title="Stroke and Fill" id="graphics2d.6.3">

<p>Attributes such as line width that affect the visual appearance of
strokes and fills are stored as properties of the graphics context.
For example, the value of <i>graphics.lineWidth</i> is a number that
represents the width that will be used for strokes.  (The width is 
given in pixels for the default coordinate system, but it is subject 
to transforms.)  You can change the line width by assigning a value
to this property:</p>

<pre>graphics.lineWidth = 2.5;  // Change the current width.</pre>

<np>The change affects subsequent strokes.  You can also read the current
value:</np>

<pre>saveWidth = graphics.lineWidth;  // Save current width.</pre>

<np>The property <i>graphics.lineCap</i> controls the appearance of
the endpoints of a stroke.  It can be set to
"round", "square", or "butt".  The quotation marks are part of the value.  For example,</np>

<pre>graphics.lineCap = "round";</pre>

<np>Similarly, <i>graphics.lineJoin</i> controls
the appearance of the point where one segment of a stroke joins another
segment; its possible values are "round", "bevel", or "miter".  (Line
endpoints and joins were discussed in <localref href="graphics2d.2.1"/>.)</np>

<p>Note that the values for <i>graphics.lineCap</i> and <i>graphics.lineJoin</i>
are strings.  This is a somewhat unusual aspect of the API.  Several other properties
of the graphics context take values that are strings, including the properties that
control the colors used for drawing and the font that is used for drawing
text.</p>

<p>Color is controlled by the values of the properties <i>graphics.fillStyle</i>
and <i>graphics.strokeStyle</i>.  The graphics context maintains separate styles
for filling and for stroking.  A&nbsp;solid color for stroking or filling is specified
as a string.  Valid color strings are ones that can be used in <word>CSS</word>, the language
that is used to specify colors and other style properties of elements on web pages.
Many solid colors can be specified by their names, such as "red", "black", and
"beige".  An <word>RGB color</word> can be specified as a string of the
form "rgb(r,g,b)", where the parentheses contain three numbers in the range
0 to 255 giving the red, green, and blue components of the color.  Hexadecimal color
codes are also supported, in the form "#XXYYZZ" where XX, YY, and ZZ are two-digit
hexadecimal numbers giving the RGB color components.  For example,</p>

<pre>graphics.fillStyle = "rgb(200,200,255)"; // light blue
graphics.strokeStyle = "#0070A0"; // a darker, greenish blue</pre>

<np>The style can actually be more complicated
than a simple solid color:  <word term="gradient">Gradients</word> and 
<word term="pattern fill">patterns</word> are also supported.  As an 
example, a gradient can be created with a series of steps such as</np>

<pre>let lineargradient = graphics.createLinearGradient(420,420,550,200);
lineargradient.addColorStop(0,"red");
lineargradient.addColorStop(0.5,"yellow");
lineargradient.addColorStop(1,"green");
graphics.fillStyle = lineargradient;  // Use a gradient fill!</pre>

<np>The first line creates a linear gradient that will vary in color along
the line segment from the point (420,420) to the point (550,200).
Colors for the gradient are specified by the <i>addColorStop</i> function:
the first parameter gives the fraction of the distance from the initial
point to the final point where that color is applied, and the second is a string
that specifies the color itself.  A color stop at 0 specifies
the color at the initial point; a color stop at 1 specifies the color
at the final point.  Once a gradient has been created, it can be used both
as a fill style and as a stroke style in the graphics context.</np>

<p>Finally, I note that the font that is used for drawing text is the
value of the property <i>graphics.font</i>.  The value is a string
that could be used to specify a font in <word>CSS</word>.
As such, it can be fairly complicated, but the simplest versions
include a font-size (such as <i>20px</i> or <i>150%</i>) and a font-family
(such as <i>serif</i>, <i>sans-serif</i>, <i>monospace</i>, or the name of any font
that is accessible to the web page).
You can add <i>italic</i> or <i>bold</i> or both to the front of the string.
Some examples:
</p>

<pre>graphics.font = "2cm monospace";  // the size is in centimeters
graphics.font = "bold 18px sans-serif";
graphics.font = "italic 150% serif";   // size is 150% of the usual size</pre>

<np>The default is "10px sans-serif," which is usually too small.  Note that text, like all drawing, is
subject to coordinate transforms.  Applying a scaling operation changes the
size of the text, and a negative scaling factor can produce mirror-image text.</np>


</subsection>


<subsection title="Transforms" id="graphics2d.6.4">

<p>A graphics context has three basic functions for modifying the current transform
by scaling, rotation, and translation.  There are also functions that will compose
the current transform with an arbitrary transform and for completely
replacing the current transform:</p>

<ul>
<li><codedef>graphics.scale(sx,sy)</codedef> &mdash; scale by <i>sx</i> in the <i>x</i>-direction
and <i>sy</i> in the <i>y</i>-direction.</li>
<li><codedef>graphics.rotate(angle)</codedef> &mdash; rotate by <i>angle</i> radians about the
origin.  A positive rotation is clockwise in the default coordinate system.</li>
<li><codedef>graphics.translate(tx,ty)</codedef> &mdash; translate by <i>tx</i> in the <i>x</i>-direction
and <i>ty</i> in the <i>y</i>-direction.</li>
<li><codedef>graphics.transform(a,b,c,d,e,f)</codedef> &mdash; apply the <word>affine transform</word>
<code>x1 = a*x + c*y + e</code>, and <code>y1 = b*x + d*y + f</code>.</li>
<li><codedef>graphics.setTransform(a,b,c,d,e,f)</codedef> &mdash; discard the current transformation,
and set the current transformation to be <code>x1 = a*x + c*y + e</code>, and
<code>y1 = b*x + d*y + f</code>.</li>
</ul>

<np>Note that there is no <word>shear transform</word>, but you can apply a shear as
a general transform.  For example, for a horizontal shear with shear factor&nbsp;0.5, use</np>

<pre>graphics.transform(1, 0, 0.5, 1, 0, 0)</pre>

<p>To implement hierarchical modeling, as discussed in <localref href="graphics2d.4"/>, 
you need to be able to save
the current transformation so that you can restore it later.  Unfortunately,
no way is provided to read the current transformation from a canvas graphics
context.  However, the graphics context itself keeps a stack of transformations
and provides methods for pushing and popping the current transformation.  In fact,
these methods do more than save and restore the current transformation.  They actually
save and restore almost the entire state of the graphics context, including properties
such as current colors, line width, and font (but not the current path):</p>


<ul>
<li><codedef>graphics.save()</codedef> &mdash; push a copy of the current state of the graphics
context, including the current transformation, onto the stack.</li>
<li><codedef>graphics.restore()</codedef> &mdash; remove the top item from the stack, containing
a saved state of the graphics context, and restore the graphics context to that state.</li>
</ul>

<p>Using these methods, the basic setup for drawing an object with a modeling
transform becomes:</p>

<pre>graphics.save();          // save a copy of the current state
graphics.translate(a,b);  // apply modeling transformations
graphics.rotate(r);     
graphics.scale(sx,sy);
   .
   .  // Draw the object!
   .
graphics.restore();       // restore the saved state</pre>

<np>Note that if drawing the object includes any changes to attributes
such as drawing color, those changes will be also undone by the call to <i>graphics.restore</i>().
In hierarchical graphics, this is usually what you want, and it eliminates the
need to have extra statements for saving and restoring things like color.</np>

<p>To draw a hierarchical model, you need to traverse a <word>scene graph</word>, either
procedurally or as a data structure.  It's pretty much the same as in Java.
In fact, you should see that the basic concepts that you learned about
transformations and modeling carry over to the canvas graphics API.  Those
concepts apply very widely and even carry over to 3D graphics APIs, with
just a little added complexity.  The sample web page
<sourceref href="canvas2d/HierarchicalModel2D.html"/>
implements hierarchical modeling using the 2D canvas API.</p>

<break/>

<p>Now that we know how to do transformations, we can see how to draw an oval
using the canvas API.  Suppose that we want an oval with center at (<i>x,y</i>),
with horizontal radius <i>r1</i> and with vertical radius <i>r2</i>.
The idea is to draw a circle of radius 1 with center at (0,0), then transform
it.  The circle needs to be scaled by a factor of <i>r1</i> horizontally and
<i>r2</i> vertically.  It should then be translated to move its center from
(0,0) to (<i>x,y</i>).  We can use <i>graphics.save</i>() and <i>graphics.restore</i>()
to make sure that the transformations only affect the circle.  Recalling that
the order of transforms in the code is the opposite of the order in which they
are applied to objects, this becomes:</p>

<pre>graphics.save();
graphics.translate( x, y );
graphics.scale( r1, r2 );
graphics.beginPath();
graphics.arc( 0, 0, 1, 0, Math.PI );  // a circle of radius 1
graphics.restore();
graphics.stroke();</pre>

<np>Note that the current path is <b>not</b> affected by the
calls to <i>graphics.save</i>() and <i>graphics.restore</i>().  So,
in the example, the oval-shaped path is not discarded when
<i>graphics.restore</i>() is called. When <i>graphics.stroke</i>() is
called at the end, it is the oval-shaped path that is stroked.  On the
other hand, the line width that is used for the stroke is not affected
by the scale transform that was applied to the oval.  Note that if
the order of the last two commands were reversed, then the line width
would be subject to the scaling.</np>

<p>There is an interesting point here about transforms and paths.  In the HTML canvas
API, the points that are used to create a path are transformed by the
current transformation before they are saved.  That is, they are saved
in pixel coordinates.  Later, when the path is stroked or filled, the current
transform has no effect on the path (although it can affect,
for example, the line width when the path is stroked).  In particular,
you can't make a path and then apply different transformations.  For example,
you can't make an oval-shaped path, and then use it to draw several ovals
in different positions.  Every time you draw the oval, it will be in the
same place, even if different translation transforms are applied to
the graphics context.</p>

<p>The situation is different in Java, where the coordinates that are stored
in the path are the actual numbers that are used to specify the path,
that is, the <word>object coordinates</word>.  When the path is stroked or
filled, the transformation that is in effect at that time is applied
to the path.  The path can be reused many times
to draw copies with different transformations.  This comment is offered as an
example of how APIs that look very similar can have subtle differences.</p>

</subsection>


<subsection title="Auxiliary Canvases" id="graphics2d.6.5">

<p>In <localref href="graphics2d.5.5"/>, we looked at the sample program
<sourceref href="java2d/JavaPixelManipulation.java"/>, which uses a
<classname>BufferedImage</classname> both to implement an
<word>off-screen canvas</word> and to allow direct manipulation of
the colors of individual pixels.  The same ideas can be applied
in HTML canvas graphics, although the way it's done is a little different.
The sample web application <sourceref href="canvas2d/SimplePaintProgram.html"/>
does pretty much the same thing as the Java program (except for the
image filters).</p>

<demo src="c2/SimplePaintDemo.html" width="600" height="425"><p><web>Here
is</web><tex>The on-line version of this section has</tex> a live demo 
version of the program that has the same functionality.
You can try it out to see how the various drawing tools work.  Don't
forget to try the "Smudge" tool! (It has to be applied to shapes that
you have already drawn.)</p></demo>


<p>For JavaScript, a web page is represented as a data structure, defined
by a standard called the <word>DOM</word>, or Document Object model.
For an off-screen canvas, we can use a <tag>canvas</tag> that is not part of
that data structure and therefore is not part of the page.
In JavaScript, a <tag>canvas</tag>
can be created with the function call <i>document.createElement</i>("canvas").
There is a way to add this kind of dynamically created canvas to the
DOM for the web page, but it can be used as an off-screen canvas without doing so.
To use it, you have to set its width and height properties, and you
need a graphics context for drawing on it.  Here, for example, is
some code that creates a 640-by-480 canvas, gets a graphics
context for the canvas, and fills the whole canvas with white:</p>


<pre>OSC = document.createElement("canvas");  // off-screen canvas

OSC.width = 640;    // Size of OSC must be set explicitly.
OSC.height = 480;

OSG = OSC.getContext("2d");  // Graphics context for drawing on OSC.

OSG.fillStyle = "white";  // Use the context to fill OSC with white.
OSG.fillRect(0,0,OSC.width,OSC.height);</pre>

<np>The sample program lets the user drag the mouse on the canvas to
draw some shapes. The off-screen canvas holds the official copy of
the picture, but it is not seen by the user.  There is also an
on-screen canvas that the user sees.  The off-screen canvas is copied 
to the on-screen canvas whenever the picture is modified.  
While the user is dragging the mouse to
draw a line, oval, or rectangle, the new shape is actually
drawn on-screen, over the contents of the off-screen canvas. It is
only added to the off-screen canvas when the user finishes the
drag operation. For the other tools, changes are made directly
to the off-screen canvas, and the result is then copied to the
screen.  This is an exact imitation of the Java program.</np>

<p>(The demo version <web>shown</web><tex>mentioned</tex> above 
actually uses a somewhat different technique to accomplish the
same thing.  It uses two on-screen canvases, one located exactly
on top of the other.  The lower canvas holds the actual image.
The upper canvas is completely transparent, except when the
user is drawing a line, oval, or rectangle.  While the user
is dragging the mouse to draw such a shape, the new shape
is drawn on the upper canvas, where it hides the part of
the lower canvas that is beneath the shape.  When the user
releases the mouse, the shape is added to the lower canvas
and the upper canvas is cleared to make it completely transparent
again.  Again, the other tools operate directly on the lower
canvas.)</p>


</subsection>


<subsection title="Pixel Manipulation" id="graphics2d.6.6">

<p>The "Smudge" tool in the <sourceref href="canvas2d/SimplePaintProgram.html">sample program</sourceref> 
and demo is implemented by computing with the color component values of pixels in the image.
The implementation requires some way to read the colors of pixels in a canvas.  That can be 
done with the function <i>graphics.getPixelData</i>(<i>x,y,w,h</i>), where <i>graphics</i> is a 2D graphics
context for the canvas.  The function reads the colors of a rectangle of pixels, where (<i>x,y</i>) is
the upper left corner of the rectangle, <i>w</i> is its width, and <i>h</i> is its height.  The
parameters are always expressed in pixel coordinates.  Consider, for example</p>

<pre>colors = graphics.getImageData(0,0,20,10)</pre>

<np>This returns the color data for a 20-by-10 rectangle in the upper left corner of the canvas.
The return value, <i>colors</i>, is an object with properties <i>colors.width</i>,
<i>colors.height</i>, and <i>colors.data</i>.  The <i>width</i> and <i>height</i> give the number of
rows and columns of pixels in the returned data.  (According to the documentation, on a high-resolution 
screen, they might not be the same as the width and height in the function call.  The data can be 
for real, physical pixels on the display device, not the "nominal" pixels that are used in the pixel 
coordinate system on the canvas. There might be several device pixels for each nominal pixel.
I'm not sure whether this can really happen in practice.)</np>

<p>The value of <i>colors.data</i> is an array, with four array elements for each pixel.  The four
elements contain the red, blue, green, and alpha color components of the pixel, given as integers
in the range 0 to 255.  For a pixel that lies outside the canvas, the four component values will
all be zero.  The array is a value of type <i>Uint8ClampedArray</i> whose elements are
8-bit unsigned integers limited to the range 0 to 255.  This is one of JavaScript's
<newword>typed array</newword> datatypes, which can only hold values of a specific numerical type.
As an example, suppose that you just want to read the RGB color of one pixel, at coordinates (<i>x,y</i>).
You can set</p>

<pre>pixel = graphics.getImageData(x,y,1,1);</pre>

<np>Then the RGB color components for the pixel are R = <i>pixel.data</i>[0],
G = <i>pixel.data</i>[1], and B = <i>pixel.data</i>[2].</np>

<p>The function <i>graphics.putImageData</i>(<i>imageData</i>,<i>x</i>,<i>y</i>) is
used to copy the colors from an image data object into a canvas, placing it into
a rectangle in the canvas with upper left corner at (<i>x,y</i>).  The <i>imageData</i>
object can be one that was returned by a call to <i>graphics.getImageData</i>, possibly
with its color data modified.  Or you can create a blank image data object by
calling <i>graphics.createImageData</i>(<i>w,h</i>) and fill it with data.</p>

<p>Let's consider the "Smudge" tool in the sample program. When the user clicks the
mouse with this tool, I use <i>OSG.getImageData</i> to get the color data from a 
9-by-9 square of pixels surrounding the mouse location.  <i>OSG</i> is the graphics
context for the canvas that contains the image.  Since I want to do real-number
arithmetic with color values, I copy the color components into another typed array,
one of type <i>Float32Array</i>, which can hold 32-bit floating point numbers.
Here is the function that I call to do this:</p>

<pre>function grabSmudgeData(x, y) {  // (x,y) gives mouse location
    let colors = OSG.getImageData(x-5,y-5,9,9);
    if (smudgeColorArray == null) {
          // Make image data &amp; array the first time this function is called.
        smudgeImageData = OSG.createImageData(9,9);
        smudgeColorArray = new Float32Array(colors.data.length);
     }
     for (let i = 0; i &lt; colors.data.length; i++) {
           // Copy the color component data into the Float32Array.
        smudgeColorArray[i] = colors.data[i];
    }
}</pre>

<np>The floating point array, <i>smudgeColorArray</i>, will be used for computing new
color values for the image as the mouse moves.  The color values
from this array will be copied into the image data object, <i>smudgeImageData</i>, 
which will then be used to put the color values into the image.  This is done in
another function, which is called for each point that is visited as the user
drags the Smudge tool over the canvas:</np>

<pre>function swapSmudgeData(x, y) { // (x,y) is new mouse location
    let colors = OSG.getImageData(x-5,y-5,9,9);  // get color data from image
    for (let i = 0; i &lt; smudgeColorArray.length; i += 4) {
        // The color data for one pixel is in the next four array locations.
        if (smudgeColorArray[i+3] &amp;&amp; colors.data[i+3]) {
              // alpha-components are non-zero; both pixels are in the canvas;
              // (getImageData() gets 0 for the alpha value at pixel coordinates
              // that are not actually part of the canvas).
            for (let j = i; j &lt; i+3; j++) { // compute new RGB values
                let newSmudge = smudgeColorArray[j]*0.8 + colors.data[j]*0.2;
                let newImage  = smudgeColorArray[j]*0.2 + colors.data[j]*0.8;
                smudgeImageData.data[j] = newImage;
                smudgeColorArray[j] = newSmudge;
            }
            smudgeImageData.data[i+3] = 255;  // alpha component
        }
        else {
              // one of the alpha components is zero; set the output
              // color to all zeros, "transparent black", which will have
              // no effect on the color of the pixel in the canvas.
            for (let j = i; j &lt;= i+3; j++) {
                smudgeImageData.data[j] = 0; 
            }
        }
    }
    OSG.putImageData(smudgeImageData,x-5,y-5); // copy new colors into canvas
}</pre>

<np>In this function, a new color is computed for each pixel in a 9-by-9 square of
pixels around the mouse location.  The color is replaced by a weighted average
of the current color of the pixel and the color of the corresponding pixel in the
<i>smudgeColorArray</i>.  At the same time, the color in <i>smudgeColorArray</i>
is replaced by a similar weighted average.</np>

<p>It would be worthwhile to try to understand this example to see how pixel-by-pixel
processing of color data can be done.  See the 
<sourceref href="canvas2d/SimplePaintProgram.html">source code</sourceref>
of the example for more details.</p>

</subsection>



<subsection title="Images" id="graphics2d.6.7">

<p>For another example of pixel manipulation, we can look at 
image filters that modify an image by replacing the color of each pixel with
a weighted average of the color of that pixel and the 8 pixels that
surround it. Depending on the weighting factors that are used, the
result can be as simple as a slightly blurred version of the image, or
it can be something more interesting.</p>

<demo src="c2/image-filters.html" width="600" height="310"><p><web>Here is 
an</web><tex>The on-line version of this section includes</tex> an
interactive demo that lets you apply several different image filters to
a variety of images<tex>.</tex><web>:</web></p></demo>

<p>The filtering operation in the demo uses the image data functions
<i>getImageData</i>, <i>createImageData</i>, and <i>putImageData</i>
that were discussed above.  Color data from the entire image is obtained
with a call to <i>getImageData</i>.  The results of the averaging 
computation are placed in a new image data object, and the resulting
image data is copied back to the image using <i>putImageData</i>.</p>

<p>The remaining question is, where do the original images come
from, and how do they get onto the canvas in the first place?
An image on a web page is specified by an element in the web page
source such as</p>

<pre>&lt;img src="pic.jpg" width="400" height="300" id="mypic"&gt;</pre>
 
 <np>The <i>src</i> attribute specifies the URL from which the image is
loaded.  The optional <i>id</i> can be used to reference the image
in JavaScript.  In the script,</np>

<pre>image = document.getElementById("mypic");</pre>

<np>gets a reference to the object that represents the image in the
document structure.  Once you have such an object, you can use it to
draw the image on a canvas.  If <i>graphics</i> is a graphics context
for the canvas, then</np>

<pre>graphics.drawImage(image, x, y);</pre>

<np>draws the image with its upper left corner at (<i>x,y</i>).  Both
the point (<i>x,y</i>) and the image itself are transformed by any
transformation in effect in the graphics context.  This will draw
the image using its natural width and height (scaled by the transformation,
if any).  You can also specify the width and height of the rectangle
in which the image is drawn:</np>

<pre>graphics.drawImage(image, x, y, width, height);</pre>

<np>With this version of <i>drawImage</i>, the image is scaled to fit
the specified rectangle.</np>

<p>Now, suppose that the image you want to draw onto the canvas is not
part of the web page?  In that case, it is possible to load the image dynamically.
This is much like making an off-screen canvas, but you are making
an "off-screen image."  Use the <i>document</i> object to create an
<i>img</i> element:</p>

<pre>newImage = document.createElement("img");</pre>

<np>An <i>img</i> element needs a <i>src</i> attribute that
specifies the URL from which it is to be loaded.  For example,</np>

<pre>newImage.src = "pic2.jpg";</pre>

<np>As soon as you assign a value to the <i>src</i> attribute, the browser
starts loading the image.  The loading is done asynchronously; that is,
the computer continues to execute the script without waiting for the
load to complete.  This means that you can't simply draw the image on
the line after the above assignment statement:  The image is very likely
not done loading at that time.  You want to draw the image after it has
finished loading.  For that to happen, you need to assign a function to the image's <i>onload</i>
property before setting the <i>src</i>. That function will
be called when the image has been fully loaded.  Putting this together, here is a simple 
JavaScript function for loading an image from a specified URL and drawing it on a canvas
after it has loaded:</np>

<pre>function loadAndDraw( imageURL, x, y ) {
    let image = document.createElement("img");
    image.onload = doneLoading;
    image.src = imageURL;
    function doneLoading() {
        graphics.drawImage(image, x, y);
    }
}</pre>

<np>A similar technique is used to load the images in the filter demo.</np>

<p>There is one last mystery to clear up.  When discussing the use of an off-screen
canvas in the <i>SimplePaintProgram</i> example earlier in this section, I noted that
the contents of the off-screen canvas have to be copied to the main canvas,
but I didn't say how that can be done.  In fact, it is done using <i>drawImage</i>.
In addition to drawing an image onto a canvas, <i>drawImage</i> can be used to draw the contents of
one canvas into another canvas.  In the sample program, the command</p>

<pre>graphics.drawImage( OSC, 0, 0 );</pre>

<np>is used to draw the off-screen canvas to the main canvas.  Here, <i>graphics</i>
is a graphics context for drawing on the main canvas, and <i>OSC</i> is the object
that represents the off-screen canvas.</np>

</subsection>



</section>
