<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../graphicstext.dtd" >

<section title="Introduction to Lighting" id="gl1light.1">

<p1><word term="lighting">Lighting</word> is one of the most important considerations for
realistic 3D graphics.  The goal is to simulate light sources
and the way that the light that they emit interacts with
objects in the scene.  Lighting calculations are disabled by
default in OpenGL.  This means that when OpenGL applies color to 
a vertex, it simply uses the current color value as set by the
one of the functions <i>glColor*</i>.  In order to get OpenGL
to do lighting calculations, you need to enable lighting by
calling <i>glEnable</i>(<i>GL_LIGHTING</i>).  If that's all you
do, you will find that your objects are all completely black.
If you want to see them, you have to turn on some lights.</p1>

<p>The properties of a surface that determine how it interacts 
light are referred to as the <newword>material</newword> of the surface.
A surface can have several different material properties.
Before we study the OpenGL <word>API</word> for
light and material, there are a few general ideas about
light and material properties that you need to understand.  Those ideas are
introduced in this section.  We postpone discussion of how lighting is actually done in 
OpenGL 1.1 until the <localref href="gl1light.2">next section</localref>.</p>

<subsection title="Light and Material" id="gl1light.1.1">

<p>When light strikes a surface, some of it will be reflected.  Exactly
how it reflects depends in a complicated way on the nature of the
surface, what I am calling the material properties of the surface.
In OpenGL&nbsp;1.1, the complexity
is approximated&mdash;very crudely&mdash;by two general types of reflection, 
<newword>specular reflection</newword> and <newword>diffuse reflection</newword>.
These two types of reflection are important in other 3D graphics systems as well.
(But see <localref href="advanced.2"/> for a more modern view of materials.)
</p>

<img src="diffuse-vs-specular.png" width="538" height="247" tex="diffuse-vs-specular.eps" texscale="0.6"/>

<p>In perfect specular ("mirror-like") reflection, an incoming ray of light is reflected
from the surface intact.  The reflected ray makes the same angle with the
surface as the incoming ray.  A viewer can see the reflected ray only
if the viewer is in exactly the right position, somewhere along the path of the
reflected ray.  Even if the entire surface is illuminated by the light
source, the viewer will only see the reflection of the light source at
those points on the surface where the geometry is right.  Such reflections
are referred to as <newword term="specular highlight">specular highlights</newword>.  In practice,
we think of a ray of light as being reflected not as a single perfect
ray, but as a cone of light, which can be more or less narrow.</p>

<img src="reflection-cone.png" width="442" height="185" tex="reflection-cone.eps" texscale="0.6"/>

<np>Specular reflection from a very shiny surface produces very narrow cones of
reflected light; specular highlights on such a material are small and sharp.
A duller surface will produce wider cones of reflected light and bigger,
fuzzier specular highlights.  In OpenGL, the material property that
determines the size and sharpness of specular highlights is called
<newword>shininess</newword>.  Shininess in OpenGL is a number in the range
0 to 128.  As the number increases, specular highlights get smaller.
This image shows eight spheres that differ only in the value of the
shininess material property:</np>

<img src="specular_hilites.png" width="570" height="85" tex="specular_hilites.eps" texscale="0.75"/>

<np>For the sphere on the left, the shininess is 0, which leads to an ugly specular "highlight"
that almost covers an entire hemisphere.  Going from left to right, the shininess increases by
16 from one sphere to the next.</np>


<p>In pure diffuse reflection, an incoming ray of light is scattered in
all directions equally.  A viewer would see reflected light from
all points on the surface.  If the incoming light arrives in parallel rays
that evenly illuminate the surface, then the surface would appear to the viewer
to be evenly illuminated.  (If different rays strike the surface at different angles, as they
would if they come from a nearby lamp or if the surface is curved, then the amount 
of illumination at a point depends on the angle at which the ray hits the surface
at that point, but not on the angle of the line from that point to the user.)</p>

<p>When light strikes a surface, some of the light can be
absorbed, some can be reflected diffusely, and some can be reflected
specularly.  The amount of reflection can be different for different wavelengths.
The degree to which a material reflects light of various
wavelengths is what constitutes the color of the material.  We now see
that a material can have two different colors&mdash;a <newword>diffuse color</newword> that tells 
how the material reflects light diffusely, and a <newword>specular color</newword> that tells how it reflects
light specularly.  The diffuse color is the basic color of the
object.  The specular color determines the color of specular highlights.
The diffuse and specular colors can be the same; for example, this is often true
for metallic surfaces.  Or they can be different; for example, a plastic surface
will often have white specular highlights no matter what the diffuse color.</p>

<demo src="c4/materials-demo.html" width="640" height="590"><p><web>here is a demo that
lets you experiment with the material properties that we have discussed so far.  Read the
help text in the demo for more information.</web><tex>(The demo <demoref href="c4/materials-demo.html"/>
in the on-line version of this section lets the user experiment with the material properties 
that we have discussed so far.)</tex></p></demo>

<break/>

<p>OpenGL goes even further.  In fact, there are two more colors
associated with a material.  The third color is the
<newword>ambient color</newword> of the material, which tells how the surface
reflects <newword>ambient light</newword>.  Ambient light refers
to a general level of illumination that does not come directly from
a light source.  It consists of light that has been reflected and
re-reflected so many times that it is no longer coming from any 
particular direction.  Ambient light is why shadows are not absolutely
black.  In fact, ambient light is only a crude approximation for the
reality of multiply reflected light, but it is better than ignoring
multiple reflections entirely.  The ambient color of a material 
determines how it will reflect various wavelengths of ambient light.
Ambient color is generally set to be the same as the diffuse color.</p>

<p>The fourth color associated with a material is an <newword>emission color</newword>,
which is not really a color in the same sense as the first three color properties.
That is, it has nothing to do with how the surface reflects light.
The emission color is color that does not come
from any external source, and therefore seems to be emitted by the
material itself.  This does not mean that the object is giving off
light that will illuminate other objects, but it does mean that
the object can be seen even if there is no source of light (not
even ambient light).  In the presence of light, the object will
be brighter than can be accounted for by the light that illuminates
it, and in that sense it appears to glow.  The emission color
is usually black; that is, the object has no emission at all.</p>

<p>Each of the four material color properties is specified in terms of three numbers
giving the <word term="RGB color">RGB</word> (red, green, and blue) components of the color.
Real light can contain an infinite number of different wavelengths.
An RGB color is made up of just three components, but the nature
of human color vision makes this a pretty good approximation for most purposes.
(See <localref href="graphics2d.1.4"/>.)  Material colors can also have
<word term="alpha color component">alpha components</word>, but the only alpha
component that is ever used in OpenGL is the one for the diffuse material color.</p>


<p>In the case of the red, blue, and green components of the
ambient, diffuse, or specular color,  the term "color" really
means reflectivity.  That is, the red component of a color gives the
proportion of red light hitting the surface that is reflected by that
surface, and similarly for green and blue.   There are three different
types of reflective color because there are three different types
of light in OpenGL, and a material can have a different 
reflectivity for each type of light.</p>

</subsection>



<subsection title="Light Properties" id="gl1light.1.2">

<p>Leaving aside ambient light, the light in an environment comes from a light
source such as a lamp or the sun.  In fact, a lamp and the sun are examples of
two essentially different kinds of light source: a <newword>point light</newword>
and a <newword>directional light</newword>.  A point light source is located at
a point in 3D space, and it emits light in all directions from that point.
For a directional light, all the light comes from the same direction, so that
the rays of light are parallel.  The sun is considered to be a directional
light source since it is so far away that light rays from the sun
are essentially parallel when they get to the Earth .</p>

<img src="point-vs-directional-light.png" width="402" height="205" tex="point-vs-directional-light.eps" texscale="0.6"/>

<p>A light can have color.  In fact, in OpenGL, each light source has three colors: an
ambient color, a diffuse color, and a specular color.
Just as the color of a material is more properly referred
to as reflectivity, color of a light is more properly referred to as 
<newword term="intensity of a light source">intensity</newword>
or energy.  More exactly, color refers to how the light's energy is
distributed among different wavelengths.  Real light can
contain an infinite number of different wavelengths; when the wavelengths are
separated, you get a spectrum or rainbow containing a continuum of colors.
Light as it is usually modeled on a computer contains only the three basic colors,
red, green, and blue.  So, just like material color, light color is specified by 
giving three numbers representing the red, green, and blue intensities of the
light.</p>

<p>The diffuse intensity of a light is the aspect of the light that interacts with
diffuse material color, and the specular intensity of a light is what interacts
with specular material color.  It is common for the diffuse and specular light intensities
to be the same.</p>

<p>The ambient intensity of a light works a little differently.  Recall that
ambient light is light that is not directly traceable to any light source.
Still, it has to come from somewhere and we can imagine that turning on
a light should increase the general level of ambient light in the environment.
The ambient intensity of a light in OpenGL is added to the general level of
ambient light.  (There can also be global ambient light, which is not associated
with any of the light sources in the scene.)  Ambient light interacts with the ambient color of
a material, and this interaction has no dependence on the position of the
light sources or viewer.  So, a light doesn't have to shine on an object for the object's
ambient color to be affected by the light source; the light source just has
to be turned on. </p>

<p>I should emphasize again that this is all just an approximation, and in this
case not one that has a basis in the physics of the real world.  Real light sources
do not have separate ambient, diffuse, and specular colors, and many computer
graphics systems model light sources using just one color.</p>

</subsection>



<subsection title="Normal Vectors" id="gl1light.1.3">

<p>The visual effect of a light shining on a surface depends on the properties of the surface
and of the light.  But it also depends to a great extent on the angle at which the light
strikes the surface.  The angle is essential to specular reflection and also affects diffuse reflection.
That's why a curved, lit surface looks different at different points,
even if its surface is a uniform color.  To calculate this angle, OpenGL needs to know the direction in
which the surface is facing.  That direction is specified by a <word>vector</word>
that is perpendicular to the surface.
Another word for "perpendicular" is "normal," and a non-zero vector that is perpendicular to a surface
at a given point is called a <newword>normal vector</newword> to that surface.  When used in lighting
calculations, a normal vector must have length equal to one.  A normal vector of length one
is called a <newword>unit normal</newword>.  For proper lighting calculations in OpenGL,
a unit normal must be specified for each vertex.  However, given any normal vector,
it is possible to calculate a unit normal from it by dividing the vector by its length.
(See <localref href="gl1geom.5"/> for a discussion of vectors and their lengths.)</p>

<p>Since a surface can be curved, it can face different directions at different points.
So, a normal vector is associated with a particular point on a surface.  In OpenGL,
normal vectors are actually assigned only to the vertices of a 
<word term="geometric primitive">primitive</word>. The
normal vectors at the vertices of a primitive are used to do lighting calculations
for the entire primitive.</p>

<p>Note in particular that you can assign different normal vectors at each vertex of
a polygon.
Now, you might be asking yourself, "Don't all the normal vectors to a polygon point in
the same direction?" After all, a polygon is flat; the perpendicular direction to the polygon
doesn't change from point to point.  This is true, and if your objective is to display a
<word term="polyhedron">polyhedral</word> object whose sides are flat polygons, 
then in fact, all the normals of each of
those polygons should point in the same direction.  On the other hand, polyhedra are often used
to approximate curved surfaces such as spheres.  If your real objective
is to make something that looks like a curved surface, then you want to use normal vectors
that are perpendicular to the actual surface, not to the polyhedron that approximates it.
Take a look at this example:</p>

<img src="flat-vs-smooth-2.png" width="297" height="244" tex="flat-vs-smooth-2.eps" texscale="0.75"/>


<np>The two objects in this picture are made up of bands of rectangles.  The two objects have
exactly the same geometry, yet they look quite different.  This is because different
normal vectors are used in each case.  For the top object, the band of rectangles is supposed
to approximate a smooth surface.  The vertices of the rectangles
are points on that surface, and I really didn't want to see the rectangles at all&mdash;I wanted
to see the curved surface, or at least a good approximation.  So for the top object, 
when I specified the normal vector at each of the vertices, I used
a vector that is perpendicular to the surface rather than one perpendicular to the rectangle.
For the object on the bottom, on the other hand,
I was thinking of an object that really <b>is</b> a band of rectangles, and I used normal vectors
that were actually perpendicular to the rectangles.  Here's a two-dimensional illustration that shows the
normal vectors that were used for the two pictures:</np>

<img src="flat-vs-smooth.png" width="396" height="289" tex="flat-vs-smooth.eps" texscale="0.6"/>

<np>The thick blue lines represent the rectangles, as seen edge-on from above.
The arrows represent the normal vectors.  Each rectangle has two normals, one at each endpoint.
Each vertex is part of two rectangles, and so two normal vectors are specified at each vertex.
</np>

<p>In the bottom half of the illustration, two rectangles that meet at a point have different
normal vectors at that point.  The normal vectors for a rectangle are actually perpendicular to the rectangle.
There is an abrupt change in direction as you move from one rectangle to the next, so where one rectangle
meets the next, the normal vectors to the two rectangles are different.  The visual effect on
the rendered image is an abrupt change in shading that is perceived as a corner or edge between the
two rectangles.</p>

<p>In the top half, on the other hand, the vectors are perpendicular to a curved surface that 
passes through the endpoints of the rectangles.  When two rectangles share a vertex, 
they also share the same normal at that vertex.  Visually, this eliminates the abrupt 
change in shading, resulting in something that looks more like a smoothly curving surface.</p>

<demo src="c4/smooth-vs-flat.html" width="630" height="380"><p>The two ways of assigning normal
vectors are called <newword>flat shading</newword> and <newword>smooth shading</newword>.
Flat shading makes a surface look
like it is made of flat sides or facets.  Smooth shading makes it look more like a smooth
surface.  <web>This demo will help you to understand these concepts.</web><tex>The
on-line demo <demoref href="c4/smooth-vs-flat.html"/> can help you to understand the difference.</tex>
It shows a <word>polygonal mesh</word> being used to approximate a sphere, with your choice of
smooth or flat shading.<web>  Use the sliders to control the number of polygons in the mesh.</web></p>
</demo>

<p>The upshot of all this is that you get to make up whatever normal vectors suit your purpose.
A normal vector at a vertex is whatever you say it is,
and it does not have to be literally perpendicular to the polygon.  The normal vector that you choose
should depend on the object that you are trying to model.</p>

<p>There is one other issue in choosing normal vectors:  There are always two possible unit normal vectors
at a point on a surface, pointing in opposite directions.  A polygon in 3D has two faces, facing in opposite directions.
OpenGL considers one of these to be the <word>front face</word>
and the other to be the <word>back face</word>.  OpenGL tells them apart by the
order in which the vertices are specified.  (See <localref href="gl1geom.4.1"/>.)
The default rule is that the order of the vertices is
counterclockwise when looking at the front face and is clockwise when looking at the back face.
When the polygon is drawn on the screen, this rule lets OpenGL tell whether it is the front
face or the back face that is being shown.  When specifying a normal vector for the polygon,
the vector should point out of the front face of the polygon.  This is another example of
the right-hand rule.  If you curl the fingers of your right hand in the direction in which the
vertices of the polygon were specified, then the normal vector should point in the direction of
your thumb.  Note that when you are looking at the front
face of a polygon, the normal vector should be pointing towards you.  If you are looking at the back
face, the normal vector should be pointing away from you.
</p>

<p>It can be a difficult problem to come up with the correct normal vectors for an object.
Complex geometric models often come with the necessary normal vectors included.  This is true,
for example, for the solid shapes drawn by the <word>GLUT</word> library.</p>

</subsection>



<subsection title="The OpenGL 1.1 Lighting Equation" id="gl1light.1.4">

<p>What does it actually mean to say that OpenGL performs "lighting
calculations"?  The goal of the calculation is to produce a color,
(<i>r,g,b,a</i>), for a point on a surface.  In OpenGL&nbsp;1.1, lighting calculations
are actually done only at the vertices of a primitive.  After the color of each
vertex has been computed, colors for interior points of the primitive are obtained
by interpolating the vertex colors.</p>

<p>The alpha component of the vertex color, <i>a</i>, is easy: It's simply the alpha component of
the diffuse material color at that vertex.  The calculation of
<i>r</i>, <i>g</i>, and <i>b</i> is fairly complex and rather mathematical, and you don't necessarily
need to understand it.  But here is a short description of how it's done&dots;</p>

<p>Ignoring alpha components, let's assume that the ambient, diffuse,
specular, and emission colors of the material have RGB components
(<i>ma<sub>r</sub>,ma<sub>g</sub>,ma<sub>b</sub></i>), (<i>md<sub>r</sub>,md<sub>g</sub>,md<sub>b</sub></i>), 
(<i>ms<sub>r</sub>,ms<sub>g</sub>,ms<sub>b</sub></i>),  and (<i>me<sub>r</sub>,me<sub>g</sub>,me<sub>b</sub></i>),
respectively.  Suppose that the global ambient intensity, which represents ambient light that
is not associated with any light source in the environment, is (<i>ga<sub>r</sub>,ga<sub>g</sub>,ga<sub>b</sub></i>).
There can be several point and directional light sources, 
which we refer to as light number 0, light number 1, light number 2, and so on.
With this setup, the red component of the vertex color will be:</p>

<pre>r = me<sub>r</sub> + ga<sub>r</sub>*ma<sub>r</sub> + I<sub>0,r</sub> + I<sub>1,r</sub> + I<sub>2,r</sub> + ...</pre>

<np>where <i>I<sub>0,r</sub></i> is the red component of the contribution to the color that comes from light number 0;
<i>I<sub>1,r</sub></i> is the contribution from light number 1; and so on.
A similar equation holds for the green and blue components of the color.
This equation says that the emission color, <i>me<sub>r</sub></i>, is simply added to any other contributions
to the color.  And the contribution of global ambient light is obtained by multiplying
the global ambient intensity, <i>ga<sub>r</sub></i>, by the material ambient color, <i>ma<sub>r</sub></i>.
This is the mathematical
way of saying that the material ambient color is the fraction of the ambient light
that is reflected by the surface.</np>

<p>The terms I<sub>0,r</sub>,  I<sub>1,r</sub>, and so on, represent contributions to the final color from
the various light sources in the environment.
The contributions from the light sources are complicated.  Consider just one of the
light sources.
Note, first of all, that if a light source is disabled (that is, if it is turned off), then the contribution
from that light source is zero.  For an enabled light source, we have to look at
the geometry as well as the colors:</p>

<img src="light-equation.png" width="513" height="227" tex="light-equation.eps" texscale="0.6"/>

<np>In this illustration, <i>N</i> is the normal vector at the point whose color
we want to compute.  <i>L</i>&nbsp;is a vector that points back along the direction from which the light
arrives at the surface.
<i>V</i>&nbsp;is a vector that points in the direction of the viewer. And 
<i>R</i> is the direction of the reflected ray, that is, the direction in which a light
ray from the source would be reflected specularly when it strikes the surface at the point in
question.  The angle between <i>N</i> and <i>L</i> is the same as the angle
between <i>N</i> and <i>R</i>; this is a basic fact about the physics of light.
All of the vectors are unit vectors, with length 1.
Recall that for unit vectors <i>A</i> and <i>B</i>, the inner product
<i>A</i>&nbsp;&middot;&nbsp;<i>B</i> is equal to the cosine of the angle between the
two vectors.  Inner products occur at several points in the lighting equation,
as the way of accounting for the angles between various vectors.</np>

<p>Now, let's say that the light has ambient, diffuse, and specular color components
(la<sub>r</sub>,la<sub>g</sub>,la<sub>b</sub>), (ld<sub>r</sub>,ld<sub>g</sub>,ld<sub>b</sub>), 
and (ls<sub>r</sub>,ls<sub>g</sub>,ls<sub>b</sub>).  Also, let <i>mh</i> be the value of the
shininess property of the material.  
Then, assuming that the light is enabled, the contribution of this
light source to the red component of the vertex color can be computed as
</p>

<pre>I<sub>r</sub> = la<sub>r</sub>*ma<sub>r</sub> + f*( ld<sub>r</sub>*md<sub>r</sub>*(L&middot;N) + ls<sub>r</sub>*ms<sub>r</sub>*max(0,V&middot;R)<sup>mh</sup> )</pre>

<np>with similar equations for the green and blue components.  The first term,
<i>la<sub>r</sub>*ma<sub>r</sub></i> accounts for the contribution of the ambient light
from this light source to the color of the surface.  This term is added to the color
whether or not the surface is facing the light.</np>

<p>The value of <i>f</i> is 0 if the surface is facing away from the 
light and is 1 if the surface faces the light; that is,
it accounts for the fact that the light only illuminates one side of the surface.
To test whether <i>f</i> is 0 or 1, we can check whether <i>L</i>&middot;<i>N</i> 
is less than 0.  This dot product is the cosine of the angle between <i>L</i> and <i>N</i>;
it is less than 0 when the angle is greater than 90 degrees, which would mean that the
normal vector is on the opposite side of the surface from the light.
When <i>f</i> is zero, there is no diffuse or specular contribution from the 
light to the color of the vertex.</p>

<p>The diffuse component of the color, before adjustment by <i>f</i>,
is given by <i>ld<sub>r</sub>*md<sub>r</sub>*(L&middot;N)</i>.  This represents the
diffuse intensity of the light times the diffuse reflectivity of the material, multiplied
by the cosine of the angle between <i>L</i> and <i>N</i>.  The angle is involved because for
a larger angle, the same amount of energy from the light is spread out over a greater area:</p>

<img src="angle-of-incidence.png" width="427" height="246" tex="angle-of-incidence.eps" texscale="0.75"/>

<np>As the angle increases from 0 to 90 degrees, the cosine of the angle decreases from 1 to 0,
so the larger the angle, the smaller the value of <i>ld<sub>r</sub>*md<sub>r</sub>*(L&middot;N)</i> and
the smaller the contribution of diffuse illumination to the color.</np>

<p>For the specular component, recall that a light ray is reflected specularly as a cone
of light.  The reflection vector, <i>R</i>, is at the center of the cone.  The closer the
viewer is to the center of the cone, the more intense the specular reflection. The distance
of the viewer from the center of the cone depends on the angle between <i>V</i> and <i>R</i>,
which appears in the equation as the dot product <i>V&middot;R</i>.  Mathematically,
the specular contribution to the color is given by
<i>ls<sub>r</sub>*ms<sub>r</sub>*max(0,V&middot;R)<sup>mh</sup></i>.
Taking the maximum of 0 and <i>V&middot;R</i> ensures that the specular contribution is
zero if the angle between <i>V</i> and <i>R</i> is greater than 90 degrees.  Assuming that
is not the case, <i>max(0,V&middot;R)</i> is equal to <i>V&middot;R</i>.
Note that this dot product is raised to the exponent <i>mh</i>, which is
the material's shininess property.
When <i>mh</i> is 0, <i>(V&middot;R)<sup>mh</sup></i> is 1, and there is no dependence on the angle; 
in that case, the result is the sort of huge and undesirable specular highlight
that we have seen for shininess equal to zero.  For positive values of shininess,
the specular contribution is maximal when the angle between <i>V</i> 
and <i>R</i> is zero, and it decreases as the
angle increases.  The larger the shininess value, the faster the rate of decrease.  The
result is that larger shininess values give smaller, sharper specular highlights.
</p>

<p>Remember that the same calculation is repeated for every enabled light
and that the results are combined to give the final vertex color.  It's
easy, especially when using several lights, to end up with color components larger
than one.  In the end, before the color is used to color a pixel on the screen,
the color components must be clamped to the range zero to one.  Values greater than
one are replaced by one.  This makes it easy to produce ugly
pictures in which large areas are a uniform white because all the color values
in those areas exceeded one.  All the information that was supposed to be conveyed
by the lighting has been lost.  The effect is similar to an over-exposed photograph.
It can take some work to find appropriate lighting levels to avoid this kind of
over-exposure.</p>

<p>(My discussion of lighting in this section leaves out some factors.  
The equation as presented doesn't take into account
the fact that the effect of a point light can depend on the distance to the light,
and it doesn't take into account spotlights, which emit just a cone of light.  Both of these
can configured in OpenGL&nbsp;1.1, but this book does not cover how to do that.  There are also many
aspects of light that are not captured by the simple model used in OpenGL.  One of the
most obvious omissions is shadows: Objects don't block light! Light shines right through them.
We will encounter some extensions to the model in later chapters when we discuss other graphics
systems.)</p>


</subsection>




</section>

