<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../graphicstext.dtd" >

<section title="Lights, Camera, Action" id="gl1light.4">

<p1>A scene in computer graphics can be a complex collection of objects, each with
its own <word term="attribute">attributes</word>.  In <localref href="graphics2d.4.2"/>,
we saw how a <word>scene graph</word> can be used to organize all the objects in a 2D
scene.  <word term="rendering">Rendering</word> a scene means traversing the
scene graph, rendering each object in the graph as it is encountered.
For 3D graphics, scene graphs must deal with a larger variety of objects,
attributes, and transforms.  For example, it is often useful to consider lights
and cameras to be objects and to be able to include them in scene graphs.  In this
section, we consider scene graphs in 3D, and how to treat cameras and lights
as objects.</p1>

<p>When designing scene graphs, there are many options to consider.  For example,
should transforms be properties of object nodes, or should there be separate nodes
to represent transforms?  The same question can be asked about attributes.
Another question is whether an attribute value should apply only to the node
of which it is a property, or should it be inherited by the children of that node?</p>

<p>A fundamental choice is the shape of the graph.  In general, a scene graph can
be a <word>directed acyclic graph</word>, or "dag," which is a tree-like structure except
that a node can have several parents in the graph.  The scene graphs in
<localref href="graphics2d.4.2"/> were dags.  This has the advantage that a
single node in the graph can represent several objects in the scene, since in a
dag, a node can be encountered several times as the graph is traversed.  On the other
hand, representing several objects with one scene graph node can lead to a lack of flexibility,
since those objects will all have the same value for any property encoded in
the node.  So, in some applications, scene graphs are required to be trees.  
In a tree, each node has a unique parent, and the node will be encountered only
once as the tree in traversed.  The distinction between trees and dags will show
up when we discuss camera nodes in scene graphs.</p>


<subsection title="Attribute Stack" id="gl1light.4.1">

<p>We have seen how the functions <i>glPushMatrix</i> and <i>glPopMatrix</i> are used
to manipulate the transform stack.  These functions are useful when traversing a
scene graph: When a node that contains a transform is encountered during a traversal
of the graph, <i>glPushMatrix</i> can be called before applying the transform.  Then, after the
node and its descendants have been rendered, <i>glPopMatrix</i> is called to restore the
previous modelview transformation.</p>

<p>Something similar can be done for attributes such as color and material, if it is assumed 
that an attribute value in a scene graph node should be inherited as the default value of
that attribute for children of the node.  OpenGL 1.1 maintains an attribute stack, which is
manipulated using the functions <i>glPushAttrib</i> and <i>glPopAttrib</i>.  In addition
to object attributes like the current color, the attribute stack can store global
attributes like the global ambient color and the enabled state of the depth test.
Since there are so many possible attributes, <i>glPushAttrib</i> does not simply
save the value of every attribute.  Instead, it saves a subset of the
possible attributes.  The subset that is to be saved is specified as a parameter to
the function.  For example, the command</p>

<pre>glPushAttrib(GL_ENABLED_BIT);</pre>

<np>will save a copy of each of the OpenGL state variables that can be enabled or
disabled.  This includes the current state of <i>GL_DEPTH_TEST</i>, <i>GL_LIGHTING</i>,
<i>GL_NORMALIZE</i>, and others.  Similarly,</np>

<pre>glPushAttrib(GL_CURRENT_BIT);</pre>

<np>saves a copy of the current color, normal vector, and texture coordinates.  And</np>

<pre>glPushAttrib(GL_LIGHTING_BIT);</pre>

<np>saves attributes relevant to lighting such as the values of material properties and light properties,
the global ambient color, color material settings, and the enabled state for lighting and each of
the individual lights.  Other constants can be used to save other sets of attributes; see the
OpenGL documentation for details.  It is possible to OR together several constants to combine
sets of attributes.  For example,</np>

<pre>glPushAttrib(GL_LIGHTING_BIT | GL_ENABLED_BIT)</pre>

<np>will save the attributes in both the <i>GL_LIGHTING_BIT</i> set and in the
<i>GL_ENABLED_BIT</i> set.</np>

<p>Calling <i>glPopAttrib</i>() will restore all the values that were saved by the
corresponding call to <i>glPushAttrib</i>.  There is no need for a parameter to
<i>glPopAttrib</i>, since the set of attributes that are restored is determined
by the parameter that was passed to <i>glPushAttrib</i>.</p>

<p>It should be easy to see how <i>glPushAttrib</i> and <i>glPopAttrib</i> can be used
while traversing a scene graph:  When processing a node, before changing attribute values,
call <i>glPushAttrib</i> to save a copy of the relevant set or sets of attributes.
Render the node and its descendants. Then call <i>glPopAttrib</i> to restore the
saved values.  This limits the effect of the changes so that they apply only to the node and
its descendants.</p>

<break/>

<p>There is an alternative way to save and restore values.  OpenGL has a variety of "get" functions
for reading the values of various state variables.  I will discuss just some of them here.
For example,</p>

<pre>glGetFloatv( GL_CURRENT_COLOR, floatArray );</pre>

<np>retrieves the current color value, as set by <i>glColor*</i>.  The <i>floatArray</i> parameter
should be an array of <ptype>float</ptype>, whose length is at least four.  The RGBA color components
of the current color will be stored in the array.  Note that, later, you can simply call
<i>glColor4fv</i>(<i>colorArray</i>) to restore the color.  The same function can be used
with different first parameters to read the values of different floating-point state variables.
To find the current value of the <word>viewport</word>, use</np>

<pre>glGetIntegerv( GL_VIEWPORT, intArray );</pre>

<np>This will set <i>intArray</i>[0] and <i>intArray</i>[1] to be the <i>x</i> and <i>y</i> coordinates
of the lower left corner of the current viewport, <i>intArray</i>[2] to be its width, and <i>intArray</i>[3]
to be its height. To read the current values of material properties, use</np>

<pre>glGetMaterialfv( face, property, floatArray );</pre>

<np>The <i>face</i> must be <i>GL_FRONT</i> or <i>GL_BACK</i>.  The property must be
<i>GL_AMBIENT</i>, <i>GL_DIFFUSE</i>, <i>GL_SPECULAR</i>, <i>GL_EMISSION</i>, or <i>GL_SHININESS</i>.
The current value of the property will be stored in <i>floatArray</i>, which must be of length at least
four for the color properties, or length at least one for <i>GL_SHININESS</i>.  There is
a similar command, <i>glGetLightfv</i>, for reading properties of lights.</np>

<p>Finally, I will mention <i>glIsEnabled</i>(<i>name</i>), which can be used to check the
enabled/disabled status of state variables such as <i>GL_LIGHTING</i> and <i>GL_DEPTH_TEST</i>.
The parameter should be the constant that identifies the state variable.  The function returns 0 if the state
variable is disabled and 1 if it is enabled.  For example, <i>glIsEnabled</i>(<i>GL_LIGHTING</i>)
tests whether lighting is enabled.  Suppose that a node in a scene graph has an attribute
<i>lit</i> to tell whether that node (and its descendants) should be rendered with lighting
enabled.  Then the code for rendering a node might include something like this:</p>

<pre>int saveLit = glIsEnabled(GL_LIGHTING);
if (lit)
    glEnable(GL_LIGHTING);
else
    glDisable(GL_LIGHTING);
   .
   .  // Render the node and its descendants
   .
if (saveLit)
   glEnable(GL_LIGHTING);
else
   glDisable(GL_LIGHTING);</pre>
   
<p>Since <i>glPushAttrib</i> can be used to push large
groups of attribute values, you might think that it would
be more efficient to use <i>glIsEnabled</i> and the <i>glGet*</i> family of commands
to read the values of just those state variables that you are 
planning to modify.  However, recall that OpenGL can queue a number
of commands into a batch to be sent to the graphics card, and those commands
can be executed by the <word>GPU</word> at the same time that your program
continues to run.  A <i>glGet</i> command can require your 
program to communicate with the graphics card and wait for the response.
This means that any pending OpenGL commands will have to be sent to the
graphics card and executed before the <i>glGet</i> command can complete.
This is the kind of thing that can hurt performance.  
In contrast, calls to <i>glPushAttrib</i> and <i>glPopAttrib</i> can
be queued with other OpenGL commands and sent to the graphics
card in batches, where they can be executed efficiently by
the graphics hardware.  In fact, you should generally prefer
using <i>glPushAttrib</i>/<i>glPopAttrib</i> instead of a
<i>glGet</i> command when possible.</p>


</subsection>



<subsection title="Moving Camera" id="gl1light.4.2">

<p>Let's turn to another aspect of modeling.  Suppose that we want to implement a
viewer that can be moved around in the world like other objects.  Sometimes, such
a viewer is thought of as a moving camera.  The camera is used to take pictures of
the scene.  We want to be able to apply transformations
to a camera just as we apply transformations to other objects.  The position
and orientation of the camera determine what should be visible when the scene is 
rendered.  And the "size" of the camera, which can be affected by a scaling transformation,
determines how large a field of view it has.   But a camera is not
just another object.  A camera really represents the viewing transformation that
we want to use.  Recall that modeling and viewing transformations have opposite effects:
Moving objects to the right with a modeling transform is equivalent to moving the
viewer to the left with a viewing transformation.  (See <localref href="gl1geom.3.4"/>.)
To apply a modeling transformation to the camera, we
really want to apply a viewing transformation to the scene as a whole, and that viewing transformation
is the <word term="inverse transform">inverse</word> of the camera's modeling transformation.</p>

<p>The following illustration shows a scene viewed from a moving camera.  The camera starts
in the default viewing position, at the origin, looking in the direction of the negative <i>z</i>-axis.
This corresponds to using the identity as the viewing transform.  For the second image,
the camera has moved forward by ten units.  This would correspond to applying the modeling
transformation <i>glTranslatef</i>(0,0,&minus;10) to the camera (since it is moving in the negative
<i>z</i>-direction).  But to implement this movement as a change of view, 
we want to apply the inverse operation as a viewing transformation.  So, the viewing
transform that we actually apply is <i>glTranslatef</i>(0,0,10).  This can be seen, 
if you like, as a modeling transformation
that is applied to all the <b>other</b> objects in the scene:  Moving the camera ten units in
one direction is equivalent to moving all the other objects 10 units in the opposite direction.</p>

<img src="walkthrough.png" width="629" height="220" tex="walkthrough.eps" texscale="0.75"/>

<np>For the third image, the camera has rotated in place by 21 degrees to the right&mdash;a 21-degree
clockwise rotation about the <i>y</i>-axis&mdash;<b>after</b> it has been translated.  This can be 
implemented by the transformation <i>glRotatef</i>(21,0,1,0)&mdash;a 21-degree counterclockwise
rotation about the <i>y</i>-axis&mdash;applied <b>before</b> the translation. Remember that the
inverse of a composition of transformations is the composition of their inverses, in the opposite
order.  Mathematically, using <i>T<sup>&minus;1</sup></i> to represent the inverse of a
transformation <i>T</i>, we have that 
<i>(RS)<sup>&minus;1</sup>&nbsp;=&nbsp;S<sup>&minus;1</sup>R<sup>&minus;1</sup></i> for
two transformations <i>R</i> and <i>S</i>.</np>


<demo src="c4/walkthrough.html" width="800" height="440">
<p>The images in the illustration are from <web>the following demo.</web><tex>the demo <demoref href="c4/walkthrough.html"/>, which you
can try on-line.</tex>  The demo lets you move around in a scene.  More accurately, of course, it 
lets you change the viewing transformation to see the scene from different viewpoints.</p>
</demo>

<break/>

<p>When using scene graphs, it can be useful to include a camera object in the graph.  That is,
we want to be able to include a node in the graph that represents the camera, and we want to
be able to use the camera to view the scene.  It can even be useful to have several cameras
in the scene, providing alternative points of view.  To implement this, we need to be able
to render a scene from the point of view of a given camera.  From the previous discussion,
we know that in order to do that, we need to use a viewing transformation that is the
inverse of the modeling transformation that is applied to the camera object.
The viewing transform must be applied before any of the objects in the scene are rendered.</p>

<p>When a scene graph is traversed, a modeling transformation can be applied at any node.
The modeling transform that is in effect when a given node is encountered is the composition
of all the transforms that were applied at nodes along the path that led to given node.
However, if the node is a camera node, we don't want to apply that modeling transform;
we want to apply its inverse as a viewing transform.  To get the inverse, we can
start at the camera node and follow the path backwards, applying the inverse of
the modeling transform at each node.</p>

<img src="camera-transform.png" width="445" height="225" bordered="true" tex="camera-transform.eps" texscale="0.75"/>

<np>To easily implement this, we can add "parent pointers" to the scene graph data structure.  
A parent pointer for a node is a link to the parent of that node in the graph. Note that this only works
if the graph is a tree; in a tree, each node has a unique parent, but that is not true in a general
directed acyclic graph.  It is possible to move up the tree by following parent pointers.</np>

<p>We this in mind, the algorithm for rendering the scene from the point of view of a camera
goes as follows: Set the modelview transform to be the identity, by calling <i>glLoadIdentity</i>().
Start at the camera node, and follow parent pointers until you reach the root of the tree.
At each node, apply the <i>inverse</i> of any modeling transformation in that node.
(For example, if the modeling transform is translation by (a,b,c), call
<i>glTranslatef</i>(<i>&minus;a,&minus;b,&minus;c</i>).)  Upon reaching the root, the viewing
transform corresponding to the camera has been established.  Now, traverse the scene graph
to render the scene as usual.  During this traversal, camera nodes should be ignored.</p>

<p>Note that a camera can be attached to an object, in the sense that the camera and the object
are both subject to the same modeling transformation and so move together as a unit.
In modeling terms, the camera and the object
are sub-objects in a complex object.  For example, a camera might be attached
to a car to show the view through the windshield of that car.  If the car moves, because its
modeling transformation changes, the camera will move along with it.  </p>

</subsection>



<subsection title="Moving Light" id="gl1light.4.3">

<p>It can also be useful to think of lights as objects, even as part of a complex object.
Suppose that a scene includes a model
of a lamp.  The lamp model would include some geometry to make it visible, but if it
is going to cast light on other objects in the scene, it also has
to include a source of light.  This means that the lamp is a complex
object made up of an OpenGL light source plus some geometric objects.
Any modeling transformation that is applied to the lamp should
affect the light source as well as the geometry.  In terms of the
scene graph, the light is represented by a node in the graph,
and it is affected by modeling transformations in the same
way as other objects in the scene graph.  You can even have
animated lights&mdash;or animated objects that include lights
as sub-objects, such as the headlights on a car.</p>

<p>Recall from <localref href="gllight.2.3"/> that a light source is subject to the
modelview transform that is in effect at the time the position of the
light source is set by <i>glLightfv</i>.  If the light is represented as a node in
a scene graph, then the modelview transform that we need is the one that
is in effect when that node is encountered during a traversal of the scene
graph.  So, it seems like we should just traverse the graph and set the position
of the light when we encounter it during the traversal.</p>

<p>But there is a problem:  Before any geometry is rendered,
all the light sources that might affect that geometry must already be
configured and enabled.  In particular, the lights' positions must be set
before rendering any geometry.  This means that you can't simply set the
position of light sources in the scene graph as you traverse the graph in the
usual way.  If you do that, objects that are drawn before the
light is encountered won't be properly illuminated by the
light.  Similarly,
if the light node contains values for any other properties of
the light, including the enabled/disabled state of the light,
those properties must be set before rendering any geometry.</p>

<p>One solution is to do two traversals of the scene graph, the first
to set up the lights and the second to draw the geometry.  Since
lights are affected by the modelview transformation, you have to
set up the modeling transform during the first traversal
in exactly the same way that you do in the second traversal.
When you encounter the lights during the first traversal,
you need to set the position of the light, since setting the
position is what triggers the application of the current modelview
transformation to the light.  You also need to set any other
properties of the light.  During the first traversal, geometric
objects in the scene graph are ignored.  During the second traversal, when
geometry is being rendered, light nodes can be ignored.</p>



</subsection>

</section>
