<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../graphicstext.dtd" >

<section title="Image Textures" id="webgl.4">

<p1><word term="texture">Textures</word> play an essential role in 3D graphics,
and support for <word term="image texture">image textures</word> is built into
modern <word term="GPU">GPUs</word> on the hardware level.  In this section,
we look at the WebGL API for image textures. Image textures
in OpenGL&nbsp;1.1 were covered in <localref href="gl1light.3"/>.  Much of
that section is still relevant in modern OpenGL, including WebGL.  So,
as we cover image textures in WebGL, much of the material will not be
new to you.  However, there is one feature that is new since OpenGL&nbsp;1.1:
<newword term="texture unit">texture units</newword>.</p1>

<p>One of the significant differences between WebGL 1.0 and WebGL 2.0 is 
an increase in support for different types of textures and for
different ways of using textures.  Access to most of the new features
requires using <word>GLSL</word>&nbsp;ES&nbsp;3.00 for the <word term="shader">shader</word> programs.
We will stick to WebGL&nbsp;1.0 for most of this section, but will discuss some
of the new WebGL&nbsp;2.0 features in the final subsection.
</p>

<subsection title="Texture Units and Texture Objects" id="webgl.4.1">

<p>A texture unit, also called a texture mapping unit (<newword>TMU</newword>) or
a texture processing unit (TPU),
is a hardware component in a GPU  that does sampling.  <newword term="sampling">Sampling</newword>
is the process of computing a color from an image texture and <word>texture coordinates</word>.
Mapping a texture image to a surface is a fairly complex operation, since it requires more
than just returning the color of the <word>texel</word> that contains some given texture
coordinates.  It also requires applying the appropriate <word term="minification filter">minification</word>
or <word>magnification filter</word>, possibly using <word term="mipmap">mipmaps</word> if available.
Fast texture sampling is one of the key requirements for good GPU performance.</p>

<p>Texture units are not to be confused with <word term="texture object">texture objects</word>.
We encountered texture objects in <localref href="gl1light.3.7"/>.  A texture object
is a data structure that contains the color data for an image texture, and possibly for
a set of mipmaps for the texture, as well as the values of texture properties such
as the minification and magnification filters and the <word>texture repeat mode</word>.
A texture unit must access a texture object to do its work.  The texture unit is the
processor; the texture object holds the data that is processed.</p>

<p>(By the way, I should really be more careful about throwing around the terms "GPU" and
"hardware."  Although a texture unit probably does use an actual hardware component in the
GPU, it could also be emulated, more slowly, in software.  And even if there is
hardware involved, having eight texture units does not necessarily mean that there are
eight hardware components; the texture units might share time on a smaller number of
hardware components.  Similarly, I said previously that texture objects are stored
in memory in the GPU, which might or might not be literally true in a given case.
Nevertheless, you will probably find it conceptually easier to think of a texture unit 
as a piece of hardware and a texture object as a data structure in the GPU.)</p>

<break/>

<p>In <word>GLSL</word>, texture lookup is done using <newword term="sampler variable">sampler variables</newword>.
A sampler variable is a variable in a shader program.  In GLSL&nbsp;ES&nbsp;1.00, the only sampler types are 
<i>sampler2D</i> and <i>samplerCube</i>.
A <i>sampler2D</i> is used to do lookup in a standard texture image; a <i>samplerCube</i> is used
to do lookup in a <word>cubemap texture</word> (<localref href="threejs.3.4"/>).
The value of a sampler variable is a reference to a texture unit.  The value tells which texture
unit is invoked when the sampler variable is used to do texture lookup.
Sampler variables must be declared as global uniform variables.  
It is not legal for a shader program to assign a value to a sampler variable.  The
value must come from the JavaScript side.</p>

<p>On the JavaScript side, the available texture units are numbered 0, 1, 2,&nbsp;&dots;, where
the maximum value is implementation dependent.  The number of units can be determined as the value of
the expression</p>

<pre>gl.getParameter( gl.MAX_COMBINED_TEXTURE_IMAGE_UNITS )</pre>

<np>(Please remember, again, that <i>gl</i> here is the name of a JavaScript variable that refers to the
WebGL context, and that the name is up to the programmer.)</np>

<p>As far as JavaScript is concerned, the value of a sampler variable is an integer.  If you
want a sampler variable to use texture unit number 2, then you set the value of the
sampler variable to&nbsp;2.  This can be done using the function <i>gl.uniform1i</i>
(<localref href="webgl.1.4"/>).  For example, suppose a shader program declares a sampler
variable
</p>

<pre>uniform sampler2D u_texture;</pre>

<np>To set its value from JavaScript, you need the location of the variable in the
shader program.  If <i>prog</i> is the shader program, the location is obtained by
calling</np>

<pre>u_texture_location = gl.getUniformLocation( prog, "u_texture" );</pre>

<np>Then, you can tell the sampler variable to use texture unit number 2 by calling</np>

<pre>gl.uniform1i( u_texture_location, 2 );</pre>

<np>Note that the integer value is not accessible in GLSL.  The integer tells the
sampler which texture unit to use, but there is no way for the shader program to
find out the number of the unit that is being used.</np>

<break/>

<p>To use an image texture, you also need to create a texture object, and you need to load
an image into the texture object.  You might want to set some properties of the texture
object, and you might want to create a set of mipmaps for the texture.  And
you will have to associate the texture object with a texture unit.  All this is
done on the JavaScript side.</p>

<p>The command for creating a texture object is <i>gl.createTexture</i>().  The command
in OpenGL&nbsp;1.1 was <i>glGenTextures</i>.  The WebGL command is easier to use.
It creates a single texture object and returns a reference to it.  For example,</p>

<pre>textureObj = gl.createTexture();</pre>

<np>This just allocates some memory for the object.  In order to use it, you must
first "bind" the texture object by calling <i>gl.bindTexture</i>.  For example,</np>

<pre>gl.bindTexture( gl.TEXTURE_2D, textureObj );</pre>

<np>The first parameter, <i>gl.TEXTURE_2D</i>, is the texture target.  This target is
used for working with an ordinary texture image.  There is a different target for
cubemap textures.</np>

<p>The function <i>gl.texImage2D</i> is used to load an image into the currently bound
texture object.  We will come back to that in the next subsection.  But remember that
this command and other commands always apply to the currently bound texture object.
The texture object is not mentioned in the command; instead, the texture object must be bound
before the command is called.</p>

<p>You also need to tell a texture unit to use the texture object.  Before you can
do that, you need to make the texture unit "active," which is done by calling the function
<i>gl.activeTexture</i>.  The parameter is one of the constants
<i>gl.TEXTURE0</i>, <i>gl.TEXTURE1</i>, <i>gl.TEXTURE2</i>,&nbsp;&dots;, which represent
the available texture units.  (The values of these constants are <b>not</b> 0, 1, 2,&nbsp;&dots;.)
Initially, texture unit number 0 is active.  To make texture unit number 2 active, for example, use</p>

<pre>gl.activeTexture( gl.TEXTURE2 );</pre>

<np>(This function should really have been called <i>activeTexture<b>Unit</b></i>, or maybe
<i>bindTextureUnit</i>, since it works similarly to the various WebGL "bind" functions.) 
If you then call</np>


<pre>gl.bindTexture( gl.TEXTURE_2D, textureObj );</pre>

<np>to bind a texture object, while texture unit 2 is active, then
the texture object <i>textureObj</i> is bound to texture unit number&nbsp;2 for
<i>gl.TEXTURE_2D</i> operations.  The binding
just tells the texture unit which texture object to use.  That is, when texture unit&nbsp;2 does
<i>TEXTURE_2D</i> lookups, it will do so using the image and the settings that are stored in <i>textureObj</i>.
A texture object can be bound to several texture units at the same time.  However, a given
texture unit can have only one bound <i>TEXTURE_2D</i> at a time.</np>

<p>So, working with texture images in WebGL involves working with texture objects, texture
units, and sampler variables.  The relationship among the three is illustrated in this
picture:</p>

<img src="texture-units-and-objects.png" width="566" height="357" tex="texture-units-and-objects.eps" texscale="0.75"/>

<np>A sampler variable uses a texture unit, which uses a texture object, which holds a texture image.
The JavaScript commands for setting up this chain are shown in the illustration.  To apply a texture
image to a primitive, you have to set up the entire chain. Of course, you also have to
provide texture coordinates for the primitive, and 
you need to use the sampler variable in the shader program to access the texture.</np>

<p>Suppose that you have several images that you would like to use on several different
primitives.  Between drawing primitives, you need to change the texture image that will be
used.  There are at least three different ways to manage the images in WebGL:</p>

<ol>
<li>You could use a single texture object and a single texture unit.  The bound texture object,
the active texture unit, and the value of the sampler variable can be set once and never changed.  
To change to a new image, you would use <i>gl.texImage2D</i> to load the image into the texture
object.  This is essentially how things were done in OpenGL&nbsp;1.0.  It's very inefficient,
except when you are going to use each image just once.  That's why texture objects were
introduced.</li>
<li>You could use a different texture object for each image, but use just a single texture unit.
The active texture and the value of the sampler variable will never have to be changed.
You would switch to a new texture image using <i>gl.bindTexture</i> to bind the texture
object that contains the desired image.</li>
<li>You could use a different texture unit for each image.  You would load each
image into its own texture object and bind that object to one of the texture units.
You would switch to a new texture image by changing the value of the sampler variable.</li>
</ol>

<np>I don't know how options 2 and 3 compare in terms of efficiency.  Note that you
are only <b>forced</b> to use more than one texture unit if you want to apply more
than one texture image to the same primitive.  To do that, you will need several
sampler variables in the shader program.  They will have different values so that
they refer to different texture units, and the color of a pixel will somehow depend
on samples from both images.  This picture shows two textures being combined
in simple ways to compute the colors of pixels in a textured square:</np>

<img src="multi-texture.png" width="560" height="279" tex="multi-texture.eps" texscale="0.6"/>


<demo src="c6/multi-texture.html" width="625" height="475">
<np>In the image on the left, a <word>grayscale</word> "brick" image is multiplied by an "Earth" image;
that is, the red component of a pixel is computed by multiplying the red component from
the brick texture by the red component from the Earth texture, and same for green and blue.
On the right, the same Earth texture is subtracted from a "cloth" texture.  Furthermore,
the pattern is distorted because the texture coordinates were  modified before being
used to sample the textures, using the formula <i>texCoords.y</i> <code>+=</code> 
0.25<code>*</code><i>sin</i>(6.28*<i>texCoords.x</i>).  That's the kind of thing that
could only be done with programmable shaders!  The images are taken from
<web>the following demo</web><tex>the on-line demo <demoref href="c6/multi-texture.html"/></tex>.
Try it out!</np>
</demo>

<p>You might want to view the <demoref href="c6/multi-texture.html">source code</demoref>
to see how the textures are programmed.  Two texture units are used.  The values of two
uniform sampler variables, <i>u_texture1</i> and <i>u_texture2</i>, are set during
initialization with the code</p>

<pre>u_texture1_location = gl.getUniformLocation(prog, "u_texture1");
u_texture2_location = gl.getUniformLocation(prog, "u_texture2");
gl.uniform1i(u_texture1_location, 0);
gl.uniform1i(u_texture2_location, 1);</pre>

<np>The values are never changed.  The program uses several texture images.  There is a
texture object for each image.  On the JavaScript side, the IDs for the texture objects are stored in an array,
<i>textureObjects</i>.  Two popup menus allow the user to select which texture images
are applied to the primitive.  This is implemented in the drawing routine by binding
the two selected texture objects to texture units 0 and&nbsp;1, which are the units used
by the two sampler variables.  The code for that is:</np>

<pre>let tex1Num = Number(document.getElementById("textureChoice1").value);
gl.activeTexture( gl.TEXTURE0 );
gl.bindTexture( gl.TEXTURE_2D, textureObjects[tex1Num] );

let tex2Num = Number(document.getElementById("textureChoice2").value);
gl.activeTexture( gl.TEXTURE1 );
gl.bindTexture( gl.TEXTURE_2D, textureObjects[tex2Num] );</pre>

<np>Getting images into the texture objects is another question, which we turn to next.</np>

</subsection>


<subsection title="Working with Images" id="webgl.4.2">

<p>An image can be loaded into a texture object using the function <i>gl.texImage2D</i>.
For use with WebGL, this function usually has the form
</p>

<pre>gl.texImage2D( target, 0, gl.RGBA, gl.RGBA, gl.UNSIGNED_BYTE, image );</pre>

<np>The target is <i>gl.TEXTURE_2D</i> for ordinary textures; there are other targets for
loading cubemap textures.  The second parameter is the mipmap level, which is 0 for the
main image.  Although it is possible to load individual mipmaps, that is rarely done.
The next two parameters give the format of the texture inside the texture object and
in the original image.  In WebGL&nbsp;1.0, the two format parameters should have the same value.
Since web images are stored in RGBA format, <i>gl.RGBA</i> is probably the most efficient choice, 
and there is rarely a need to use anything else.
But you can use <i>gl.RGB</i> if you don't need the alpha component.  And by
using <i>gl.LUMINANCE</i> or <i>gl.LUMINANCE_ALPHA</i>, you can convert the
image to grayscale.  (<word term="luminance">Luminance</word> is a weighted average
of red, green, and blue that approximates the perceived brightness of a color.)
The fourth parameter is always going to be <i>gl.UNSIGNED_BYTE</i>, indicating that
the colors in the image are stored using one byte for each color component.  Although
other values are possible, they don't really make sense for web images.</np>

<p>The last  parameter in the call to <i>gl.texImage2D</i> is the image.  Ordinarily,
<i>image</i> will be a <word>DOM</word> image element that has been loaded asynchronously
by JavaScript.   The <i>image</i> can also be a <tag>canvas</tag> element.
This means that you can draw on a canvas, using the <word>HTML canvas</word> 2D graphics
API, and then use the canvas as the source for a texture image.  You can even do 
that with an <word>off-screen canvas</word> that is not visible on the web page.</p>

<p>The image is loaded into the texture object that is currently bound to <i>target</i> in
the currently active texture unit.  There is no default texture object; that is, if no texture 
has been bound when <i>gl.texImage2D</i> is called, an error occurs.  The active texture unit
is the one that has been selected using <i>gl.activeTexture</i>, or is texture unit 0
if <i>gl.activeTexture</i> has never been called.  A texture object is bound to the active texture unit
by <i>gl.bindTexture</i>.  This was discussed earlier in this section.</p>

<p>Using images in WebGL is complicated by the fact that images are loaded
asynchronously.  That is, the command for loading an image just starts the
process of loading the image.  You can specify a callback function that will
be executed when the loading completes.  The image won't actually be available
for use until after the callback function is called.  When loading an
image to use as a texture, the callback function should load the image into
a texture object.  Often, it will also call a rendering function to draw
the scene, with the texture image.</p>

<p>The sample program <sourceref href="webgl/simple-texture.html"/> is an example
of using a single texture on a triangle.  Here is a function that is
used to load the texture image in that program.  The texture object is
created before the function is called.</p>

<pre>/**
 *  Loads a texture image asynchronously.  The first parameter is the url
 *  from which the image is to be loaded.  The second parameter is the
 *  texture object into which the image is to be loaded.  When the image
 *  has finished loading, the draw() function will be called to draw the
 *  triangle with the texture.  (Also, if an error occurs during loading,
 *  an error message is displayed on the page, and draw() is called to
 *  draw the triangle without the texture.)
 */
function loadTexture( url, textureObject ) {
    const  img = new Image();  //  A DOM image element to represent the image.
    img.onload = function() { 
        // This function will be called after the image loads successfully.
        // We have to bind the texture object to the TEXTURE_2D target before
        // loading the image into the texture object. 
        gl.bindTexture(gl.TEXTURE_2D, textureObject);
        try {
           gl.texImage2D(gl.TEXTURE_2D,0,gl.RGBA,gl.RGBA,gl.UNSIGNED_BYTE,img);
           gl.generateMipmap(gl.TEXTURE_2D);  // Create mipmaps; you must either
                              // do this or change the minification filter.
        }
        catch (e) { // Probably a security exception, because this page has been
                    // loaded through a file:// URL.
            document.getElementById("headline").innerHTML =
              "Sorry, couldn't load texture.&lt;br&gt;" +
              "Some web browsers won't use images from a local disk";
        }
        draw();  // Draw the canvas, with or without the texture.  
    };
    img.onerror = function() { 
        // This function will be called if an error occurs while loading.
        document.getElementById("headline").innerHTML =
                        "&lt;p&gt;Sorry, texture image could not be loaded.&lt;/p&gt;";
        draw();  // Draw without the texture; triangle will be black.
    };
    img.src = url;  // Start loading of the image.
                    // This must be done after setting onload and onerror.
}</pre>


<p>Note that image textures for WebGL 1.0 should be power-of-two textures.  That is,
the width and the height of the image should each be a power of 2, such as
128, 256, or 512.  You can, in fact, use non-power-of-two textures, but you can't
use mipmaps with such textures, and the only texture repeat mode that is supported
by such textures is <i>gl.CLAMP_TO_EDGE</i>.  (WebGL&nbsp;2.0 does not have these
restrictions.)</p>

<p>(The <code>try..catch</code> statement is used in this function because most
web browsers will throw a security exception when a page attempts to use an
image from the local file system as a texture.  This means that if you attempt to run a program
that uses textures from a downloaded version of this book, the programs that
use textures might not work.)</p>

<break/>

<p>There are several parameters associated with a texture object, including the
texture repeat modes and the minification and magnification filters.  They can
be set using the function <i>gl.texParameteri</i>.   The setting applies to
the currently bound texture object.  Most of the details are
the same as in OpenGL 1.1 (<localref href="gl1light.3.3"/>).  For example, the minification
filter can be set to <i>LINEAR</i> using</p>

<pre>gl.texParameteri( gl.TEXTURE_2D, gl.TEXTURE_MIN_FILTER, gl.LINEAR);</pre>

<np>Recall that the default minification filter won't work without mipmaps.
To get a working texture, you have to change the minification filter or install
a full set of mipmaps.  Fortunately, WebGL has a function that will generate
the mipmaps for you:</np>

<pre>gl.generateMipmap( gl.TEXTURE_2D );</pre>

<p>The texture repeat modes determine what happens when texture coordinates 
lie outside the range 0.0 to 1.0.  There is a separate repeat mode for
each direction in the texture coordinate system.
In WebGL, the possible values are <i>gl.REPEAT</i>, <i>gl.CLAMP_TO_EDGE</i>,
and <i>gl.MIRRORED_REPEAT</i>.  The default is <i>gl.REPEAT</i>.  The mode
<i>CLAMP_TO_EDGE</i> was called <i>CLAMP</i> in OpenGL 1.1, and <i>MIRRORED_REPEAT</i> 
is new in WebGL.  With <i>MIRRORED_REPEAT</i>, the texture image is repeated to
cover the entire plane, but every other copy of the image is reflected.  This
can eliminate visible seams between the copies.  To set a texture
to use mirrored repeat in both directions, use</p>

<pre>gl.texParameteri( gl.TEXTURE_2D, gl.TEXTURE_WRAP_S, gl.MIRRORED_REPEAT);
gl.texParameteri( gl.TEXTURE_2D, gl.TEXTURE_WRAP_T, gl.MIRRORED_REPEAT);</pre>

<break/>

<p>In WebGL, texture coordinates are usually input to the vertex shader as an attribute
of type <i>vec2</i>.  They are communicated to the fragment shader in a varying variable.
Often, the vertex shader will simply copy the value of the attribute into the varying
variable.  Another possibility is to apply an affine <word>texture transformation</word>
to the coordinates in the vertex shader before passing them on to the fragment shader.
In the fragment shader, the texture coordinates are used to sample a
texture.  The GLSL&nbsp;ES&nbsp;1.00 function for sampling an ordinary texture is</p>

<pre>texture2D( samplerVariable, textureCoordinates );</pre>

<np>where <i>samplerVariable</i> is the uniform variable of type <i>sampler2D</i> that
represents the texture, and <i>textureCoordinates</i> is a <i>vec2</i> containing
the texture coordinates. The return value is an RGBA color, represented as a
value of type <i>vec4</i>.  As a very minimal example, here is a fragment shader that
simply uses the sampled value from the texture as the color of the pixel.</np>


<pre>precision mediump float;
uniform sampler2D u_texture;
varying vec2 v_texCoords;
void main() {
   vec4 color = texture2D( u_texture, v_texCoords );
   gl_FragColor = color;
}</pre>

<np>This shader is from the sample program <sourceref href="webgl/simple-texture.html"/>.</np>

<demo src="c6/textured-points.html" width="600" height="375">
<p>Textures are sometimes used on primitives of type <i>gl.POINTS</i>.  In that case,
it's natural to get the texture coordinates for a pixel from the special fragment
shader variable <i>gl_PointCoord</i>.  A point is rendered as a square, and the
coordinates in <i>gl_PointCoord</i> range from 0.0 to 1.0 over that square.
So, using <i>gl_PointCoord</i> means that one copy of the texture will be
pasted onto the point.  If the <i>POINTS</i> primitive has more than one
vertex, you will see a copy of the texture at the location of each vertex.
This is an easy way to put an image, or multiple copies of an image, into a
scene.  The technique is sometimes referred to as "point sprites."</p>
<p><web>The following demo draws a single textured primitive of type
<i>gl.POINTS</i>, so you can see what it looks like.  In the demo, only
a circular cutout from each square point is drawn.</web><tex>Here is an
example of a textured primitive of type <i>gl.POINTS</i>.  Only
a circular cutout from each square point is drawn.  The picture
is from an on-line demo, <demoref href="c6/textured-points.html"/>.</tex></p></demo>

<texdiv><img tex="textured-points.eps" texscale="0.6"/></texdiv>

<break/>

<p>The pixel data for a texture image in WebGL is stored in memory starting with the
row of pixels at the bottom of the image and working up from there.  When WebGL creates the
texture by reading the data from an image, it assumes that the image uses the same format.  However,
images in a web browser are stored in the opposite order, starting with the pixels
in the top row of the image and working down.  The result of this mismatch is that
texture images will appear upside down.  You can account for this by modifying
your texture coordinates.  However, you can also tell WebGL to invert the
images for you as it "unpacks" them.  To do that, call</p>

<pre>gl.pixelStorei( gl.UNPACK_FLIP_Y_WEBGL, 1 );</pre>

<np>Generally, you can do this as part of initialization.  Note however that
for <i>gl.POINTS</i> primitives, the coordinate system used by <i>gl_PointCoord</i>
is already upside down, with the <i>y</i>-coordinate increasing from top to bottom.
So, if you are loading an image for use on a <i>POINTS</i> primitive, you might
want to set <i>gl.UNPACK_FLIP_Y_WEBGL</i> to its default value,&nbsp;0.</np>

</subsection>

<subsection title="More Ways to Make Textures" id="webgl.4.3">

<p>We have seen how to create a texture from an image or canvas element using <i>gl.texImage2D</i>.
There are several more ways to make an image texture in WebGL.  First of all, the function
</p>

<pre>glCopyTexImage2D( target, mipmapLevel, internalFormat,
                                     x, y, width, height, border );</pre>
                                     
<np>which was covered in <localref href="gl1light.3.6"/> also exists in WebGL.
This function copies data from the color buffer (where WebGL renders its images)
into the currently bound texture object.  The data is taken from the
rectangular region in the color buffer with the specified <i>width</i> and
<i>height</i> and with its lower left corner at (<i>x,y</i>).  The
<i>internalFormat</i> is usually <i>gl.RGBA</i>.  For WebGL, the <i>border</i>
must be zero. For example,</np>

<pre>glCopyTexImage2D( gl.TEXTURE_2, 0, gl.RGBA, 0, 0, 256, 256, 0);</pre>

<np>This takes the texture data from a 256-pixel square in the bottom left corner
of the color buffer.  (In a later chapter, we will see that it is actually possible, and more efficient, for
WebGL to render an image directly to a texture object, using something called a "framebuffer.")</np>

<p>More interesting, perhaps, is the ability to take the texture data directly from
an array of numbers.  The numbers will become the color component values for the
pixels in the texture.  The function that is used for this is an alternative version
of <i>texImage2D</i>:</p>

<pre>texImage2D( target, mipmapLevel, internalFormat, width, height,
                                  border, dataFormat, dataType, dataArray )</pre>

<np>and a typical function call would have the form</np>

<pre>gl.texImage2D(gl.TEXTURE_2D, 0, gl.RGBA, 16, 16, 
                                  0, gl.RGBA, gl.UNSIGNED_BYTE, pixels);</pre>

<np>Compared to the original version of <i>texImage2D</i>, there are three extra 
parameters, <i>width</i>, <i>height</i>, and <i>border</i>. The <i>width</i>
and <i>height</i> specify the size of the texture image.  For WebGL, the
<i>border</i> must be zero, and for WebGL&nbsp;1.0, the <i>internalFormat</i> and <i>dataFormat</i>
must be the same.</np>

<p>The last parameter in this version of <i>texImage2D</i> must be a typed array of 
type <classname>Uint8Array</classname> or <classname>Uint16Array</classname>, depending 
on the <i>dataFormat</i> of the texture.  My examples will use <classname>Uint8Array</classname> 
and texture format <i>gl.RGBA</i> or <i>gl.LUMINANCE</i>.</p>

<p>For an RGBA texture, four color component values are needed for each pixel.  The values
will be given as unsigned bytes, with values ranging from 0 to 255, in a <i>Uint8Array</i>.
The length of the array will be 4<code>*</code><i>width</i><code>*</code><i>height</i> (that is,
four times the number of pixels in the image).  The data for the bottom row of pixels comes
first in the array, followed by the row on top of that, and so on, with the pixels in 
a given row running from left to right.
And within the data for one pixel, the red component comes first, followed by the
blue, then the green, then the alpha.</p>

<p>As an example of making up texture data from scratch, let's make a 16-by-16 texture image, 
with the image divided into four 8-by-8 squares that are colored red, white, and blue.  The code uses the fact that
when a typed array is created, it is initially filled with zeros.  We just have to
change some of those zeros to 255.</p>

<pre>let pixels = new Uint8Array( 4*16*16 );  // four bytes per pixel

for (let i = 0; i &lt; 16; i++) {
    for (let j = 0; j &lt; 16; j++) {
        let offset = 64*i + 4*j ;    // starting index of data for this pixel
        pixels[offset + 3] = 255;    // alpha value for the pixel
        if ( i &lt; 8 &amp;&amp; j &lt; 8) { // bottom left quadrant is red
            pixels[offset] = 255;  // set red component to maximum
        }
        else if ( i &gt;= 8 &amp;&amp; j &gt;= 8 ) { // top right quadrant is blue
            pixels[offset + 2] = 255; // set blue component to maximum
        }
        else { // the other two quadrants are white
            pixels[offset] = 255;     // set all components to maximum
            pixels[offset + 1] = 255;
            pixels[offset + 2] = 255;
        }
    }
}

texture = gl.createTexture();
gl.bindTexture(gl.TEXTURE_2D, texture);
gl.texImage2D(gl.TEXTURE_2D, 0, gl.RGBA, 16, 16, 
                             0, gl.RGBA, gl.UNSIGNED_BYTE, pixels);
gl.texParameteri(gl.TEXTURE_2D, gl.TEXTURE_MIN_FILTER, gl.LINEAR);</pre>

<p>The last line is there because the default minification filter won't work without
mipmaps.  The texture uses the default magnification filter, which is also
<i>gl.LINEAR</i>.  This texture is used on the leftmost square in the image shown below.  The image
is from the sample program <sourceref href="webgl/texture-from-pixels.html"/>.</p>

<img src="textures-from-pixels.png" width="599" height="119" tex="textures-from-pixels.eps" texscale="0.5"/>

<np>Note the blending along the edges between colors in the leftmost square.  The blending is
caused by the <i>gl.LINEAR</i> magnification filter.  The second square uses the same
texture, but with the <i>gl.NEAREST</i> magnification filter, which eliminates the blending.
The same effect can be seen in the next two squares, which use a black/white
checkerboard pattern, one with <i>gl.Linear</i> as the magnification filter and
one using <i>gl.NEAREST</i>.  The texture is repeated ten times horizontally and vertically
on the square.  In this case, the texture is a tiny 2-by-2 image with two black
and two white pixels.</np>

<p>As another example, consider the rightmost square in the image.  The gradient 
effect on that square comes from a texture.  The texture size is 256-by-1 pixels,
with the color changing from black to white along the length of the texture.  One
copy of the texture is mapped to the square.  For
the gradient texture, I used <i>gl.LUMINANCE</i> as the texture format, which means
that the data consists of one byte per pixel, giving the grayscale value for that
pixel.  The texture can be created using</p>

<pre>let pixels = new Unit8Array( 256 );  // One byte per pixel
for ( let i = 0; i &lt; 256; i++ ) {
    pixels[i] = i;  // Grayscale value for pixel number i is i.
}

gl.texImage2D(gl.TEXTURE_2D, 0, gl.LUMINANCE, 256, 1, 
                             0, gl.LUMINANCE, gl.UNSIGNED_BYTE, pixels);</pre>
                             
<np>See the <sourceref href="webgl/texture-from-pixels.html">sample program</sourceref> for more detail.</np>

</subsection>



<subsection title="Cubemap Textures" id="webgl.4.4">

<p>We encountered cubemap textures in <localref href="threejs.3.4"/>, where saw how they
are used in <i><word>three.js</word></i> for <word term="skybox">skyboxes</word> 
and <word>environment mapping</word>.  WebGL has built-in support for cubemap
textures.  Instead of representing an ordinary image texture, a texture object
can hold a cubemap texture.  And two texture objects can be bound to the same texture
unit simultaneously, one holding an ordinary texture and one holding a
cubemap texture.  The two textures are bound to different targets, <i>gl.TEXTURE_2D</i>
and <i>gl.TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP</i>.
A&nbsp;texture object, <i>texObj</i>, is bound to the cubemap target in the currently
active texture unit by calling</p>

<pre>gl.bindTexture( gl.TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP, texObj );</pre>

<np>A given texture object can be either a regular texture or a cubemap texture, not both.
Once it has been bound to one texture target, it cannot be rebound to the other target.</np>

<p>A cubemap texture consists of six images, one for each face of the cube.
A texture object that holds a cubemap texture has six image slots, identified by
the constants</p>

<pre>gl.TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_NEGATIVE_X
gl.TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_POSITIVE_X
gl.TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_NEGATIVE_Y
gl.TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_POSITIVE_Y
gl.TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_NEGATIVE_Z
gl.TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_POSITIVE_Z</pre>

<np>The constants are used as the targets in <i>gl.texImage2D</i> and <i>gl.copyTexImage2D</i>,
in place of <i>gl.TEXTURE_2D</i>.
(Note that there are six targets for loading images into a cubemap texture object, but only
one target, <i>gl.TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP</i>, for binding the texture object to a texture unit.)
A cubemap texture is often stored as a set of six images, which must be loaded
separately into a texture object.  Of course, it is also possible for WebGL to create a cubemap by rendering the
six images.</np>

<p>As usual for images on the web, there is the problem
of asynchronous image loading to be dealt with.  Here, for example, is a function
that creates a cubemap texture in my sample program <sourceref href="webgl/cubemap-fisheye.html"/>:</p>

<pre>function loadCubemapTexture() {
    const  tex = gl.createTexture();
    let  imageCt = 0; // Number of images that have finished loading.

    load( "cubemap-textures/park/negx.jpg", gl.TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_NEGATIVE_X );
    load( "cubemap-textures/park/posx.jpg", gl.TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_POSITIVE_X );
    load( "cubemap-textures/park/negy.jpg", gl.TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_NEGATIVE_Y );
    load( "cubemap-textures/park/posy.jpg", gl.TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_POSITIVE_Y );
    load( "cubemap-textures/park/negz.jpg", gl.TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_NEGATIVE_Z );
    load( "cubemap-textures/park/posz.jpg", gl.TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_POSITIVE_Z );

    function load(url, target) {
        let  img = new Image();
        img.onload = function() {
            gl.bindTexture(gl.TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP, tex);
            try {
                gl.texImage2D(target, 0, gl.RGBA, gl.RGBA, gl.UNSIGNED_BYTE, img);
            }
            catch (e) {
                document.getElementById("headline").innerHTML =
                   "Can't access texture.  Note that some browsers" +
                   " can't use  a texture from a local file.";
                return;
            }
            imageCt++;
            if (imageCt === 6) {  // all 6 images have been loaded
                gl.generateMipmap( gl.TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP );
                document.getElementById("headline").innerHTML = 
                                      "Funny Cubemap (Fisheye Camera Effect)";
                textureObject = tex;
                draw();
            }
        };
        img.onerror = function() {
            document.getElementById("headline").innerHTML = 
                                              "SORRY, COULDN'T LOAD TEXTURES";
        };
        img.src = url;
    }
}</pre>


<p>The images for a cubemap must all be the same size.  They must be square.
The size should, as usual, be a power of two.  For a cubemap texture, texture 
parameters such as the minification filter are set using the target <i>gl.TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP</i>,
and they apply to all six faces of the cube.
For example, </p>

<pre>gl.texParameteri(gl.TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP, gl.TEXTURE_MIN_FILTER, gl.LINEAR);</pre>

<np>Similarly, <i>gl.generateMipmap</i> will generate mipmaps for all six faces (so
it should not be called until all six images have been loaded).</np>

<break/>

<p>In a shader program, a cube map texture is represented by a uniform
variable of type <i>samplerCube</i>.  In GLSL&nbsp;ES&nbsp;1.00, the texture is sampled using
function <i>textureCube</i>.  For example,</p>

<pre>vec4 color = textureCube( u_texture, vector );</pre>

<np>The first parameter is the <i>samplerCube</i> variable that represents the texture.
The second parameter is a <i>vec3</i>.  Cube map textures are not sampled using
regular texture coordinates.  Instead, a 3D <word>vector</word> is used.  The goal is to
pick out a point in the texture.  The texture lies on the surface of a cube.
To use a vector to pick out a point in the texture, cast a ray from the center of the cube
in the direction given by the vector, and check where that ray intersects
the cube.  That is, if you put the starting point of the vector at the center 
of the cube, it points to the point on the cube where the texture is to be sampled.</np>

<p>Since we aren't doing 3D graphics in this chapter, we can't use cube maps
in the ordinary way.  The sample program <sourceref href="webgl/cubemap-fisheye.html"/> uses
a cube map in an interesting, if not very useful way.  The program uses
2D texture coordinates.  The fragment shader transforms a pair of 2D texture coordinates
into a 3D vector that is then used to sample the cubemap texture.  The effect is
something like a photograph produced by a fisheye camera.  Here's what it looks like.</p>

<img src="cubemap-fisheye.png" width="606" height="306" tex="cubemap-fisheye.eps" texscale="0.5"/>

<np>The picture on the left imitates a fisheye camera with a 170-degree field of view.
On the right the field of view is 330-degrees, so that pixels near the edge
of the disk actually show parts of the cube that lie behind the camera.</np>

<p>For each picture, the program draws a square with texture coordinates ranging from 0.0 to 1.0.
In the texture coordinate system, pixels at a distance greater than 0.5 from the point (0.5,0.5)
are colored white.  Within the disk of radius 0.5, each circle around the center is mapped
to a circle on the unit sphere.  That point is then used
as the direction vector for sampling the cubemap texture.  The point in the texture that appears at the center
of the disk is the point  where the cube intersects the positive z-axis, that is, 
the center of the "positive z" image from the cube map.  You don't actually need to understand
this, but here, for your information, is the fragment shader that does the work:</p>

<pre>#ifdef GL_FRAGMENT_PRECISION_HIGH
    precision highp float;
#else
    precision mediump float;
#endif
uniform samplerCube u_texture;  
uniform float u_angle;  // field of view angle
varying vec2 v_texCoords;  
void main() {
   float dist =  distance( v_texCoords, vec2(0.5) );
   if (dist > 0.5)
       gl_FragColor = vec4(1.0);  // white
   else {
       float x,y; // coords relative to a center at (0.5,0.5)
       x = v_texCoords.x - 0.5; 
       y = v_texCoords.y - 0.5;
       vec2 circ = normalize(vec2(x,y));  // on the unit circle
       float phi = radians(u_angle/2.0)*(2.0*dist);  // "latitude"
       vec3 vector = vec3(sin(phi)*circ.x, sin(phi)*circ.y, cos(phi));
       gl_FragColor = textureCube( u_texture, vector );  
    } 
}</pre>

</subsection>




<subsection title="A Computational Example" id="webgl.4.5">

<p>A GPU can offer an immense amount of processing power.  Although GPUs
were originally designed to apply that power to rendering images, it was
quickly realized that the same power could be harnessed to do much more
general types of programming.  Not every programming task can take
advantage of the highly parallel architecture of the typical GPU, but
if a task can be broken down into many subtasks that can be run in
parallel, then it might be possible to speed up the task significantly
by adapting it to run on a GPU.  Modern GPUs have become much more
computationally versatile, but in GPUs that were designed to work
only with colors, that might mean somehow representing the data
for a computation as color values.  The trick often involves
representing the data as colors in a texture, and accessing the
data using texture lookup functions.</p>

<p>The sample program <sourceref href="webgl/webgl-game-of-life.html"/> 
is a simple example of this approach.  The program implements
John Conway's well-known 
<tex>Game of Life</tex><web><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conway%27s_Game_of_Life">Game of Life</a></web>
(which is not really a game).  A Life board consists of a grid of cells that can be either
alive or dead.  There is a set of rules that takes the current state, or "generation," of
the board and produces a new generation.  Once some initial state has been assigned to each
cell, the game can play itself, producing generation after generation, according to the
rules.  The rules compute the state of a cell in the next generation from the
states of the cell and its eight neighboring cells in the current generation.  To 
apply the rules, you have to look at each neighboring cell and count the 
number of neighbors that are alive.  The same process is applied to every
cell, so it is a highly parallelizable task that can be easily adapted to run
on a GPU.</p>

<p>In the sample program, the Life board is a 1024-by-1024 canvas, with each pixel
representing a cell. Living cells are colored white, and dead cells are black. 
The program uses WebGL to compute the next generation of the board from the
current board.  The work is done in a fragment shader.  To trigger the
computation, a single square is drawn that covers the entire canvas, which
causes the fragment shader to be called for every pixel in the canvas.
The fragment shader needs access to the current color of the fragment and
of its eight neighbors, but it has no way to query those colors directly.
To give the shader access to that information, the program copies the
board into a texture object, using the function <i>gl.copyTexImage2D()</i>.
The fragment shader can then get the information that it needs using
the GLSL texture lookup function <i>texture2D()</i>.</p>

<p>An interesting point is that the fragment shader needs the texture coordinates
not just for itself but for its neighbors.  The texture coordinates for the
fragment itself are passed into the fragment shader as a varying variable, with
values in the range 0 to 1 for each coordinate.  It can get the texture coordinates for a neighbor
by adding an offset to its own texture coordinates.  Since the texture is
1024-by-1024 pixels, the texture coordinates for a neighbor need to be offset
by 1.0/1024.0.  Here is the complete GLSL&nbsp;ES&nbsp;1.00 fragment shader program:</p>

<pre>#ifdef GL_FRAGMENT_PRECISION_HIGH
   precision highp float;
#else
   precision mediump float;
#endif
varying vec2 v_coords;     // texture coordinates for this cell
const float scale = 1.0/1024.0;  // 1.0 / canvas_size; (offset between 
                                 //   neighboring cells, in texture coords)
uniform sampler2D source;  // the texture holding the previous generation

void main() {
    int alive;  // is this cell alive ?
    if (texture2D(source,v_coords).r > 0.0)
       alive = 1;
    else
       alive = 0;
       
    // Count the living neighbors.  To check for living, just test
    // the red component of the color, which will be 1.0 for a
    // living cell and 0.0. for a dead cell.
       
    int neighbors = 0; // will be the number of neighbors that are alive
    
    if (texture2D(source,v_coords+vec2(scale,scale)).r > 0.0)
       neighbors += 1;
    if (texture2D(source,v_coords+vec2(scale,0)).r > 0.0)
       neighbors += 1;
    if (texture2D(source,v_coords+vec2(scale,-scale)).r > 0.0)
       neighbors += 1;
       
    if (texture2D(source,v_coords+vec2(0,scale)).r > 0.0)
       neighbors += 1;
    if (texture2D(source,v_coords+vec2(0,-scale)).r > 0.0)
       neighbors += 1;
       
    if (texture2D(source,v_coords+vec2(-scale,scale)).r > 0.0)
       neighbors += 1;
    if (texture2D(source,v_coords+vec2(-scale,0)).r > 0.0)
       neighbors += 1;
    if (texture2D(source,v_coords+vec2(-scale,-scale)).r > 0.0)
       neighbors += 1;
    
    // Output the new color for this cell. using the rules of Life.
       
    float color = 0.0; // color for dead cell
    if (alive == 1) {
        if (neighbors == 2 || neighbors == 3)
           color = 1.0; // color for living cell; cell stays alive
    }
    else if ( neighbors == 3 )
        color = 1.0; // color for living cell; cell comes to life
        
    gl_FragColor = vec4(color, color, color, 1);
}
</pre>

<p>There are some other points of interest in the program.  When the
WebGL graphics context is created, anti-aliasing is turned off to
make sure that every pixel is either perfectly black or perfectly
white. Antialiasing could smear out the colors by averaging the
colors of nearby pixels.  Similarly, the magnification and minification
filters for the texture are set to <i>gl.NEAREST</i> to avoid averaging
of colors.  Also, there is the issue of setting the initial configuration
onto the board&mdash;that's done by drawing onto the board using
another shader program with a different fragment shader.</p>

<p>On my computer, the <sourceref href="webgl/webgl-game-of-life.html"/>
can easily compute 360 generations per second.  I urge you to try it.  It can be fun to watch.</p>

<p>General purpose programming on GPUs has become more and more important.
Modern GPUs can do computations that have nothing to do with color,
using various numerical data types.  WebGL&nbsp;2.0, as we'll see, has
moved a bit in that direction, but accessing the full computational power
of GPUs from the Web will require a new API.  <newword>WebGPU</newword>,
currently under development and already available as an experimental
feature in some web browsers, is an attempt to fulfill that need.
(However, unlike WebGL, it is not based on OpenGL.)
</p>

</subsection>




<subsection title="Textures in WebGL 2.0" id="webgl.4.6">

<p>One of the major changes in WebGL 2.0 is greatly increased support
for textures.  A large number of new texture formats have been added.
RGBA color components in OpenGL are represented as floating point
values in the range zero to one, but in practice are often stored as
one-byte unsigned integers, with values in the range 0 to 255,
which matches the format that is used for displaying colors on
most screens.  In fact, you don't really have control over
how colors are represented internally for use on displays.
There have been computer displays that used only 16 bits per pixel
instead of 32, and new HDR (High Dynamic Range) displays can use even more
bits per pixel.  But when storing data in a texture, it's not really
necessary to match the color format that is used on a physical display.
</p>

<p>WebGL 2.0 introduced a large number of so-called "sized" texture formats,
which give the programmer control over how the data in the texture is represented.
For example, if the format is <i>gl.RGBA32F</i>, then the texture contains four 32-bit
floating point numbers for each pixel, one for each of the four RGBA color components.
The format <i>gl.R32UI</i> indicates one 32-bit unsigned integer per pixel.
And <i>gl.RG8I</i> means two 8-bit integers per pixel. And <i>gl.RGBA8</i>
corresponds to the usual format, using one 8-bit unsigned integer for each
color component. These sized formats are
used for the internal format of a texture, the <i>internalFormat</i> parameter in a call to a 
function like <i>gl.texImage2D</i>(), which specifies how the data is actually
stored in the texture.  You can use textures with sized internal formats as
image textures for rendering.  But 32 bits for a color component encodes
far more different colors than could ever be distinguished visually.
These data formats are particularly useful for computational applications,
where you really need to control what kind of data you are working with.
But to effectively compute with data stored in textures, we really need
to be able to write data to textures, as well as read from textures.
And for that, we need <word term="framebuffer">framebuffers</word>, which
won't be covered until <localref href="webgl3d.4"/>.  For now, we will just
look at a few aspects of the WebGL&nbsp;2.0 API for working with textures.
</p>

<p>Various versions of the <i>texImage2D</i>() function can be used to initialize
a texture from an image or from an array of data&mdash;or to zero, when no data source
is provided.  WebGL&nbsp;2.0 has another, potentially more efficient, function for
allocating the storage for a texture and initializing it to zero:</p>

<pre>gl.texStorage2D( target, levels, internalFormat, width, height );</pre>

<np>The first parameter is <i>gl.TEXTURE_2D</i> or <i>gl.TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP</i>.
The second parameter specifies the number of mipmap level that should be generated;
generally, this will be&nbsp;1.  The <i>width</i> and <i>height</i> give the
size of the texture, and of course the <i>internalFormat</i> specifies
the data format for the texture.  The <i>internalFormat</i> must be one
of the sized internal formats, such as <i>gl.RGBA8</i>.</np>

<p>WebGL 2.0 has support for 3D textures, which hold data for a 3D grid of 
<word term="texel">texels</word>, with functions <i>gl.texImage3D</i>() and
<i>gl.texStorage3D()</i>.  It has depth textures, which store depth values 
like those used in the <word>depth test</word> and are commonly used for
<word>shadow mapping</word>.  And it can work with compressed textures, which
can decrease the amount of data that needs to be transferred between the
CPU and the GPU.  However, I will leave you to explore these capabilities
on your own if you need them.</p>

<p>Shader programs use <word term="sampler variable">sampler variables</word> to 
read data from textures.  The shader programming language GLSL&nbsp;ES&nbsp;3.00 
introduces a number of new sampler types to deal with the new texture
formats in WebGL&nbsp;2.0.  Where GLSL&nbsp;ES&nbsp;1.00 had only <ptype>sampler2D</ptype>
and <ptype>samplerCube</ptype>, the newer language adds types such as  <ptype>sampler3D</ptype>
for 3D textures, <ptype>isampler2D</ptype> for sampling textures whose values are 
signed integers, and <ptype>sampler2DShadow</ptype> for sampling depth textures.  For
example, for sampling a texture with a 32-bit integer format, you might
declare a sampler variable such as
</p>

<pre>uniform highp isampler2D datatexture;</pre>

<np>The <word>precision qualifier</word>, <i>highp</i>, must be specified because
<i>isampler2D</i> variables do not have a default precision.  Using high precision
ensures that you can read 32-bit integers exactly.  (The <i>sampler2D</i> type has
default precision <i>lowp</i>, which is sufficient when color components
are really 8-bit integers but which might not be what you want for floating
point data textures.)</np>

<p>GLSL ES 1.00 uses the function <i>texture2D</i>() to sample a 2D texture
and <i>textureCube</i>() for sampling a cubemap texture.  Rather than have
a separate function for each sampler type, GLSL&nbsp;ES&nbsp;3.00 removes
<i>texture2D</i> and <i>textureCube</i> and replaces them with a single
overloaded function <i>texture</i>(), which can be used to sample any kind
of texture.  So, the <i>datatexture</i> defined above might be sampled
using</p>

<pre>highp ivec4 data = texture( datatexture, coords );</pre>

<np>where <i>coords</i> is a <ptype>vec2</ptype> holding the texture coordinates.
But in fact, you might want to access texel values more directly.  There is
a new <i>texelFecth</i>() function that fetches texel values from a texture,
treating the texture as an array of texels.  Texels are accessed using integer
coordinates that range from 0 up to the size of the texture.  Applied to
<i>datatexture</i>, this could look like
</np>

<pre>highp ivec4 data = texelFetch( datatexture, 0, ivec2(i,j) );</pre>

<np>where <i>i</i> ranges from 0 to the width of the texture minus one, and <i>j</i>
ranges from 0 to the height minus one.  The second parameter, 0&nbsp;here, specifies
the mipmap level that is being accessed.  (For integer textures, you are not likely
to be using mipmaps.)</np>

<p>(The sample program <sourceref href="webgl/texelFetch-MonaLisa-webgl2.html"/>
is a rather fanciful example of using <i>texelFetch</i>(), though with an ordinary image
texture rather than a data texture.)</p>

<p>There is a lot more that could be said about WebGL 2.0 textures, but it would
take us well beyond what I need for this introductory textbook.</p>

</subsection>

</section>

