<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE intro SYSTEM "../graphicstext.dtd" >

<intro>

<p1>This chapter introduces <newword>WebGPU</newword>, 
the new graphics <word>API</word> for the web.
WebGPU has been under development for several years, but it is only
recently that it has begun to be included as a standard feature in
web browsers.  In some browsers, you might find that it is
available as an experimental feature that has to be explicitly 
enabled before it can be used.  Some browsers might not support
it at all.</p1>

<p>WebGPU will not replace <word>WebGL</word>, which will continue to be well-supported
in almost all browsers for the foreseeable future.  However, WebGL,
like the OpenGL API on which it is based, is not likely to see much
further development.  WebGPU, on the other hand, is inspired by and
similar to modern graphics APIs such as <word>Vulkan</word>, <word>Direct3D</word>,
and <word>Metal</word>, and it is likely to evolve along with those APIs.
So WebGPU should be thought of as the Web graphics API of the future.</p>

<p>WebGPU is similar to WebGL in many ways. For example, it has
<word term="vertex shader">vertex shaders</word> and 
<word term="fragment shader">fragment shaders</word>,
and a lot of the programmer's work involves managing the flow
of data into and through the rendering <word>pipeline</word>.
But WebGPU is an even lower level API than WebGL.
It is more verbose, and it puts more responsibility on the 
programmer for managing details of the rendering process.  At
the same time, however, it gives the programmer more control,
access to more powerful capabilities of modern <word term="GPU">GPUs</word>, 
and the possibility of more efficient code.</p>

<p>The WebGPU specification is at
<a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/webgpu/">https://www.w3.org/TR/webgpu/</a>,
but it is not very useful for learning.  A simpler and more useful API reference can
be found on the Mozilla Developer Network:
<a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/WebGPU_API">https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/WebGPU_API</a>.
Hopefully, though, this chapter has enough information to get you
started with WebGPU.</p>

</intro>
