<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../graphicstext.dtd" >

<section id="webgpu.3" title="WGSL">

<p1><newword>WGSL</newword> is the shader programming language for <word>WebGPU</word>.  
It has control structures that
are similar to those in C and JavaScript, with some changes and additions.  And it has
data types and a large set of built in functions that are similar to those in
<word>GLSL</word>.  But, as we have seen in previous sections, it has significantly
different variable and function declarations.</p1>

<p>This rather technical section covers major aspects of the syntax and semantics of 
WGSL.  Note that the parts of the language that deal with textures are not covered
here; they are postponed until the <localref href="webgpu.4">next section</localref>.
And some details about working with <word term="compute shader">compute shaders</word>
are postponed until <localref href="webgpu.6"/>.
I will assume that you are already familiar with a language like C or JavaScript,
but see <localref href="proglang"/> if you need a refresher.
Familiarity with GLSL (<localref href="webgl.3"/>) would also be useful, but not essential.
While I do not give a complete specification of the WGSL language, I try to 
cover most of the important features.  For the very long complete specification,
see <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/WGSL/">https://www.w3.org/TR/WGSL/</a>.</p>

<subsection title="Address Spaces and Alignment" id="webgpu.3.1">

<p>To avoid a lot of frustration when working with WGSL data values, you will need to 
understand two aspects of WGSL that are not common in other programming languages: 
<word term="address space (in WGSL)">address spaces</word> and 
<word term="alignment (in WGSL)">alignment</word>.</p>

<p>Memory that is accessible to a <word>GPU</word> is divided into address spaces, which have
different accessibility rules and which might be physically accessed in different ways.
Every variable lives in a particular address space, and that address space is part of the
variable's type.  For example, we have seen how a global variable can be declared using 
<code>var&lt;uniform&gt;</code>.  That variable lives in the <i>uniform</i> address space,
which holds values that generally come from the JavaScript side of the program.  Here are the
available address spaces:</p>

<ul>

<li><b>function</b> address space &mdash; The <i>function</i> address space is for
local variables and parameters in functions.  It is basically the function call stack
for a single processor in the GPU, which is stored in the dedicated local memory for that processor.
Local variables can be declared using
<code>var&lt;function&gt;</code>, but the <i>function</i> address space is the only 
possibility for local variables, and they can declared using simply <code>var</code>.</li>

<li><b>private</b> address space &mdash; The <i>private</i> address space is used for
global variables in shader programs, but each GPU processor has its own copy of the
variable, stored in the dedicated local memory for that processor.
As a global variable, a variable declared using <code>var&lt;private&gt;</code> can be used
in any function in the shader program, but a given copy of the variable is only shared by
function calls in the same invocation of the shader.</li>

<li><b>uniform</b> address space &mdash; The <i>uniform</i> address space holds global
variables that are shared by all GPU processors.  Uniform variables are read-only.  A variable
declaration using <code>var&lt;uniform&gt;</code> cannot include an initial value for the
variable, and a shader cannot assign a new value to the variable.  The values in a uniform
variable are "resources" that come from a bind group, and every every uniform variable declaration
must have  <code>@group</code> and <code>@binding</code> annotations that are used to
specify the source of the resource.</li>

<li><b>storage</b> address space &mdash; The <i>storage</i> address space is similar to
the <i>uniform</i> space.  Storage variables require <code>@group</code> and <code>@binding</code>
annotations and cannot be assigned an initial value in the shader program.  Storage variables
by default are read-only, but read-write access is also possible.  (A storage variable with
read-write access can be used in fragment and compute shaders, but not in vertex shaders.)
A storage variable with read-write access is declared using <code>var&lt;storage,read_write&gt;</code>.</li>

<li><b>workgroup</b> address space &mdash; This address space can only be used in
compute shaders and will be covered later.</li>

</ul>

<p>Values for uniform and storage variables come from bind groups.  The JavaScript side
of the program provides their values using buffers, bind groups, and bind group
layouts (<localref href="webgpu.1.3"/>).  There are certain requirements: For a uniform variable, the <code>usage</code>
property of the buffer in <code>device.createBuffer() </code>
must include <code>GPUBufferUsage.UNIFORM</code>, and the buffer
in the bind group layout must have its <code>type</code> property set to "uniform" (which
is the default).  In the bind group itself, the <code>offset</code> property for each
entry must be a multiple of 256.  This is an example of an alignment rule.
For example, if there are two uniform variables in the shader program</p>

<pre>@group(0) @binding(0) var&lt;uniform&gt; x : f32;
@group(0) @binding(1) var&lt;uniform&gt; y : f32;</pre>

<np>and if one buffer is used to hold both variables, then the  buffer must 
be at least 300 bytes and the bind group would be something like</np>

<pre>bindGroup = device.createBindGroup({
   layout: bindGroupLayout,
   entries: [{
      binding: 0,
      resource: {
         buffer: buffer, offset: 0, size: 4
      }
   },
   {
      binding: 1,
      resource: {
         buffer: buffer, offset: <b>256</b>, size: 4
      }
   }]
});</pre>

<np>For storage variables the alignment rule is the same.  The <code>usage</code> when
creating the buffer must include <code>GPUBufferUsage.STORAGE</code>.  And the
<code>type</code> in the bind group layout must be "read-only-storage" for the
default read-only storage variables, or "storage" for read-write storage variables.</np>

<break/>

<p>In addition to the alignment rule for uniform and storage bindings, GLSL has
alignment rules for its data types.  The alignment value for a data type can be
4, 8, or 16.  An alignment is always a power of&nbsp;2.
(Alignment 2 is also possible for a 16-bit floating point type that
can only be used if a language extension is enabled; 16-bit floats are not
covered in this textbook.)  If the alignment for a data type is N, then
the memory address of any value of that type must be a multiple of&nbsp;N.
When the value is part of a data structure, the offset of that value from 
the start of the data structure must be a multiple of&nbsp;N.</p>

<p>Ordinarily, you will only need to worry about alignment for data structures
in the uniform or storage address space.  But in that case, knowing the
alignment is essential, since you have to take it into account on the JavaScript
side when writing data to buffers.</p>

<p>The basic (scalar) data types in WGSL are 4-byte integers and floats, which have
alignment&nbsp;4.  WGSL has vectors of 2, 3, an 4 scalar values, which have size
8, 12, and 16.  The alignments for 2-vectors and 4-vectors are 8 and 16, as you
might expect.  But the size of a 3-vector is 12, which is not a legal alignment,
so the alignment for 3-vectors is 16.  That is, the address in memory of the
first byte of a 3-vector must be a multiple of 16.</p>

<p>For an array data structure, the elements of the array must be aligned within the
array.  This means that in an array of 3-vectors, each element must start
at a multiple of 16 bytes from the start of the array.  Since a 3-vector
such as a <code>vec3f</code> only occupies 12 bytes, four extra bytes of padding must be inserted after
each element.  No padding is needed in an array of 2-vectors or 4-vectors.
So, an array of <code>vec3f</code> takes up just as much memory as an array
of <code>vec4f</code> with the same number of elements.  The alignment of an 
array type is equal to the alignment of its elements.</p>

<p>For structs, each element of the struct must satisfy the alignment rule for
the data type of that element, which might require padding between some elements.
The alignment for the struct itself is the maximum of the alignments of its
elements. And the size of the struct must be a multiple of its alignment, which
might require some padding at the end.</p>

<p>Let's look at an example that might appear in a shader program that does
3D graphics (see the <localref href="webgpu.4">next section</localref>).
Some of the syntax has not been covered yet, but you should be able to 
follow it:</p>

<pre>struct LightProperties {
    position : vec4f,      //  size 16,  offset  0
    color : vec3f,         //  size 12,  offset 16 bytes (4 floats)
    spotDirection: vec3f,  //  size 12,  offset 32 bytes (8 floats)
    spotCosineCutoff: f32, //  size  4,  offset 44 bytes (11 floats)
    spotExponent: f32,     //  size  4,  offset 48 bytes (12 floats)
    enabled : f32          //  size  4,  offset 52 bytes (13 floats)
}

@group(0) @binding(0) var&lt;uniform&gt; lights : array&lt;LightProperties,4&gt;</pre>

<np>The first <code>vec3f</code> in the struct, <code>color</code>, ends with byte
number 27, but the next <code>vec3f</code>, <code>spotDirection</code>,
can't start at byte 28 because the alignment rule says that it must start
at a multiple of 32. So, four bytes of padding are added.  Then, <code>spotDirection</code>
starts at byte number 32 and ends with byte number 43.  The next element is the 32-bit float
<code>spotCosineCutoff</code>, with alignment 4, and it can start at the next
byte number,&nbsp;44.  Note that there is no padding after <code>spotDirection</code>.
The alignment rule for <code>vec3f</code> does <b>not</b> say that every 
<code>vec3f</code> is followed by four bytes of padding.  Alignment rules
are restrictions on where a variable can start.  (Yes, this example did trip me
up the first time I tried it.)</np>

<p>The array in the example, <code>lights</code>, is an array of four
structs of type <code>LightProperties</code>.  The alignment for a
<code>LightProperties</code> struct is 16 (the maximum of the alignments
of its elements).  The size, which must be a multiple of the alignment,
is 64, with 8 bytes of padding at the end.  The size of the array
is therefore 256 bytes, or 64 32-bit floats.  On the JavaScript side,
data for the WGSL array could come from a <code>Float32Array</code>
of length 64.  When storing values into that <code>Float32Array</code>,
you would have to be very careful to take the data alignments into
account.</p>

<p>WGSL also has data types for matrices of floating point values.  
A matrix in WGSL is essentially an array of column vectors, and 
it follows the same alignment rules.  In particular, a matrix
with 3 rows is an array of <code>vec3f</code>, with four bytes of
padding after each column.  This will become important when we work 
with normal transformation metrics in 3D graphics.</p>

</subsection>



<subsection title="Data Types" id="webgpu.3.2">

<p>The basic, or "scalar," types in WGSL include the boolean type, <code>bool</code>,
with values <code>true</code> and <code>false</code>; the 32-bit unsigned integer type,
<code>u32</code>; the 32-bit signed integer type, <code>i32</code>; and the
32-bit floating point type, <code>f32</code>.  Note in particular that there are no
8-bit, 16-bit, or 64-bit numeric types (although a 16-bit floating point type,
<code>f16</code>, is available as a language extension).</p>

<p>The <code>bool</code> type is not "host sharable," which means that a variable of
type <code>bool</code> cannot be in the storage or uniform address space, and it can't
get its value from the JavaScript side.  This also means that any data structure that 
includes a <code>bool</code> cannot be in the storage or uniform address space.</p>

<p>Literals of integer type can be written in the usual decimal form, or in 
hexadecimal form with a leading <code>0x</code> or <code>0X</code>.  An integer
literal of type <code>u32</code> is written with a "u" suffix, and one of type
<code>i32</code> with an "i" suffix.  Some examples:  17i, 0u, 0xfadeu, 0X7Fi.
Integer literals without suffixes are also possible; they are considered to be
"abstract integers."  Curiously, an abstract integer can be automatically converted
into a <code>u32</code>, <code>i32</code>, or <code>f32</code>, even though
WGSL will not do automatic conversions between the regular types.
So, if <code>N</code> is a variable of type <code>f32</code>,
then the expression <code>N+2</code> is legal, with the abstract integer <code>2</code> 
being automatically converted into an <code>f32</code>. But the expression <code>N+2u</code> 
is illegal because the <code>u32</code> <code>2u</code> is not automatically converted 
to&nbsp;<code>f32</code>.  The main point of abstract integers seems to be to make
it possible to write expressions involving constants in a more natural way.</p>

<p>Floating point literals include either a decimal point, or an exponent, or an "f" suffix."
A floating point literal with an "f" suffix has type <code>f32</code>.  Without
the suffix, it is an "abstract float," which can be automatically converted to
type <code>f32</code>.  Examples include: .0, 17.0, 42f, 0.03e+10f.  (There are also
hexadecimal floating point literals, but they are not covered here.)</p>

<break/>

<p>WGSL has vector types with 2, 3, and 4 elements.  The elements in a vector can be any scalar
type: <code>bool</code>, <code>u32</code>, <code>i32</code>, or <code>f32</code>.  The vector
types have official names like <code>vec3&lt;f32&gt;</code> for a vector of three <code>f32</code> values
and <code>vec4&lt;bool&gt;</code> for a vector of four <code>bools</code>.  But the type
names for numeric vectors have "aliases" that are more commonly used instead of the official names:
<code>vec4f</code> is an alias for <code>vec4&lt;f32&gt;</code>, <code>vec2i</code> is an alias for 
<code>vec2&lt;i32&gt;</code>.</p>

<p>Vectors are similar to arrays, and the elements of a vector can be referred to using
array notation.  For example, if <code>V</code> is a <code>vec4f</code>, then its
elements are <code>V[0]</code>, <code>V[1]</code>, <code>V[2]</code>, and <code>V[3]</code>.
The elements can also be referred to using <word term="swizzler">swizzlers</word> as
<code>V.x</code>, <code>V.y</code>, <code>V.z</code>, and <code>V.w</code>.
By using multiple letters after the dot, you can construct vectors made up of
selected elements of <code>V</code>.  For example, <code>V.yx</code> is a <code>vec4f</code>
containing the first two elements of <code>V</code> in reversed order, and
<code>V.zzzz</code> is a <code>vec4f</code> made up of four copies of the third element of&nbsp;<code>V</code>.
The letters <code>rgba</code> can also be used, instead of <code>xyzw</code>.
(All this is similar to GLSL, <localref href="webgl.3.1"/>.)</p>

<p>WGSL also has matrix types, but only for matrices of floating point values.
There are types for N-by-M matrices for all a N and M equal to 2, 3, or&nbsp;4,
with official names like <code>mat3x2&lt;f32&gt;</code> and <code>mat4x4&lt;f32&gt;</code>.
But again these types have simpler aliases like <code>mat3x2f</code> and <code>mat4x4f</code>.</p>

<p>The elements of an array are stored in column-major order: the elements of the first column,
followed by the elements of the second column, and so on.  Each column is a vector, and the
column vectors can be accessed using array notation.  For example, if <code>M</code> is
a <code>mat4x4f</code>, then <code>M[1]</code> is the <code>vec4f</code> that is the second
column of <code>M</code>, and <code>M[1][0]</code> is the first element of that vector.</p>

<break/>

<p>For building data structures, WGSL has arrays and structs.  The data type for
an array with element type <code>T</code> and length <code>N</code> is
<code>array&lt;T,N&gt;</code>.  The array length must be a constant.  Array types
without a length are also possible, but only in the storage address space.
Array elements are referred to as usual; for example, <code>A[i]</code>.</p>

<p>A struct data type contains a list of member declarations, which can be of
different types.  See, for example, the definition of the <code>LightProperties</code>
type, above.  A member can be a scalar, a vector, a matrix, an array, or a struct.
Members are accessed using the usual dot notation.  For example, if
<code>L</code> is of type <code>LightProperties</code>, then <code>L.color</code>
is the <code>color</code> member of <code>L</code>.  I will note that the 
individual members of a struct can have annotations.  For example,</p>

<pre>struct VertexOutput {
   @builtin(position) position: vec4f,
   @location(0) color : vec3f
}</pre>

<break/>

<p>WGSL has pointer types, but as far as I can tell, they can only be used for
the types of formal parameters in function definitions.  A pointer type name 
takes the form <code>ptr&lt;A,T&gt;</code>, where <code>A</code> is an a
address space and <code>T</code> is a type; for example:  
<code>ptr&lt;function,i32&gt;</code> or <code>ptr&lt;private,array&lt;f32,5&gt;&gt;</code>.
A pointer of type <code>ptr&lt;A,T&gt;</code> can only point to a value of type
<code>T</code> in address space&nbsp;<code>A</code>.</p>

<p>If <code>P</code> is a pointer, then <code>*P</code> is the value that it
points to.  If <code>V</code> is a variable, then <code>&amp;V</code> is a pointer
to&nbsp;<code>V</code>.  Pointer types can be used to implement pass-by-reference
to a function.  For example,</p>

<pre>fn array5sum( A : ptr&lt;function,array&lt;f32,5&gt;&gt; ) -> f32 {
    var sum = 0;
    for (var i = 0; i &lt; 5; i++) {
        sum += (*A)[i];
    }
    return sum;
}</pre>

<np>Note the use of <code>*A</code> to name the array that <code>A</code> points to.
The parentheses in <code>(*A)[i]</code> are required by precedence rules.  This
function could be called as <code>array5sum(&amp;Nums)</code>
where <code>Nums</code> is a variable of type <code>array&lt;f32,5&gt;</code> in
the function address space.  (That is, <code>Nums</code> must be a local variable.)</np>

<break/>

<p>Scalar types, vectors, matrices, arrays, and structs are constructible.  That is,
a value of the given type can be constructed from an appropriate list of values.
The notation looks like a function call, with the function name being the name of
the type. Here are some examples:</p>

<pre>var a = u32(23.67f);           // a is 23u
var b = f32(a);                // b is 23.0f
var c = vec3f(1, 2, 3);        // the abstract ints 1,2,3 are converted to f32
var d = vec4f(c.xy, 0, 1);     // c.xy contributes two values to the vec4f
var e = mat2x2f(1, 0, 0, 1);   // constructs the 2-by-2 identity matrix
var f = mat3x3f(c, c, c);      // each column of f is the vec3f c
var g = array&lt;u32,4&gt;(1,2,3,4); // construct an array of length 4
var h = MyStruct( 17u, 42f );  // MyStruct is a struct made of a u32 and an f32
var i = vec4i(2);              // Same as vec4i(2,2,2,2); the 2 is repeated</pre>

</subsection>



<subsection title="Declarations and Annotations" id="webgpu.3.3">

<p>We have seen how to declare variables using <code>var&lt;A&gt;</code>, where
<code>A</code> is an address space.  Local variables in functions can be
declared using either <code>var&lt;function&gt;</code> or simply <code>var</code>.
For global variables, an address space&mdash;private, uniform, storage, or
workgroup&mdash;is required.</p>

<p>The type of a variable can be specified in a declaration by following
the variable name with a colon and then the name of the type.  For example</p>

<pre>var&lt;private&gt; sum : f32;</pre>

<np>The declaration of a variable in the function or private address space
can include an initial value for the variable.  The initial value can
be a constant, a variable, or an expression.  When an initial value is
included in the declaration, the type of the variable generally does not have
to be specified because the GLSL compiler can determine the type from the
initial value.  When a variable is initialized using an abstract int,
and no type is specified, the type is taken to be <code>i32.</code></np>

<p>In a function body, an identifier can be declared using <code>let</code>
instead of <code>var</code>.  The result is a named value rather than
a variable.  A&nbsp;<code>let</code> declaration must in include an initial
value.  The value cannot be changed after initialization.  The declaration
can optionally include a type.  An address space cannot be specified.
Using <code>let</code> makes it clear that you do not expect the
value to change and makes it impossible to change the value accidently.</p>

<p>Named values can also be declared using <code>const</code>, but the
initial value in a <code>const</code> declaration must be a constant that
is known at compile time.  The initial value can be given as an expression,
as long as the expression only contains constants.  While <code>let</code>
can only be used in functions, <code>const</code> declarations can 
be used anywhere.</p>

<p>A declaration can only declare one identifier.  So something like
"<code>var a = 1, b = 2;</code>" is not legal.  This applies to
<code>const</code> and <code>let</code>, as well as to <code>var</code>.</p>

<break/>

<p>We have seen that annotations like <code>@location(0)</code> can be 
used on variable declarations, function definitions, function formal parameters, 
and the return type of a function.  (The WGSL documentation calls them "attributes", but I prefer
to save the term "attribute" for vertex attributes.) This textbook only covers the
most common annotations.  We encountered some of them in previous
sections, and a few more will come up later when we discuss compute shaders.</p>

<ul>
<li><code>group(N)</code> and <code>@binding(M)</code>, where N and M are integers,
are used on <code>var</code> declarations in the uniform and storage address spaces
to specify the source of resource.  The association is specified by a bind group layout.
See <localref href="webgpu.1.3"/>.</li>
<li><code>@vertex</code>, <code>@fragment</code>, and <code>@compute</code> 
are used on a function definition to specify that that function can be used as
the entry point function for a vertex, fragment, or compute shader.
See <localref href="webgpu.1.2"/>.</li>
<li><code>@location(N)</code>, where N is an integer, can be used on inputs and outputs
of vertex shader and fragment shader entry point functions.  It can be applied to
their formal parameters and return types and to members of structs that
are used to specify the type of their formal parameters and return types.
The meaning depends on context.  On an input to a vertex shader entry point function, it
specifies the source of the input in a vertex buffer (<localref href="webgpu.1.6"/>).
On a fragment shader entry point function, it specifies the color attachment that is the
destination of that output (<localref href="webgpu.1.3"/>.)
And when used on a vertex shader output or a fragment shader input,
it associates a particular output of the vertex shader with the corresponding
input to the fragment shader (<localref href="webgpu.1.6"/>).</li>
<li><code>@interpolate(flat)</code> can be applied to an output from the
vertex shader entry point function and the corresponding input to the fragment shader
program.  If it is applied to one, it must be applied to both.  Usually, the
values for a fragment shader input are interpolated from the output values of
the vertex shader at all vertices of the triangle or line that
is being drawn.  The <code>@interpolate(flat)</code> annotation turns off
interpolation; instead, the value from the first vertex is used for all fragments.
This annotation is required for values of integer or boolean type and can also
be applied to floating point values.</li>
<li><code>@builtin(vertex_index)</code> and <code>@builtin(instance_index)</code> 
are used on inputs to a vertex shader entry point function to specify the vertex number
or instance number that is being processed.  See <localref href="webgpu.2.4"/>.</li>
<li><code>@builtin(position)</code>  when used on an output from a
vertex shader entry point function specifies that the output is the (x,y,z,w) coordinates
of the vertex in the clip coordinate system.
Every vertex shader entry point function is required to have an output with this annotation.
When used on an input to a fragment shader program, it specifies that
the input is the interpolated position of the fragment being processed, 
in viewport coordinates. (See <localref href="webgpu.4.2"/> for a discussion
of coordinate systems in WebGPU.)</li>
<li><code>@builtin(front_facing)</code> is used on an input of type <code>bool</code> to a fragment
shader program.  The value will be true if the fragment that is being processed is part
of a <word term="front face">front facing</word> triangle.
This can be useful, for example, when doing two-sided lighting in 
3D graphics (<localref href="webgl3d.2.4"/>).</li>
</ul>

</subsection>




<subsection title="Expressions and Built-in Functions" id="webgpu.3.4">

<p>WGSL has all the familiar arithmetic, logical, bitwise, and comparison operators:
<code>+,&nbsp;-,&nbsp;*, /, %, &amp;&amp;, ||, !, &amp;, |, ~, ^, &lt;&lt;, >>, ==, !=, &lt;, >,&nbsp;&lt;=,&nbsp;>=</code>.
It does not have the conditional <code>?:</code> operator, but it has an equivalent built-in
function, <code>select(false_case,true_case,boolean)</code>.  Note that assignment (<code>=</code>,
<code>+=</code>, etc.) is not an operator; that is, <code>A&nbsp;=&nbsp;B</code> is a statement,
not an expression, and it does not have a value like it would in C or JavaScript.</p>

<p>The interesting thing is that operators are extended in many ways to work with vectors and matrices as well as
with scalars.  For example, if <code>A</code> is an n-by-m matrix and <code>B</code> is an m-by-r matrix,
then <code>A*B</code> computes the matrix product of A and B.  And if <code>V</code> is a vector
of m floats, then <code>A*V</code> is the vector that is the linear algebra product of the matrix
and the vector.</p>

<p>The arithmetic operators can be applied to two vectors of the same numeric type.  The operation is
applied component-wise. That is,</p>

<pre>vec3f(2.0f, 3.0f, 7.0f) / vec3f(5.0f, 8.0f, 9.0f)</pre>

<np>is <code>vec3f(2.0f/5.0f, 3.0f/8.0f, 7.0f/9.0f)</code>.  Numeric vectors of the same numeric
type can also be combined using a comparison operator.  The result is a <code>bool</code> vector
of the same length.</np>

<p>Even more interesting, the arithmetic operators can be applied to a vector and a scalar.
The operation then applies to each component of the vector:
<code>2+vec2f(5,12)</code> is <code>vec2f(7,14)</code>, and
<code>vec4i(2,5,10,15)/2</code> is <code>vec4i(1,2,5,7)</code>.</p>

<p>Expressions, of course, can also include calls to functions, both built-in and 
user-defined.  WGSL has many built-in functions.  It has mathematical functions
such as <code>abs</code>, <code>cos</code>, <code>atan</code>, <code>exp</code>, <code>log</code>,
and <code>sqrt</code>.  (<code>log</code> is the natural logarithm.)
Except for <code>abs</code>, the parameter must be of floating point type.  The
parameter can be either a scalar or a vector. When it is a vector, the function
is applied component-wise: <code>sqrt(vec2f(16.0,9.0))</code> is <code>vec2f(4.0,3.0)</code>.</p>

<p>There are several built-in functions for doing linear algebra operations on vectors,
including: <code>length(v)</code> for the <word term="length of a vector">length</word> 
of vector&nbsp;<code>v</code>; <code>normalize(v)</code> for a <word>unit vector</word> pointing in
the same direction as&nbsp;<code>v</code>; <code>dot(v,w)</code> for the <word>dot product</word>
of <code>v</code> and&nbsp;<code>w</code>; <code>cross(v,w)</code> for the <word>cross product</word>
of two 3-vectors; and <code>distance(v,w)</code> for the distance between
<code>v</code> and&nbsp;<code>w</code>.  In all cases, these functions only work for vectors
of floats.  There are several functions that do operations that are common in computer graphics:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>clamp(value, min, max)</code>  clamps value to the range min to max, that is, returns value if value is
between min and max, returns min if value&nbsp;&lt;=&nbsp;min, and returns max if value&nbsp;>=&nbsp;max.</li>

<li><code>mix(a, b, blend_factor)</code> returns the weighted average of a and b, that is,
(1-blend_factor)*a + blend_factor*b.</li>

<li><code>step(edge, x)</code> returns 0 if x &lt;= edge and 1 if x > edge.</li>

<li><code>smoothstep(low_edge, high_edge, x)</code> returns 0 if x &lt; low_edge, 
returns 1 if x&nbsp;>&nbsp;high_edge, and the return value increases smoothly from 
0 to&nbsp;1 as x increases from low_edge to high_edge.</li>

<li><code>reflect(L,N)</code>, where L and N are <word term="unit vector">unit vectors</word>, computes the vector L reflected
by a surface with <word>normal vector</word>&nbsp;N.  (See <localref href="gl1light.1.4"/>, except that
the L in the illustration in that section points from the surface towards the light source, but the L in
<code>reflect(L,N)</code> points from the light source towards the surface.)</li>

<li><code>refract(L,N,ior)</code>, where L and N are unit vectors, and 
<word term="IOR">ior</word> is the ratio of indices of refraction, computes the 
<word term="refraction">refracted</word> vector when light from direction 
L hits a surface with normal V separating regions with different indices of refraction.</li>

</ul>

</subsection>


<subsection title="Statements and Control" id="webgpu.3.5">

<p>Statements in WGSL are in large part similar to those in C, but there are some 
restrictions and extensions.</p>

<p>Basic statements in WGSL include assignment (using <code>=</code>);
compound assignment (using <code>+=</code>, <code>*=</code>, etc.);
increment (using&nbsp;<code>++</code> as in <code>x++</code>); decrement (using&nbsp;<code>--</code>);
function call statements; <code>return</code> statements; <code>break</code>;
<code>continue</code>; and <code>discard</code>.  Increment and decrement are postfix only; that is,
<code>x++</code> is allowed, but not <code>++x</code>). And&mdash;like assignment statements&mdash;increment
and decrement statements are not expressions; that is, they don't have a value and cannot be used as
part of a larger expression. The <code>discard</code> statement can only be used in a fragment
shader entry point function.  It stops the output of the fragment shader from being written to its destination.</p>

<p>As for control structures, <code>for</code> loops, <code>while</code> loops, and <code>if</code> 
statements in WGSL have the
same form as in C, Java, and JavaScript, except that braces, <code>{</code>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<code>}</code>,
are always required around the body of a loop and around the statements inside an <code>if</code> statement,
even if the braces enclose just a single statement.  <code>break</code> and <code>continue</code> can be used
in loops as usual, but note that statements cannot have labels and there is no labeled <code>break</code>
or labeled <code>continue</code> statement. There is an additional looping statement in WGSL that takes the form</p>

<pre>loop {
   <bnf>statements</bnf>
}</pre>

<np>This kind of loop is exited with a <code>break</code> or <code>return</code> statement.
It is basically the same as a "<code>while(true)</code>" loop.</np>

<p>The <code>switch</code> statement in WGSL is significantly changed from its usual form.
Cases can be combined (<code>case&nbsp;1,2,3</code>).  The colon after a case is optional.
The code in each case must be enclosed in braces.  There is no fallthrough from one case to the
next in the absence of a <code>break</code> statement, so <code>break</code> statements
are optional in cases.  However, <code>break</code> and <code>return</code> can still be
used to end a case early.  A <code>default</code> case is required.  The switch expression
must be of type <code>i32</code> or <code>u32</code>, and all of the case constants must either
be of the same type, or be abstract integers.  For an example, see the
<code>switch</code> statement in the shader source code in
<sourceref href="webgpu/indices_in_shader.html"/>.</p>

<p>WGSL does not have the concept of exceptions, and there is no <code>try..catch</code> statement.</p>

</subsection>



<subsection title="Function Definitions" id="webgpu.3.6">

<p>We have seen examples of function definitions in <localref href="webgpu.1"/> and <localref href="webgpu.2"/>.
All of the examples in those sections were shader entry point functions, annotated with 
<code>@vertex</code> or <code>@fragment</code>.  It is possible to define additional functions
in a shader, and those functions can then be called in the usual way.  Note however that is
is <b>not</b> legal to call an entry point function; they can only be called by the system
as part of a a pipeline.</p>

<p>I will remark that the vertex shader and the fragment shader for a pipeline can be
defined in different shader modules.  Also, a shader module can contain any number of
shader entry points.  The entry point functions to be used by a pipeline are specified
in a pipeline descriptor (<localref href="webgpu.1.3"/>).</p>

<p>A function is defined using <code>fn</code> followed by the function name, then the
formal parameter list, followed optionally by <code>-></code>, and finally
the function body, which must be enclosed in braces.  A user-defined function, other than
an entry point function, can be called from anywhere in the same shader module.</p>

<p>There are some restrictions on functions.  Recursion, direct or indirect, is not allowed.
There is no nesting: a function definition cannot be inside another function definition.
Array parameters must have a specified size.  Pointer types for parameters must be in
the function or private namespace.  Function names can't be overloaded; that is,
you can't have two functions with the same name, even if they have different parameter lists.
Also, a function cannot have the same name as a global variable.</p>

<p>To finish this section, here are a few user-defined functions:</p>

<pre>fn invertedColor( color : vec4f ) -> vec4f { // return the inverted color
   return vec4f( 1 - color.rgb, color.a );
}

fn grayify( color : ptr&lt;function,vec4f> ) { // modify color in place
    let c = *color;
    let gray = c.r * 0.3 + c.g * 0.11 + c.b * 0.59;
    *color = vec4f( gray, gray, gray, c.a );  
}

fn min10( A : array&lt;f32,10> ) -> f32 { // parameter is passed by value!
    var min = A[0];
    for (var i = 1; i &lt; 5; i++) {
       if ( A[i] &lt; min ) {
           min = A[i];
       }
    }
    return min;
}

fn simpleLighting(N : vec3f, L : vec3f, V : vec3f, diffuse : vec3f) -> vec3f {
       // N is the unit surface normal vector.
       // L is the unit vector pointing towards the light.
       // V is the unit vector pointing towards viewer
    if ( dot(N,L) &lt;= 0 ) { // wrong side of surface to be illuminated
        return vec3f(0);   // return the zero vector
    }
    var color = diffuse * dot(N,L);
    let R = -reflect(L,N);  // reflected ray;
    if ( dot(R,V) > 0 ) { // add in specular lighting
         // specular color is gray, specular exponent is 10
       color += vec3f(0.5) * pow(dot(R,V), 10);
    }
    return color;
}</pre>

</subsection>



</section>
