<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../graphicstext.dtd">

<section id="gimp.1" title="Gimp: A 2D Painting Program">

<p1>Gimp, the Gnu Image Manipulation Program,
is a free and open-source program that has many of the capabilities of the better-known
commercial program, Adobe Photoshop. Gimp can be used both for creating images
from scratch and for modifying existing images.  This book covers only
a very limited subset of Gimp's features.  It's easy to find
documentation and tutorials on Gimp, starting with its "Help" menu.</p1>

<p>Gimp can be downloaded from <a href="https://www.gimp.org">https://www.gimp.org</a>.  It is 
available for Linux, Mac&nbsp;OS, and Windows. (For Linux, consider installing it from your
distribution's software repository.)  This section was originally written for
Gimp&nbsp;2.8.  The current stable version as of July, 2021 is Gimp&nbsp;2.10,
and version 3.00 is under development.  If you are using version 2.10, you will see additional
tools and options, but everything covered in this section is still valid.  I will note
a few differences as we go along.
User manuals are available on-line at <a href="https://docs.gimp.org/2.8/en/">https://docs.gimp.org/2.8/en</a>
and <a href="https://docs.gimp.org/2.10/en/">https://docs.gimp.org/2.10/en/</a>.
</p>

<p><b>About Gimp 2.8</b>: Note that when you start Gimp 2.8 for the first time, it will be in 
"multi-window mode."  I find it much easier to use "single-window mode,"
which organizes all of Gimp's open images and dialogs into one window.
To use it, just  enable the option "Single-Window Mode" in the "Windows" menu.
You will then see a window with a central area where you can work on
images, with dialogs along the left and right edges.  The central
editing area uses tabs when multiple images are open. 
If you ever mess up the original window layout, it can be difficult to
figure out how to get it back.  To do that:  Select the "Preferences" command
from the menu.  Go to the "Window Management" section
of the preferences.  Click "Reset Saved Window Positions to Default
Values."  Restart Gimp for the changes to take effect.  And finally,
switch back to single-window mode by selecting the option in the "Windows"
menu.</p>

<p><b>About Gimp 2.10</b>:  Gimp 2.10 will start up in single-window mode by
default, but there is still an option for multi-window mode in the "Windows" menu
if you prefer that mode.
However, I would recommend changing some interface preferences.  Open the
"Preferences" dialog from the "Edit" menu (or from the
"Gimp&nbsp;2.10" menu on Mac), and look under the "Interface" section in the list on the
left.  Under the "Toolbox" section, I strongly recommend turning off the
"Use tool groups" option.  This will let you see all the tools at once, similar
to what is shown in the image below, rather than hiding many of them in groups.
Under "Theme" in the "Interface" section, I prefer the "Light" or "System"
theme.  And under "Icon Theme", I much prefer "Color" or "Legacy".</p>

<break/>

<p>Gimp's "File" menu has a "New" command that lets you create a new image
from scratch.  You will be able to set the size of the image and other
properties, such as background color.  And there is an "Open" command
that lets you open an existing image for editing.</p>

<p>Saving is a little more problematic.  The "Save" command will save
an ".xcf" file, which is Gimp's own format.  An xcf file is not an
image, and it can only be opened with Gimp.  It saves the full
Gimp editing environment, which you need for more complex
projects if you want to be able to return to editing them later.</p>

<p>To save an image file, you should
use the "Export" or "Export As" command in the "File" menu.
If you opened an image file for editing, the "Export" command becomes
an "Overwrite" command that is used to replace the original image with
the edited version.  These commands let you save images in a wide
variety of formats.  In general, you should save your images in
JPEG or PNG format.</p>

<subsection title="Painting Tools" id="gimp.1.1">

<p>I strongly suggest that you get Gimp and experiment with it as you read
about it here!  As you experiment, remember that you can always use Control-Z to 
undo any action (Command-Z on a Mac).</p>

<p>Gimp has a wide variety of tools, which you can
find in the "Toolbox" in the upper left corner of the window.
(My discussion here assumes that you are working in single-window mode, with the
window in its original configuration.)  You can hover your mouse
over a tool button to find out what the tool is for.  Click a button to select a tool.
Click or drag the mouse on an image window to apply the selected tool.
The Toolbox also has buttons for controlling the foreground and background color.
Here is an illustration of the Toolbox with a few annotations.
The appearance of the Toolbox on your computer will depend on the version
of Gimp and on the theme that you are using, but all the tools shown here should
be available:</p>

<img src="gimp-tools.png" width="459" height="286" tex="gimp-tools.eps" texscale="0.7"/>


<np>Below the Toolbox is the "Tool Options" dialog, which contains
options for the drawing tool that is currently selected. The contents of
the dialog change when you select a new tool.  Here, for example, are the options for
the Brush tool, which is used for painting on an image in the usual sense.
(In Gimp&nbsp;2.10, you will see some additional options.)
The Brush is probably the most basic and useful tool:</np>

<img src="gimp-tool-options.png" width="467" height="518" tex="gimp-tool-options.eps" texscale="0.7"/>


<p>You'll notice that Gimp does not have tools for drawing shapes
such as rectangles and circles.  However, it is possible to draw
such shapes using <i>selections</i>.  Selection tools
can be used to select regions in the
image.  For example, click the Rectangle tool, and drag the
mouse on the image to select a rectangular region.  
One of the settings in the "Tool Options" dialog for the Rectangle Select tool allows you
to round off the corners of the rectangle.  The Ellipse
Select tool can be used to select oval-shaped regions.
The Free Select (or Lasso) tool, which is next to the Ellipse in the above image,
can be used to select polygonal regions: Just click a sequence
of points to select the vertices of the polygon, and click back
on the initial point to close the polygon.  You can also 
drag the Lasso tool to draw the outline of a region freehand.
Once you have a selection, there are many things that you 
can do with it.</p>

<p>One important fact is that when there is 
a selection, you can only draw inside the selection&mdash;the
area outside the selection is completely unaffected by painting tools, or by
anything else that you try to do the image!  If you forget about this,
you can be very confused when you try to apply a painting tool outside
the selection and it has no effect at all.</p>

<p>The Bucket Fill Tool, which looks like a spilling paint bucket,
is especially useful with selections.  After selecting the bucket tool,
set the "Affected Area" in its Tool Options dialog
to "Fill whole selection".  With that setting, clicking inside
the selected area will fill that area with color.  Another useful option is
the "Fill Type" which allows you to fill regions with either the foreground
color, the background color, or a a pattern.  To change the pattern
that is used, click on the image of the pattern, just below the
"Pattern fill" option.</p>

<p>Drawing straight lines in Gimp is a little strange.
To draw a line, click the image and immediately release the mouse button.
Then press the shift key.  Move the mouse while
holding down the shift key (without holding down any button on the
mouse).  Then click the mouse again.  A line is
drawn from the original click to the final click.  You can apply this
technique to the Brush tool as well as to other tools, such as the
Eraser.</p>

<p>The Gradient tool allows you to paint with gradients.
A <word>gradient</word> is a smoothly-changing sequence of colors, arranged in
some pattern.  Many different gradients are available in Gimp.  After selecting the Gradient tool, click the
image of the gradient in the Tool Options dialog to select the gradient that you would like to use.
Note that some of the more interesting gradients include
transparent colors, which create regions where the gradient is transparent or translucent.</p>

<p><word term="linear gradient">Linear gradients</word>, <word term="radial gradient">radial gradients</word>
and other shapes can be selected using the "Shape" setting in the gradient Tool Options.
And you can get much smoother-looking gradients by turning on the "Adaptive supersampling" option.</p> 

<p>To apply a gradient to an image, press the left mouse button at the point where you want
the color sequence to start, drag the mouse while holding down the button,
and release the button at the point where you want the color sequence to end.
Remember that you can limit the area affected by the gradient by
making a selection; that is, you can fill a shape with a gradient by creating the shape as a selection
and then applying the gradient tool.</p>

<p>The gradient tool is somewhat changed in Gimp 2.10.  By default, after you draw
a gradient, a line remains on the screen with dots along the line showing the
gradient's color stops.  You can edit the gradient by dragging the dots. Or click
one of the dots and you will get a dialog where you can edit the color.  Press return
to finish editing.  This can get annoying if you don't actually want to edit the
gradient.  If you turn on "Instant mode" in the Tool Options for the gradient tool,
then you will not get the editing option when you draw a gradient.</p>

<p>As an example of what you can do with gradients, 
here is an image that was created entirely with a few
applications of the gradient tool:</p>

<img src="gimp-gradients.png" width="256" height="256" tex="gimp-gradients.eps" texscale="0.7"/>

<np>For this picture, the background was made by selecting the gradient named "Land and Sea", 
setting the gradient Shape set to "Linear", and dragging the mouse from the bottom of the image
to the top.  The frame around the edges was made using the "Square Wood Frame"
gradient with the Shape option set to "Square". Much of the "Square Wood Frame" gradient is transparent.
The frame was made by dragging the mouse from the center of the image to the edge, but the only
opaque part of the gradient was near the edges.
The eye was made using a "Radial Eyeball" gradient with the shape set to "Radial".
And the rainbow used the "Radial Rainbow Hoop" gradient with the shape set to "Radial."
A rectangular selection was used while creating the rainbow.  Without the selection,
the rainbow would have been a full circle.  However, only part of that circle was inside the
selection, so only that part was drawn.</np>

<p>You will want to try some of the other tools as well, such as the Smudge tool,
the Eraser, and the Clone tool.  For help on using any tool, look at the
message at the bottom of the image window while using the tool.  Consult the
user manual if you want to learn more.</p>

<break/>

<p>In addition to its painting tools, Gimp has a wide variety of color manipulation tools
that apply to an entire image at once (or just to the selected part of
the image, if there is a selection).  Look for them in the "Color" menu and in the
"Filter" menu.  These tools are often used to modify the colors in photographs or to apply 
effects to images. </p>

<p>For example, the "Brightness and Contrast" command in the "Color" menu opens a dialog that
can be used to adjust the brightness and the contrast of an image, while the "Color Balance" and
"Hue-Saturation" dialogs in the same menu can be used to adjust the color.  Remember that if
there is a selection, then the change will apply only to the pixels in the selected area.</p>

<p>As an example, I used the "Hue-Saturation" dialog to change the color of the flowers in
an image from purple to pink:</p>

<img src="gimp-color-adjust.png" width="600" height="218" tex="gimp-color-adjust.eps" texscale="0.6"/>

<np>(The original image, on the left, is from Wikimedia Commons, <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org">https://commons.wikimedia.org</a>,
which is a good source of images for experimentation.  This image is in the public domain.)  Note that
only the colors of the flowers have been modified, not the leaves or branches.  To make that possible, I had to select the
flowers before changing the color, so that the color change would be limited to the selection.
The selection was made using the "Select by Color" tool.  If you click on an image using that
tool, all pixels that have a similar color to the clicked pixel will be selected.  By holding down the
shift key as you click, you can add new pixels to the pixels that were already selected.
I found that it was easier to get the selection that I wanted when I change the "Threshold"
option for the tool from  15.0 to 30.0; this option determines how similar the colors have to be.
I had to click many times, using Undo whenever I accidently added too much to the selection.
Once the selection was ready, I selected "Hue-Saturation" from the "Color" menu, changed the
hue, and increased both the lightness and the saturation to get the color that I wanted.</np>

<p>Another way to modify an image is with a filter.  
Filters in Gimp can be very general.  They might better be called
"effects."  For example, there is a filter for blurring the
image, one for making the image look like an old photograph,
and one to make it look like it's made out of cloth. Some filters
in Gimp generate images from nothing, and some do even more
complicated things.  You will find Gimp's filters in the
"Filter" menu.  I will not discuss them further here, but
some interesting filters to try include:  Distorts/Emboss, Distorts/Mosaic,
Distorts/Ripple, Edge-Detect, Artistic/Apply-Canvas, Artistic/Cubism,
Decor/Old-Photo, and Map/Warp.</p>

</subsection>



<subsection title="Selections and Paths" id="gimp.1.2">

<p>Selections are very important in Gimp, and there is a lot more to learn about them.
One of the most important things to understand about them 
is that a pixel can be "partially selected."
That is, a selection is not necessarily just a collection of pixels; it's really an assignment
of a "degree of selectedness" to each pixel.  For example, the Cut command
(Control-X or Command-X on Mac) deletes the content of a selection.  It sets a fully selected pixel
to transparent (if the image has an <word term="alpha color component">alpha component</word>) 
or to the background color (if there is no alpha component).  However, a partially selected pixel will only
be partially cut.  If there is an alpha component, the pixel becomes translucent;
if not, the current color of the pixel is blended with the background color.
Similarly, when you fill a selection, the current color of a partially selected
pixel is blended with the fill color.  This is very much like <word>alpha blending</word>,
with the degree of selectedness playing the role of the alpha component.
(See <localref href="graphics2d.1.4"/> for a discussion of the alpha color component and
alpha blending.)</p>

<p>One way to get partially selected pixels is to "feather" a selection.  When
a selection is feathered by, say, 10 pixels, the sharp boundary around the selection
is replaced by a 10-pixel-wide border, with the degree of selectedness decreasing from one to
zero across the width of the border.  Use the "Feather" command in the "Select"
menu to feather the current selection.  Alternatively, selection tools, such as the Rectangle
Select tool, have a Tool Option that will automatically feather the border of any selection
that you create with the tool.  As an example, a feathered elliptical selection was used
to make the image on the right, starting from the image on the left:</p>

<img src="gimp-feather-selection.png" width="600" height="237" tex="gimp-feather-selection.eps" texscale="0.6"/>

<np>The original image is, again, a public-domain image from Wikimedia Commons.
I started with an elliptical selection around the flowers in the original image.
In the Tool Options for the Elliptical Selection tool, the "Feather Edges" option was
set to 40.  I then applied the "Invert" command from the "Select" menu, which inverted the
selection so that the outside of the ellipse was selected instead of the inside.  Finally, I used
"Cut" to delete the selected region, leaving just the flowers, with a 40-pixel border in which
the flowers fade into the background.  (Note: To add some visual interest to the image,
I applied the  "Artistic" / "Oilify" filter to the original before doing the selection.)</np>

<p>Gimp users often put a great deal of work into creating a selection.  One way to get more
control over selections is with the Path tool, which is discussed below.  Another is the
"Quick Mask," which gives you complete control of the degree of selectedness of individual
pixels.  Use the "Toggle Quick Mask" command in the "Select" menu to turn the Quick Mask on and off.
When the Quick Mask is on, the current selection is represented as a translucent pink overlay
on the image.  The degree of transparency of the overlay 
corresponds to the degree of selectedness of the pixel.
The overlay is completely transparent for fully selected pixels.  When the Quick Mask is on, all
painting tools affect the mask rather than the image.  For example, drawing with black will add to the
mask (and therefore subtract from the selection), and drawing with white&mdash;or erasing&mdash;will
subtract from the mask (and therefore add to the selection).  
When editing the Quick Mask, consider using the pencil tool instead of the bursh tool.
The pencil tool is the same as the brush tool, except that it does not do any
transparency or antialiasing.</p>

<break/>
<p>A "path" in Gimp is a <word>Bezier curve</word>.  (See <localref href="graphics2d.2.3"/>.)
Paths are not visible in the actual image, but you
can "stroke" a path to make it visible.  Paths are not selections, but they are closely
related.  You can convert a path into a selection, or a selection into a path.</p>

<p>Paths are created using the Paths Tool.  To create
a path, click a sequence of points with the Path Tool.  Optionally, you can make a closed
path by control-clicking back on the first point (or command-clicking on a Mac).  
This gives a polygonal path.
You can then drag on one of the sides of the polygon to change it from a straight line
into a curve.  When you do that, the usual Bezier control handles will appear at the
endpoints of the curve. You can drag the ends of the control handles for finer control
of the shape.  At a point where two segments of the curve join, there are
two control handles.  If you hold down the shift key while dragging an end of one of the two handles, 
then the two
handles are constrained to be a straight line and to have the same length, which makes
the curve smooth at that point.</p>

<p>Paths are ordinarily not visible except when they are being edited with the
Paths Tool.  However, any path that you create is saved to the Path Dialog.  The Path
Dialog is one of a group of tabbed dialogs that you will find along the right
edge of the Gimp window.  (See the
illustration of the Layers Dialog, later in this section.)  Initially,
it is hidden behind the Layers Dialog.  Click the Paths tab to see the 
Path Dialog.  The Paths Dialog contains a list of paths.
Right-click one of the paths in the list to get a popup menu.  From the popup menu, choose "Path Tool"
to make the path visible again in the image and to switch to the Path Tool so that the path
can be edited.  Choose "Path to Selection" from the popup menu to convert the
path into a selection; all of the pixels that lie inside the path will be selected.
Choose "Stroke Path" to draw a line or drag a paint tool along the path.  A dialog box will
open to let you set the properties of the stroke.  There is also a command "Selection to Path"
that will convert the current selection into a path; this command is available in the popup
menu if you click anywhere in the Path Dialog.</p>

<p>As an example of using paths, this illustration explains how I made a heart shape using the Path Tool:</p>


<img src="gimp-heart.png" width="620" height="261" bordered="true" tex="gimp-heart.eps" texscale="0.8"/>

</subsection>

<subsection title="Layers" id="gimp.1.3">

<p>In Gimp, an image can be composed
from a stack of "layers."  Each layer is itself an image.  The final image is composed by
starting with a blank canvas, then copying each layer to the canvas, one after the other.
A layer doesn't necessarily have to be
the same size as the canvas. A layer can be translucent, and can have transparent parts.
The advantage of layers is that you can edit one layer without changing the others.  You can
move a layer (with the Move Tool), and the stuff in the lower layers will be still be there.
While layers are used mostly in advanced applications, they are an important feature
and one that can lead to confusion if you don't know about them&mdash;especially since several
tools and commands add new layers to an image automatically.</p>

<p>It is important to understand that only one layer can be edited at any given time.
That layer is called the active layer.  This can be annoying if you lose track of which
layer is active.  It can be especially annoying if the active layer is hidden in the
visible image or has been made completely transparent!</p>

<p>Layers are listed in the Layer Dialog, one of the tabbed dialogs in the 
upper right or lower right corner of
the Gimp window. In the list of layers, the active layer is highlighted.  Click a different
layer in the list to make it active.  Right-click the dialog for a popup menu of commands for
working with layers.  Some of the commands are duplicated in the "Layer" menu.
If you right-click one of the layers in the list, the popup menu 
will also include commands that apply to that individual layer.  Here is an illustration of the
Layer Dialog from a project that uses four layers:</p>

<img src="gimp-layers.png" width="455" height="415" tex="gimp-layers.eps" texscale="0.8"/>

<p>A new image will only have one layer.  You can add a new layer with a command in the
"Layer" menu or in the popup menu that you get by right-clicking the Layer Dialog.  New layers
are also added automatically in some cases.  The Text Tool, in particular, always creates
a new layer.  Text layers are special.  They only contain text, and they can only be
edited with the text tool.  (More exactly, if you edit a text layer with some other tool,
it is converted into a regular layer, and you can no longer edit it as text.)</p>

<p>The Paste command will also create a new layer.  In this case, the layer is special
because it is a "floating" layer.  After pasting an image into a Gimp window, you
can use the Move Tool to drag the floating layer to the desired position.
Before you do anything else, aside from moving the layer, you need to either
"anchor" the layer (that is, make it part of the active layer), or convert it into
a new regular layer.  To anchor it, just click outside the pasted layer.  To convert it
into a regular layer, right click on its entry in the Layer Dialog, and use the "To New Layer"
command in the popup menu.  (There will also be an "Anchor" command in the menu.)  Again, this
behavior can be annoying if you don't know about it.</p>


</subsection>


</section>
