<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE source SYSTEM "../graphicstext.dtd" >

<source>

<webdiv>
<p>This page contains links to source code for the programs that are used as examples in 
<a href="../index.html">this&nbsp;book</a>.
In the web site download of the book, the source code examples can be found in the folder
named <i>source</i>.  This page also contains a list of links to all of the "live demos" that
are used in the book; they can be found in the folder named <i>demos</i>.</p>
</webdiv>
<texdiv>
<p>This appendix contains a list of the programs that are used as examples in this book.
If you have downloaded the web site version of the book, you can find the source code examples in the folder
named <i>source</i>.  This page also contain a list of the "live demos" that are used in the book.
In the web site download, they can be found in the folder named <i>demos</i>.
(The web site download is available on book's web page,
<a href="http://math.hws.edu/graphicsbook">http://math.hws.edu/graphicsbook</a>.)</p>
</texdiv>

<p>(Note: Examples and demos for <word>HTML canvas</word> graphics, <word>three.js</word>, <word>WebGL</word>, and
<word>WebGPU</word>
are html files, which can be opened in a web browser.  To see the source code, you
can open the file in a plain text editor, or you can open it in a Web browser and
use the browser's "View Source" command. Many of the html programs load graphical
models and other files.
In most browsers, the  programs that use such resources will not work when the html files
are loaded from a local hard drive.  That is, they will fail in those web browsers when run
from the <i>source</i> or <i>demo</i> folder in the web site download of this book.
The programs should work OK when loaded through a web server.  It is possible to run
a web server locally.  It might be possible to configure your web browser to use resources 
from local files, but it is generally not recommended to browse the web with that setting.)</p>

<subsection title="Java Graphics2D Examples" id="source.1">

<p>There are a few examples in <localref href="graphics2d.4"/> and 
<localref href="graphics2d.5"/> that uses the 2D graphics API that is part of Java's Swing GUI toolkit.
In the web site download, the source code for these examples can be found
in the folder named <i><sourceref href="java2d/">java2d</sourceref></i> inside the <i>source</i> folder.  Each example
is a single file that can be compiled to produce an application; no
additional Java files are needed.</p>

<ul>
<li><sourceref href="java2d/HierarchicalModeling2D.java">HierarchicalModeling2D.java</sourceref> &mdash; 
shows a simple animated scene, with a moving cart and rotating windmills, that uses <word>hierarchical modeling</word>.
In this version of the program, the hierarchy is implemented procedurally, using subroutines to
draw the objects in the scene.</li>
<li><sourceref href="java2d/SceneGraphAPI2D.java">SceneGraphAPI2D.java</sourceref> &mdash;
shows the same scene as the previous example, but this time implemented using a scene graph
data structure.  The scene graph is implemented using static nested classes in the main class.</li>
<li><sourceref href="java2d/GraphicsStarter.java">GraphicsStarter.java</sourceref> and 
<sourceref href="java2d/AnimationStarter.java">AnimationStarter.java</sourceref> draw simple
static and animated scenes, respectively, and are meant to be used as a framework for 
experimenting with Java graphics.
<sourceref href="java2d/EventsStarter.java">EventsStarter.java</sourceref> is a similar
framework for working with mouse and key events in a graphics program.</li>
<li><sourceref href="java2d/PaintDemo.java">PaintDemo.java</sourceref> draws a polygon that
can be filled with either a gradient or a texture image, and lets you adjust their
properties.  This is just a demo of Java paints.  The image files
<sourceref href="java2d/QueenOfHearts.png">QueenOfHearts.png</sourceref> and
<sourceref href="java2d/TinySmiley.png">TinySmiley.png</sourceref> are part of this
program and must be in the same location as the compiled Java class files when the program
is run.</li>
<li><sourceref href="java2d/JavaPixelManipulation.java">JavaPixelManipulation.java</sourceref>
is a demo that manipulates colors of individual pixels in a <classname>BufferedImage</classname>.
The user can draw a simple picture or load an image from a file.  A "Smudge" tool smears out pixel
colors, and filters modify the image by performing averaging operations on the pixel colors in
the image.</li>
</ul>

</subsection>

<subsection title="HTML Canvas 2D Examples" id="source.2">

<p>The 2D canvas <word>API</word> is discussed in <localref href="graphics2d.6"/>, and several
examples are mentioned in that section.  Canvas examples are written as web pages, and you can 
look at the web page in a browser to see what it does.  However, you are also meant to read
the source code.  And the first four examples are meant to be used as a basis for your own
experimentation.  (Note that all of the live demos in <localref href="graphics2d"/> use
the canvas API, but you are not necessarily meant to understand the source code of the
demos.)  In the web site download of this book, you can find these examples in the 
<i><sourceref href="canvas2d/">canvas2d</sourceref></i> 
folder inside the <i>source</i> folder.</p>

<ul>
<li><sourceref href="canvas2d/GraphicsStarter.html">GraphicsStarter.html</sourceref> is a minimal framework
for drawing on an <word>HTML canvas</word>.  It includes examples of drawing text and various shapes.</li>
<li><sourceref href="canvas2d/GraphicsPlusStarter.html">GraphicsPlusStarter.html</sourceref> adds
a few convenience functions to the previous example, including a function for setting up a
<word>coordinate system</word> on the canvas and functions to draw shapes such as lines and
ovals that are not included in the basic API.  It includes examples of using <word term="geometric transform">transforms</word></li>
<li><sourceref href="canvas2d/AnimationStarter.html">AnimationStarter.html</sourceref> adds animation to the previous
example and includes a simple example using <word>hierarchical modeling</word>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="canvas2d/EventsStarter.html">EventsStarter.html</sourceref> is a minimal framework
for using keyboard and mouse events with a canvas, with some examples of basic event handling.</li>
<li><sourceref href="canvas2d/SimplePaintProgram.html">SimplePaintProgram.html</sourceref> lets the
user draw using simple shapes.  There is also a "smudge" tool that lets the user smudge the drawing
as if it is drawn in wet paint; this is an example of pixel manipulation in the HTML canvas API.
The program shows how to use an "off-screen canvas."  The demo program <demoref href="c2/SimplePaintDemo.html"/>
is a version of this program that uses an "overlay canvas" instead of an off-screen canvas.</li>
</ul>

</subsection>



<subsection title="Scalable Vector Graphics Examples" id="source.3">

<p><localref href="graphics2d.7"/> discusses <word>SVG</word>, a <word>scene description language</word>
for 2D <word>vector graphics</word>.  Several examples were discussed in that section.  These
examples can be opened in a web browser to see the images they produce.  View the source code
for the web page to see the program that produces the image.  You can also open the files
in a text editor to read the source.  Some of the examples produce
animated images.  SVG images should work in almost all modern web browsers.
These examples can be found in the <i><sourceref href="svg/">svg</sourceref></i>
folder inside the <i>source</i> folder.</p>

<ul>
<li><sourceref href="svg/first-svg-example.svg">first-svg-example.svg</sourceref> is a very
short first example that just draws a few basic shapes.</li>
<li><sourceref href="svg/svg-starter.svg">svg-starter.svg</sourceref> shows the basic document
structure for an SVG image, includes examples of most of the basic shapes, and has a lot of
comments to explain what is going on.</li>
<li><sourceref href="svg/svg-face.svg">svg-face.svg</sourceref> is a very simple first example
of grouping.</li>
<li><sourceref href="svg/svg-hierarchy.svg">svg-hierarchy.svg</sourceref> is an example of
<word>hierarchical modeling</word> that makes a model of
a wheel and a model of a cart that uses two wheels as components.  The image shows a wheel
and four copies of the cart. The wheel and cart models are also used in the
cart-and-windmill animation at the end of this list.</li>
<li><sourceref href="svg/first-svg-animation.svg">first-svg-animation.svg</sourceref> contains
examples of simple animation, keyframe animation, and transform animation.</li>
<li><sourceref href="svg/hierarchical-animation.svg">hierarchical-animation.svg</sourceref>
shows a simple animated hierarchical model.</li>
<li><sourceref href="svg/cart-and-windmills.svg">cart-and-windmill.svg</sourceref> is a more 
complex example of hierarchical modeling in SVG. The scene is an animation that shows
a "cart" moving down a road as windmills turn in the background.  The animation is the same as
the one implemented in the Java example <sourceref href="java2d/HierarchicalModeling2D.java"/>
and in the JavaScript demo <demoref href="c2/cart-and-windmills.html"/>.</li>
</ul>

</subsection>



<subsection title="OpenGL 1.1 Examples" id="source.4">
<p><word>OpenGL</word> 1.1 is the topic of <localref href="gl1geom"/> and <localref href="gl1light"/>.
Examples in those chapters primarily use the C API for OpenGL.  However, the Java API,
<word term="JOGL">JOGL</word>, is also discussed.  Most program examples are
available in both the C and the Java APIs.  The JOGL versions can be found in the
directory named <i><sourceref href="jogl/">jogl</sourceref></i> inside the 
<i>source</i> directory.  The C versions, which
use the <word>GLUT</word> library to create and manage OpenGL windows, can be 
found in the directory named <i><sourceref href="glut/">glut</sourceref></i> 
inside <i>source</i>.  (Many of these
programs use a "<word>camera</word>" API defined in <sourceref href="jogl/Camera.java"/>
for Java and in <sourceref href="glut/camera.c"/> and <sourceref href="glut/camera.h"/> 
for&nbsp;C.)</p>
<p>The OpenGL demos in the book are written using <i>glsim.js</i>, a <word>JavaScript</word>
library that implements a small subset of the C API for OpenGL&nbsp;1.1 
on top of WebGL&nbsp;1.0.  Information about
glsim can be found in <sourceref href="glsim/glsim-doc.html"/>.  Some of 
the program examples are available in <word>HTML</word> versions that use the <i>glsim</i>
library.  They can be found in the <i><sourceref href="glsim/">glsim</sourceref></i> 
directory inside the <i>source</i> directory.</p>

<ul>
<li><sourceref href="glut/first-triangle.c"/>, <sourceref href="jogl/FirstTriangle.java"/>
and <sourceref href="glsim/first-triangle.html"/> are C, Java, and JavaScript versions of
the very first OpenGL example: a triangle whose vertices are assigned the colors red,
green, and blue.  You can use this example as a starting point for trying out some
basic 2D drawing commands.  From <localref href="gl1geom.1"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="glut/unlit-cube.c"/>, <sourceref href="jogl/UnlitCube.java"/>,
and <sourceref href="glsim/unlit-cube.html"/> are C, Java, and JavaScript versions
of a program that draws a cube using modeling transformations applied to a square.
There is no lighting in this program, and it uses a basic orthographic projection, so
the image is not realistic.  From <localref href="gl1geom.2"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="glut/opengl-cart-and-windmill-2d.c"/> (for C),
<sourceref href="jogl/CartAndWindmillJogl2D.java"/> (for Java), and <sourceref href="glsim/opengl-cart-and-windmill.html"/>
(for JavaScript) are versions of an example of hierarchical modeling and animation in two dimensions
with OpenGL 1.1.  It illustrates 2D graphics in OpenGL as well as the use of 
<i>glPushMatrix</i> and <i>glPopMatrix</i> for hierarchical modeling.  The animation is almost the same as
the one implemented in the Java Graphics2D example <sourceref href="java2d/HierarchicalModeling2D.java"/>
and in the HTML canvas graphics demo <demoref href="c2/cart-and-windmills.html"/>.  From
<localref href="gl1geom.2"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="glut/camera.c"/> and the corresponding header file 
<sourceref href="glut/camera.h"/> for C, or
<sourceref href="jogl/Camera.java"/> for JOGL, implement a "<word>camera</word>" API for use with OpenGL 1.1.  This is
a library for use in other programs, not itself a complete program.  The corresponding API for
JavaScript is part of my GLSim library, <sourceref href="glsim/glsim.js"/>.  A camera is used in most of 
the following examples. Discussed in  <localref href="gl1geom.3"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="glut/ifs-polyhedron-viewer.c"/> and <sourceref href="jogl/IFSPolyhedronViewer.java"/>
are C and Java versions of a program that lets the user view polyhedra that are defined
as <word term="indexed face set">indexed face sets</word>.  The polyhedra models are defined
in <sourceref href="jogl/Polyhedron.java"/> for Java and in 
<sourceref href="glut/polyhedron.c"/> and <sourceref href="glut/polyhedron.h"/> for&nbsp;C.
This program also requires the camera API discussed in the previous item.  From
<localref href="gl1geom.4"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="glut/cubes-with-vertex-arrays.c"/>, <sourceref href="jogl/CubesWithVertexArrays.java"/>,
and the JavaScript version <sourceref href="glsim/cubes-with-vertex-arrays.html"/>
demonstrate drawing using <i>glDrawArrays</i> and <i>glDrawElements</i>.  From
<localref href="gl1geom.4"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="glut/color-cube-of-spheres.c"/> and <sourceref href="jogl/ColorCubeOfSpheres.java"/>
draw a large number of spheres using a variety of rendering methods, and show the time that
it takes to render the image.  The point is to compare render times for different rendering methods,
including <word term="display list">display lists</word>, <i>glDrawArrays</i>, and 
<word term="VBO">vertex buffer objects</word>.  The reader is not
expected to understand all of the code in this program.  From
<localref href="gl1geom.4"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="glut/glut-starter.c"/>, <sourceref href="jogl/JoglStarter.java"/>,
and <sourceref href="glsim/glsim-starter.html"/> are "starter" files for writing OpenGL 1.1
applications using C, Java, and my JavaScript OpenGL simulator.  These programs don't
draw anything, but they have function/method stubs for drawing as well as for mouse
and keyboard interaction and animation.  Discussed in <localref href="gl1geom.6"/></li>
<li><sourceref href="glut/four-lights.c"/> and <sourceref href="jogl/FourLights.java"/>
are an example of using light sources and material properties.  The program
demonstrates multiple, moving light sources and lets the user turn the lights on and
off to see the effect.  The demo <demoref href="glsim/fout-lights-demo.html"/> is
a JavaScript version of the same program. From <localref href="gl1light.2"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="glut/texture-demo.c"/> is a C program that shows a variety of
textures on a variety of objects. It depends on the files <sourceref href="glut/textured-shapes.c"/>
and <sourceref href="glut/textured-shapes.h"/>, and on the folder <sourceref href="glut/textures"/>
that contains the texture images used by the program.  The Java version is
<sourceref href="jogl/TextureDemo.java"/>, and it requires <sourceref href="jogl/TexturedShapes.java"/>,
as well as the image folder <sourceref href="jogl/textures"/>.
From <localref href="gl1light.3"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="glut/texture-from-color-buffer.c"/> and <sourceref href="jogl/TextureFromColorBuffer.java"/>
demonstrate the technique of copying an image from the color buffer using
the function <i>glCopyTexImage2D</i>().  Draws an animated 2D scene and then uses
it as a texture on various objects.  Requires the same textured shape libraries mentioned
in the previous item.  From <localref href="gl1light.3"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="glut/texture-objects.c"/> is a small program to demonstrate the use of texture
objects to handle multiple textures.  It is available for C only.  From <localref href="gl1light.3"/>.</li>
</ul>

</subsection>

<subsection title="Three.js Examples" id="source.5">

<p><i><word term="three.js">Three.js</word></i> is a JavaScript library for 3D graphics on Web pages, 
using <word>WebGL</word> and
the <word>HTML canvas</word>.  It is discussed in <localref href="threejs"/>.  The examples
can be found in the folder named <sourceref href="threejs"/>, inside the <i>source</i> folder
of the web site download.  All of the examples use the JavaScript file
<sourceref href="threejs/script/three.module.min.js">three.module.min.js</sourceref>, 
which is a "minified" version of the library, not meant for human readers.  
A&nbsp;human-readable version, <sourceref href="threejs/script/three.module.js">three.module.js</sourceref>
is also available.  The examples also use other <i>three.js</i> scripts, which can be found in the
<sourceref href="threejs/script/">script</sourceref> folder inside the threejs folder.
The version is <i>three.js</i> Release 154.  <i>Three.js</i> is an open-source project.
It can be downloaded from <a href="http://threejs.org">threejs.org</a>.</p>

<ul>
<li><sourceref href="threejs/full-window.html"/> &mdash; <i>Three.js</i> is typically used to
write programs that fill the browser window and continually run an animation.  This example
shows how to do that, but my other examples do not follow the same pattern.  The animation
shows colored balls bouncing around inside a translucent box.  The user can rotate the
scene with the mouse.
From <localref href="threejs.1"/></li>
<li><sourceref href="threejs/modeling-starter.html"/> &mdash; A starter program for experimenting
with building and animating a scene graph model with <i>three.js</i>.  The user can rotate the
model using the keyboard.  It includes a simple example. From <localref href="threejs.1"/></li>
<li><sourceref href="threejs/diskworld-1.html"/> &mdash; Shows an animated model of a simple "car" driving around
the edge of a disk, with "trees" made from a cylinder and a cone.  Based on the previous sample program.
From <localref href="threejs.1"/></li>
<li><sourceref href="threejs/vertex-groups.html"/> &mdash; Shows how to use an
array of materials on a cube and on a pyramid whose geometry is constructed
by hand.  This uses the "vertex group" feature of <classname>THREE.BufferedGeometry</classname>.
This is also a version <sourceref href="threejs/vertex-groups-indexed.html"/> that
represents the pyramid using the <word>indexed face set</word> pattern.
From <localref href="threejs.2"/></li>
<li><sourceref href="threejs/textured-pyramid.html"/> &mdash; Shows the same pyramid as the previous
example, with a texture.  Shows how to define texture coordinates for a <i>three.js</i> geometry.
From <localref href="threejs.2"/></li>
<li><sourceref href="threejs/curves-and-surfaces.html"/> &mdash; Creates several surfaces using a parametric
surface, tube geometry, <word>lathing</word>, and <word>extrusion</word>. From <localref href="threejs.2"/></li>
<li><sourceref href="threejs/model-viewer.html"/> &mdash; Displays models that are loaded
from files various formats, using <i>three.js</i> loaders. 
Models are from the <i>three.js</i> download. (See the demo <demoref href="c5/mesh-animation.html"/>
to see animated versions of two of the models.) From <localref href="threejs.2"/></li>
<li><sourceref href="threejs/instanced-mesh.html"/> &mdash; A small example of using a
<i>THREE.InstancedMesh</i> object, which makes it possible to draw a large numbers of
instances of the same basic geometry, with different transformations and, optionally, different
colors for each copy.  From <localref href="threejs.3"/></li>
<li><sourceref href="threejs/skybox.html"/> &mdash; Demonstrates using a cubemap texture to make
a <word>skybox</word>. From <localref href="threejs.3"/></li>
<li><sourceref href="threejs/reflection.html"/> &mdash; A demonstration of using an 
<word term="environment mapping">environment map</word> to simulate the reflection by 
an object of its environment.  The environment is a skybox.  From <localref href="threejs.3"/></li>
<li><sourceref href="threejs/refraction.html"/> &mdash; A demonstration of simulated <word>refraction</word>.  
This example is almost identical to the previous example, except for using refraction rather
than reflection. From <localref href="threejs.3"/></li>
</ul>
</subsection>

<subsection title="WebGL Examples" id="source.6">

<p><word>WebGL</word> is the version of OpenGL for use on Web pages.  It 
is discussed in <localref href="webgl"/> and <localref href="webgl3d"/>.  The sample programs
can be found in a folder named <sourceref href="webgl"/>, inside the <i>source</i> folder
of the web site download.  The sample programs for WebGL
are <word>HTML</word> files.  Run the programs by opening them in a Web browser. View the
source code in a text editor or using a "View Source" command in a web browser.  Part of
a WebGL program is written in <word>JavaScript</word>.  The other part consists of a
<word>vertex shader</word> and a <word>fragment shader</word> written in <word>GLSL</word>.
Many of these examples rely on scripts that are in the same <sourceref href="webgl"/> directory.
In particular, the 3D examples use the <i><word>glMatrix</word></i> library (<localref href="webgl3d.1.1"/>).
Most of these programs work with WebGL 1.0, but a few require WebGL 2.0, as noted.</p>

<ul>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/VAO-test-webgl2.html"/> &mdash; Demonstrates the use of Vertex Array Objects.
Mentioned in <localref href="webgl.1.7"/>, but it uses many techniques that will be covered later in the
textbook.  This program requires WebGL&nbsp;2.0.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/instancing-test-webgl2.html"/> &mdash; Demonstrates the use of instanced
drawing with <i>gl.drawArraysInstanced</i>().  Mentioned in <localref href="webgl.1.8"/>, but it uses
techniques that will be covered later in the textbook.  This program requires WebGL&nbsp;2.0</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/webgl-rgb-triangle.html"/> &mdash; The standard OpenGL example rendered using WebGL:
a triangle whose vertices are red, green, and blue, where the colors of interior pixels are computed
by interpolating colors from the vertices.  Demonstrates the use of attributes and varying variables.  
From <localref href="webgl.2"/></li>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/shape-stamper.html"/> &mdash; The user "stamps" shapes onto the canvas by clicking
it with the mouse.  Properties of the shape are determined by a set of pop-up menus.  Demonstrates
the use of uniform variables, the <i>preserveDrawingBuffer</i> option on the WebGL context, and
a simple coordinate transformation in the vertex shader.  From <localref href="webgl.2"/></li>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/moving-points.html"/> &mdash; A set of circles moves around in the
canvas, bouncing off the edges.  Shows how to use the <i>POINTS</i> primitive in WebGL and
introduces the <i>discard</i> statement in the fragment shader. From <localref href="webgl.2"/></li>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/simple-texture.html"/> &mdash; A very minimal texture example.  It just
applies a texture image to a triangle.  From <localref href="webgl.4"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/texture-from-pixels.html"/> &mdash; Shows how to load a texture from
an array that contains the pixel color component values for the texture.  (Also demonstrates
the difference between a <i>gl.LINEAR</i> and a <i>gl.NEAREST</i> magnification filter.)
From <localref href="webgl.4"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/cubemap-fisheye.html"/> &mdash; Loads a <word>cubemap texture</word>,
but uses it in a 2D context to imitate a picture taken with a fisheye lens.  2D&nbsp;texture
coordinates are first mapped onto a sphere to get the direction vector that is used to
sample the cubemap. From <localref href="webgl.4"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/webgl-game-of-life.html"/> &mdash;
An implementation of John H. Conway's "Game of Live" in WebGL, as a basic example of how GPUs can be used
to perform computational tasks. From <localref href="webgl.4"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/texelFetch-MonaLisa-webgl2.html"/> &mdash; 
A rather silly demo program that uses the GLSL ES 3.00 function <i>texelFetch</i>() to
get colors from a texture image.  This program requires WebGL&nbsp;2.0.
From <localref href="webgl.4"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/simple-hierarchy2D.html"/> &mdash; Demonstrates using 2D modeling transformations 
in WebGL and GLSL, with some simple animated hierarchical objects.  Transforms are implemented in
JavaScript as objects of type <classname>AffineTransform2D</classname>, defined in the
file <sourceref href="webgl/AffineTransform2D.js"/>. From <localref href="webgl.5"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/glmatrix-cube-unlit.html"/> &mdash; A first example of doing 3D graphics
directly in WebGL, with no lighting. From <localref href="webgl3d.1"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/cube-with-simple-rotator.html"/> &mdash; Demonstrates the use
of a <classname>SimpleRotator</classname> (defined in <sourceref href="webgl/simple-rotator.js"/>)
to do mouse rotation. From <localref href="webgl3d.1"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/cube-with-trackball-rotator.html"/> &mdash; Demonstrates the use
of a <classname>TrackballRotator</classname> (defined in <sourceref href="webgl/trackball-rotator.js"/>)
to do mouse rotation.  This is almost identical to the previous example.  From <localref href="webgl3d.1"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/cube-with-basic-lighting.html"/> &mdash; A first example of implementing lighting
directly in WebGL. Adds lighting to <sourceref href="webgl/glmatrix-cube-unlit.html"/>.  The
lighting in this case uses only diffuse color and a directional light from the direction of
the viewer.  From <localref href="webgl3d.2"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/basic-specular-lighting.html"/> &mdash; A first implementation of specular reflection.
From <localref href="webgl3d.2"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/basic-specular-lighting-Phong.html"/> &mdash; A second implementation of specular reflection,
using <word>Phong shading</word> (with the lighting calculations in the fragment shader).  Aside from moving
the calculation to the fragment shader, this example is identical to the previous example.
From <localref href="webgl3d.2"/>.  There is also a version that has been ported to
WebGL&nbsp;2.0 and GLSL&nbsp;ES&nbsp;3.00:
<sourceref href="webgl/basic-specular-lighting-Phong-webgl2.html"/>.  The
required changes are minimal.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/parametric-function-grapher.html"/> &mdash;  Lets
the user graph a parametric surface, given by equations x(u,v), y(u,v), and z(u,v) entered by
the user. A relatively complex program, it illustrates GLSL data structures, two-sided lighting, 
and polygon offset. From <localref href="webgl3d.2"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/spotlights.html"/> &mdash; A demo of spotlights, with three colored spotlights.
The user can change the cutoff angle and spot exponent. From <localref href="webgl3d.2"/></li>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/diskworld-2.html"/> &mdash; A relatively complex program with hierarchical
modeling and several kinds of lighting, including moving lights, spotlights, and light attenuation.
This is the same scene as the <i>three.js</i> example <sourceref href="threejs/diskworld-1.html"/>,
with added lighting features.  From <localref href="webgl3d.2"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/texture-transform.html"/> &mdash; Animated texture images, using <i>glMatrix</i> 
to implement texture transformations.  From <localref href="webgl3d.3"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/bumpmap.html"/> &mdash; A mostly successful attempt
to implement <word>bumpmapping</word>. From <localref href="webgl3d.3"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/skybox-and-env-map.html"/> &mdash; Uses a cubemap texture to make
a skybox and as an environment map.  From <localref href="webgl3d.3"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/image-blur.html"/> &mdash; Applies a blur filter to an image.  A very simple
demo of using blending for something other than transparency.  Also a very simple example of a 
multi-pass algorithm.  From <localref href="webgl3d.4"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/render-to-texture.html"/> &mdash; Uses a WebGL <word>framebuffer</word>
to draw an image directly into a texture. From <localref href="webgl3d.4"/>.
There is also a port to WebGL&nbsp;2.0, which uses vertex array objects and <i>gl.texStorage2D</i>():
<sourceref href="webgl/render-to-texture-webgl2.html"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/cube-camera.html"/> &mdash; Shows a <word>skybox</word> and moving cubes reflected on
the surface of an object.  Uses a dynamic <word>cubemap texture</word> as an 
<word term="environment mapping">environment map</word> on the reflective object.  
The six images for the cubemap texture are redrawn for each frame of an animation. 
From <localref href="webgl3d.4"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/anisotropic-filtering.html"/> &mdash;  Demonstrates the use of the WebGL
<word>anisotropic filtering</word> extension.  Shows a large textured rectangle extending into the distance and
lets the user turn anisotropic filtering on and off.  From <localref href="webgl3d.5"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/image-evolver.html"/> &mdash; Demonstrates use of the WEBGL_color_buffer_float
<word>WebGL extension</word>.  The application is a simple genetic algorithm that tries to approximate a given
image.  The floating point color buffer is used for two computations: finding the average of the color values in
an image and computing an image that represents the difference between two images.  From <localref href="webgl3d.5"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/instancing-test-webgl1.html"/> &mdash; Demonstrates the use of an extension
to do instanced drawing in WebGL 1.0.  This is a copy of <sourceref href="webgl/instancing-test-webgl2.html"/>,
modified to work with WebGL 1.0.   From <localref href="webgl3d.5"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgl/multiple-draw-buffers-webgl2.html"/> &mdash; Demonstrates drawing to multiple
textures attached as draw buffers to the same framebuffer.  Requires WebGL&nbsp;2.0 (but something
similar could be done in WebGL 1.0 with an extension.)
From <localref href="webgl3d.5"/>.</li>
</ul>
</subsection>

<subsection title="WebGPU Examples" id="source.7">

<p><word>WebGPU</word> is a new <word>API</word> for graphics on the Web.  It has been designed from
scratch to incorporate some of the features of more modern APIs such as 
<word>Vulkan</word>, <word>Direct3D</word>, and <word>Metal</word>.  It is covered
in <localref href="webgpu"/>.  These programs require a web browser that supports WebGPU.
As of July, 2023, WebGPU is enabled by default in the Chrome and Edge browsers on Windows
and MacOS.  In some other browsers, it is an experimental feature that can be enabled by the user.
In a download of the web site, they can be found in the directory named <i><sourceref href="webgpu/">webgpu</sourceref></i> in
the <i>source</i> directory.</p>

<ul>
<li><sourceref href="webgpu/basic_webgpu_1.html"/> &mdash; A first WebGPU example, which just
draws a colored triangle.  The source code has extensive comments to explain WebGPU.
From <localref href="webgpu.1"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgpu/basic_webgpu_2.html"/> and <sourceref href="webgpu/basic_webgpu_3.html"/> &mdash;
Variations on the previous example that draw a triangle with different colored vertices.  This requires
adding a second parameter to the vertex shader program. The first program does this by using two
vertex buffers; the second, by using a single vertex buffer with interleaved values for the two
input parameters.  From <localref href="webgpu.1.6"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgpu/instanced_draw.html"/>  &mdash;  Uses <word>instanced drawing</word> to draw multiple colored 
disks using a single call to <code>draw()</code>.  Shows how to use instance attributes in 
<word term="vertex buffer">vertex buffers</word>.  From <localref href="webgpu.2.1"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgpu/indexed_draw.html"/>  &mdash;  Uses the <code>drawIndexed()</code> method to 
draw a single disk as an <word>indexed face set</word> using a triangle-list primitive.  Also
draws the disk outline using a triangle-strip primitive and shows how to use two render passes
in one command buffer.  From <localref href="webgpu.2.2"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgpu/draw_multiple.html"/>  &mdash; Draws multiple outlined disks using different rendering
passes for each disk.  Also illustrates using <code>copyBufferToBuffer()</code> to set
the value of a uniform variable between rendering passes.  Also, <sourceref href="webgpu/draw_multiple_2.html"/>
is a variation on the program that does the same thing using <code>writeBuffer()</code>,
which requires a separate command encoder for drawing each disk.  From <localref href="webgpu.2.3"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgpu/indices_in_shader.html"/> &mdash; An example of using the vertex index and the
instance index in the vertex shader function.  The application in this case is to imitate what
can be done in WebGL with a POINTS primitive by setting a point size.  WebGPU does not implement
point size, so a points-list primitive can only be rendered as individual pixels.
From <localref href="webgpu.2.4"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgpu/multisampling.html"/> &mdash; Demonstrates how to add <word>multisampling</word> to a
WebGPU program, by adding it to <sourceref href="webgpu/instanced_draw.html"/>.  Multisampling
is a kind of <word>antialiasing</word>.  From <localref href="webgpu.2.5"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgpu/depth_test.html"/> &mdash; Shows how to enable the depth test in WebGPU.
The program duplicates the functionality of <sourceref href="webgpu/draw_multiple.html"/> but does it
with instanced drawing. It also adds multisampling.  But the only comments in the code are about the
depth test.  From <localref href="webgpu.4.1"/></li>
<li><sourceref href="webgpu/Phong_lighting.html"/> &mdash; A direct port of 
<sourceref href="webgl/basic-specular-lighting-Phong.html"/> to WebGPU.  It displays one
object at a time, with some user control of material and light properties.
From <localref href="webgpu.4.2"/></li>
<li><sourceref href="webgpu/diskworld_webgpu.html"/> &mdash; A direct port of <sourceref href="webgl/diskworld-2.html"/>
to WebGPU.  It is an example of the implementation of hierarchical 3D graphics and of the OpenGL lighting model.
From <localref href="webgpu.4.5"/></li>
<li><sourceref href="webgpu/first_texture.html"/> &mdash; A first example of using textures in WebGPU.  The user
can select among three different kinds of texture, applied to a square.  From <localref href="webgpu.5"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgpu/textured_objects.html"/> &mdash; Applies texture images to 3D shapes, with
basic lighting.  From <localref href="webgpu.5"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgpu/texture_from_canvas.html"/> &mdash; Takes the image for a texture from
another canvas on the same page and applies it to 3D shapes.  The user can do some very simple drawing
on the canvas.  (Aside from grabbing the texture from a canvas, there is nothing new in this program.)
From <localref href="webgpu.5"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgpu/making_mipmaps.html"/> &mdash; Defines and tests a function that creates
an image texture with a full set of mipmaps from an ImageBitmap.  From <localref href="webgpu.5.3"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgpu/cubemap_texture.html"/> &mdash; Loads a cubemap texture and uses it for
a skybox and for reflection mapping.  It is functionally identical to the WebGL example
<sourceref href="webgl/skybox-and-env-map.html"/>.  From <localref href="webgpu.5.4"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgpu/life_1.html"/> &mdash; Conway's "Game of Life", using integer-format "r32uint"
textures and the WGSL functions <code>textureLoad()</code> and <code>textureStore()</code>.
The program <sourceref href="webgpu/life_2.html"/> performs the same task, but does it
using two "r8unorm" textures, one used for sampling in the shader and one used as a color attachment
for the render pipeline.  From <localref href="webgpu.5.5"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgpu/diffusion.html"/> &mdash; Uses compute shaders to run a simulation
of Brownian motion.  White particles move randomly.  When they hit a yellow or cyan particle,
they change color and stop moving.  Over time, an interesting dendrite-like pattern will form.
From <localref href="webgpu.6.3"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgpu/map_buffer_for_read.html"/> &mdash; Illustrates reading data from a GPU buffer
into the JavaScript side of the program.  The application (which is really not the point of the exercise)
is to use the trapezoid rule to approximate a definite integral.  From <localref href="webgpu.6.4"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgpu/viewport_and_scissor.html"/> &mdash; Another moving disk animation, showing
four copies of the scene in different viewports.  A scissor rect is also applied in two of the viewports.
From <localref href="webgpu.7.4"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgpu/alpha_blend.html"/> &mdash; Uses alpha blending to draw translucent colors.  Demonstrates
the <code>blend</code> property of the target in a render pipeline.  From <localref href="webgpu.7.5"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgpu/color_mask.html"/> &mdash; Demonstrates the <code>writeMask</code> property of the target
in a render pipeline by letting the user select which color channels to write. From <localref href="webgpu.7.5"/>.</li>
<li><sourceref href="webgpu/polyhedra.html"/> &mdash; Lets the user view several polyhedra.  Demonstrates depth bias in 
a render pipeline by drawing the faces of the polyhedra with a depth bias, to make sure that parts of the edges
are not hidden by the faces.  Also uses face culling. From <localref href="webgpu.7.5"/>.</li>
</ul>
</subsection>

<subsection title="Live Demos" id="source.8">

<p><web>This book</web><tex>The web site version of this book</tex> 
includes "live" or "interactive" demos that are embedded in the web pages.  The
demos are small programs written as web pages using JavaScript and either
<word>HTML canvas</word> graphics or <word>WebGL</word>.  Although they are designed
to be run as small applications inside other web pages, they can also be run
as independent web pages.  In the web site download of this book, you can find
the demos in the folder named <i>demos</i>, organized by chapter number.
They can be run directly from that folder.  Note that each of the demos requires 
certain other files that are contained in the <i>demos</i> folder;
if you copy a demo to a different location, be sure to also copy all the
files on which it depends.</p>

<p>The demos from <localref href="graphics2d"/> use the 2D canvas graphics API,
which will work in almost all modern web browsers, 
Demos from Chapters&nbsp;3 through&nbsp;8 use WebGL, which will also work with almost all
modern web browsers.  (However, WebGL might still have
problems in some of these browsers on some machines.)  All demo programs that use
WebGL will work with WebGL&nbsp;1.0.  The demos in Chapter&nbsp;9 require
a web browser that supports WebGPU.</p>

<p>The demos in <localref href="gl1geom"/> and <localref href="gl1light"/>
use <sourceref href="glsim/glsim.js">glsim.js</sourceref>, a JavaScript library that I wrote
to simulate a subset of OpenGL 1.1.  Information about
glsim can be found in <sourceref href="glsim/glsim-doc.html"/>.</p>

<p>For many of the demos, the reader is not expected to understand the program code for
the demo at the point where the demo occurs in the book.  Note that the JavaScipt code in the
demos has <b>not</b> been updated to use the more modern version of JavaSctipt that is covered
in <localref href="proglang.3"/>.</p>

<ul>
<li><demoref href="c2/pixel-magnifier.html"/> &mdash; from <localref href="graphics2d.1"/>.
Magnifies a small square of pixels in an image so that the user can see how text, lines and other
shapes are made from pixels, including <word>antialiasing</word>.
</li>
<li><demoref href="c2/rgb-hsv.html"/> &mdash;  from <localref href="graphics2d.1"/>.
Lets the user modify a color in the <word term="RGB color">RGB</word> and 
<word term="HSV color">HSV</word> color spaces by dragging sliders.
</li>
<li><demoref href="c2/approximating-ovals.html"/> &mdash;  from <localref href="graphics2d.2"/>.
Shows how ovals can be approximated by a polygons with different numbers of sides.
</li>
<li><demoref href="c2/cubic-bezier.html"/> &mdash;  from <localref href="graphics2d.2"/>.
Lets the user modify a cubic <word>Bezier curve</word> by dragging endpoints and control points.
</li>
<li><demoref href="c2/quadratic-bezier.html"/> &mdash;  from <localref href="graphics2d.2"/>.
Lets the user modify a quadratic Bezier curve by dragging endpoints and control points.
</li>
<li><demoref href="c2/transforms-2d.html"/> &mdash;  from <localref href="graphics2d.3"/>.
Lets the user apply a sequence of rotation, scaling, and translation transforms to a shape
and see the results.
</li>
<li><demoref href="c2/transform-equivalence-2d.html"/> &mdash;    from <localref href="graphics2d.4"/>.
attempts to demonstrate the equivalence between the modeling transform and the viewport transform in 2D.
</li>
<li><demoref href="c2/cart-and-windmills.html"/> &mdash;  from <localref href="graphics2d.4"/>.
Shows a simple, animated 2D scene constructed using <word>hierarchical modeling</word>.
</li>
<li><demoref href="c2/SimplePaintDemo.html"/> &mdash;  from <localref href="graphics2d.6"/>.
Lets the user draw on a canvas using some 
basic shapes.  A "Smudge" tool illustrates pixel manipulation.  This demo is pretty much the
same as the sample program <sourceref href="canvas2d/SimplePaintProgram.html"/>.
</li>
<li><demoref href="c2/image-filters.html"/> &mdash;  from <localref href="graphics2d.6"/>.
Lets the user apply a variety of "filters" to
several images.  A filter, as the term is used here, replaces the color of each pixel with a
weighted average of the colors of that pixel and its eight neighbors.
</li>
<li><demoref href="c3/first-triangle-demo.html"/> &mdash;   from <localref href="gl1geom.1"/>.
Shows the usual first example for
OpenGL: A triangle with differently colored vertices.  For this demo, you can change the colors
of the vertices.
</li>
<li><demoref href="c3/first-cube.html"/> &mdash;    from <localref href="gl1geom.1"/>.
Draws a cube with six different colors for the sides
(with no lighting effects, and with the default orthographic projection).  The user can turn the
depth test on and off to see the effect.  And the user can use a bigger cube, to see the effects
of "clipping" when parts of the cube extend outside the visible range of z-values.
</li>
<li><demoref href="c3/axes3D.html"/> &mdash;    from <localref href="gl1geom.2"/>.
Shows a set of coordinate axes in 3D.  The user can drag the mouse to rotate the view.
</li>
<li><demoref href="c3/rotation-axis.html"/> &mdash;    from <localref href="gl1geom.2"/>.
Illustrates rotation about an axis in 3D.  A cube spins about an axis of rotation.
The user can select the axis.
</li>
<li><demoref href="c3/transform-equivalence-3d.html"/> &mdash;    from <localref href="gl1geom.3"/>.
attempts to demonstrate the
equivalence between modeling and viewing in 3D.   The user drags sliders to modify a transform,
and sees that transform applied both to objects as a modeling transform and to the
view volume as a viewing transform.  The contents of the view volume and the image that
is produced are the same in either interpretation.
</li>
<li><demoref href="c3/ifs-polyhedron-viewer.html"/> &mdash; from <localref href="gl1geom.4"/>.
Lets the user view a variety of polyhedra that are defined in the program as
<word term="indexed face set">indexed face sets</word>.  The user can rotate the polyhedron
and control some rendering options.</li>
<li><demoref href="c4/materials-demo.html"/> &mdash; from <localref href="gl1light.1"/>.
Lets the user change the diffuse, specular and shininess properties of an object and
see the result.</li>
<li><demoref href="c4/smooth-vs-flat.html"/> &mdash; from <localref href="gl1light.1"/>.
Lets the user see the difference between using normal vectors to model a smooth surface
versus modeling a flat-sided polyhedron.</li>
<li><demoref href="c4/four-lights-demo.html"/> &mdash; from <localref href="gl1light.2"/>.
Demonstrates the effect of multiple, differently colored, moving lights.</li>
<li><demoref href="c4/two-sided-demo.html"/> &mdash;  from <localref href="gl1light.2"/>.
A little demo that illustrates two-sided lighting, with different front and back materials.</li>
<li><demoref href="c4/texture-transform.html"/> &mdash; from <localref href="gl1light.3"/>.
Shows textures on various objects, with texture transformations that the user can control
using sliders.</li>
<li><demoref href="c4/texture-from-color-buffer.html"/> &mdash; from <localref href="gl1light.3"/>.
A simple demo of the <i>copyTexImage2D</i>() function; draws an animated 2D scene and uses
it as a texture on a 3D object.</li>
<li><demoref href="c4/walkthrough.html"/> &mdash; from <localref href="gl1light.4"/>.
Lets the user move around in a 3D world by clicking buttons, demonstrating the idea of a
moving viewer or camera.</li>
<li><demoref href="c5/point-cloud.html"/> &mdash; from <localref href="threejs.1"/>.
A first example of using the <i>three.js</i> JavaScript 3D modeling API.  It uses a
<classname>PointCloud</classname> object to show an animated cloud of points.</li>
<li><demoref href="c5/mesh-objects.html"/> &mdash; from <localref href="threejs.1"/>.
Lets the user view many of the basic <i>three.js</i> geometries, with a variety of
materials.</li>
<li><demoref href="c5/vertex-and-color-animation.html"/> &mdash; from <localref href="threejs.2"/>.
Uses per-face and per-vertex coloring to create a multicolored sphere.  Both the colors and
the position of the vertices can be animated.</li>
<li><demoref href="c5/textures.html"/> &mdash; from <localref href="threejs.2"/>. Demonstrates
textures on a variety of <i>three.js</i> objects.</li>
<li><demoref href="c5/mesh-animation.html"/> &mdash; from <localref href="threejs.2"/>.  Shows
animated models of a horse and a stork, using models with "morph targets" and the class
<classname>THREE.MorphAnimation</classname>.  The models are from the <i>three.js</i> download.</li>
<li><demoref href="c5/raycaster-input.html"/>  &mdash; from <localref href="threejs.3"/>.
Lets the user edit a scene using the mouse. Uses an object of type <classname>THREE.Raycaster</classname>
to get mouse input from the user.</li>
<li><demoref href="c5/shadows.html"/> &mdash; from <localref href="threejs.3"/>.
Demonstrates support for shadows in <i>three.js</i>.</li>
<li><demoref href="c5/reflection-demo.html"/> &mdash; from <localref href="threejs.3"/>.
Demonstrates environment mapping to simulate reflection of an environment.  The environment in this case
is a skybox.  (The demo is very similar to the sample program <sourceref href="threejs/reflection.html"/>.)</li>
<li><demoref href="c6/shape-stamper-demo.html"/> &mdash; from <localref href="webgl.2"/>.
A demo version of the sample WebGL program <sourceref href="webgl/shape-stamper.html"/>.
The user clicks the canvas to stamp shapes onto the canvas, with properties determined
by a set of popup menus.  The demo has the same functionality as the sample program, but
the shapes are drawn using a different technique.</li>
<li><demoref href="c6/moving-points-demo.html"/> &mdash; from <localref href="webgl.2"/>.
A demo version of the sample WebGL program <sourceref href="webgl/moving-points.html"/>,
with identical functionality.  Uses a single <i>gl.POINTS</i> primitive to display
a set of moving, colored disks.</li>
<li><demoref href="c6/webgl-limits.html"/> &mdash; from <localref href="webgl.3"/>.
Displays a list of values for certain resource limits in WebGL, such as the number of
attributes in a shader program or the size of the viewport.  These values can be
different on different devices and in different web browsers.</li>
<li><demoref href="c6/textured-points.html"/> &mdash; from <localref href="webgl.4"/>.
shows texture images used on a primitive of type <i>gl.POINTS</i>.  It is similar
to <i>moving-points-demo.html</i>, except that the points are textured instead of colored.</li>
<li><demoref href="c6/multi-texture.html"/> &mdash; from <localref href="webgl.4"/>.
Uses two textures on the same object, with two sampler variables in the shader program
to represent the texture units that are used to apply the textures.</li>
<li><demoref href="c7/rotators.html"/> &mdash; from <localref href="webgl3d.1"/>.
Demonstrates the difference between a SimpleRotator (<sourceref href="webgl/simple-rotator.js"/>)
and a TrackballRotator (<sourceref href="webgl/trackball-rotator.js"/>) by letting the
user rotate cubes using the two rotators.</li>
<li><demoref href="c7/per-pixel-vs-per-vertex.html"/> &mdash; from <localref href="webgl3d.2"/>.
Lets the user compare <word>per-pixel lighting</word> to <word>per-vertex lighting</word>,
by applying the two techniques to identical objects with identical lighting settings.</li>
<li><demoref href="c7/spotlight-demo.html"/> &mdash; from <localref href="webgl3d.2"/>.
Three colored spotlights shine on a square, and the user controls the cutoff angle and
spot exponent.  A demo version of the sample program <sourceref href="webgl/spotlights.html"/>, with
some added animation for fun.</li>
<li><demoref href="c7/generated-texcoords.html"/> &mdash; from <localref href="webgl3d.3"/>.
Uses texture coordinates generated from object or eye coordinates, instead of providing the
texture coordinates to the shader program as an attribute.</li>
<li><demoref href="c7/procedural-textures.html"/> &mdash; from <localref href="webgl3d.3"/>.
Demonstrates several 2D and 3D procedural textures.</li>
<li><demoref href="c7/cube-camera-demo.html"/> &mdash; from <localref href="webgl3d.4"/>.
Essentially a copy of the sample WebGL program <sourceref href="webgl/cube-camera.html"/>.
Shows a skybox and moving cubes reflected on the surface of a teapot or other object.
Uses a dynamic cubemap texture that is redrawn for every frame.</li>
<li><demoref href="c9/first-webgpu-demo.html"/> &mdash; from <localref href="webgpu.1"/>.
A WebGPU demo that just draws a colored triangle.  It is also meant as a test to check
whether a browser supports WebGPU.</li>
<li><demoref href="c9/multisampling-demo.html"/> &mdash; from <localref href="webgpu.2"/>.
Shows an animation of moving randomly colored disks.  The disks are drawn using instanced
drawing.  The demo uses multisampling for antialiasing, and lets the user turn multisampling 
on and off to see the effect.</li>
<li><demoref href="c9/diskworld-webgpu-demo.html"/> &mdash; from <localref href="webgpu.4"/>.
Illustrates hierarchical 3D graphics in WebGPU.  The functionality and code are identical
to the sample program <sourceref href="webgpu/diskworld_webgpu.html"/> except for changes
made to turn it into a demo.</li>
<li><demoref href="c9/diffusion-demo.html"/> &mdash;from <localref href="webgpu.6.3"/>.
Uses WebGPU compute shaders to implement a simulation of diffusion.  White particles
move by Brownian motion.  When a white particle hits a yellow or cyan particle, it 
changes color to match and stops moving.  The result is to build up an interesting
dendrite-like pattern.  This is a demo version of the sample program
<sourceref href="webgpu/diffusion.html"/>.</li>
</ul>


</subsection>

</source>
