<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../graphicstext.dtd" >

<section title="The Java Programming Language" id="proglang.1">

<p1>Java is taught as a first programming language in many college and high school
computer science programs.  It is a large and complex language, with features that 
make it suitable for large and complex programming projects.  Those features
can make it seem a little verbose and overly strict, but they also make it possible
for programming environments to provide excellent support for writing and debugging
programs.  If you are going to write Java code, you should consider using a 
full-featured programming environment such as <newword>Eclipse</newword> 
(<a href="https://eclipse.org/">https://eclipse.org/</a>).  <localref href="gl1geom.6.2"/>
explains how to set up Eclipse for programming with <word>JOGL</word>,
the Java API for <word>OpenGL</word>.</p1>

<p>This book comes with several "starter" programs for writing graphical
Java programs, such as <sourceref href="java2d/EventsStarter.java"/> for Java Graphics2D
and <sourceref href="jogl/JoglStarter.java"/> for JOGL.  Although this section
doesn't tell you enough to let you write Java programs from scratch, it might have
enough information to let you "fill in the blanks" in the starter programs and modify other
sample programs that come with the book.  If you want to learn Java in more detail,
you can consider my free on-line Java textbook, <a href="http://math.hws.edu/javanotes">http://math.hws.edu/javanotes</a>.</p>

<p>Java has had several 2D graphics <word term="API">APIs</word>: AWT, Swing, and JavaFX.  Swing is
built on top of the AWT, while JavaFX is a completely new API.  JavaFX is not used in this
textbook, but you will see references here both to Swing and to the AWT.
</p>

<subsection title="Basic Language Structure" id="proglang.1.1">

<p>Java is object-oriented.  A Java program is made up of classes, which can contain 
variable definitions and method definitions.  ("Method" is the object-oriented term for
function or subroutine.)   A class is defined in its own file,
whose name must match the name of the class:  If the class is named "MyClass", then
the name of the file must be <i>MyClass.java</i>.  Classes can also occur as nested classes
within other classes; a nested class,
of course, doesn't get its own file.  The basic syntax for defining a class is</p>

<pre>public class MyClass {
    .
    .  // Variable, method, and nested class definitions.
    .   
}</pre>

<np>There are variations on this syntax.  For example, to define a class as a subclass
of an existing class, you need to say that the new class "extends" an the existing class:</np>

<pre>public class MyClass extends ExistingClass { ...</pre>

<np>A class in Java can only extend one class.  However, in addition to or instead of extending
a class, a new class can also implement
one or more "interfaces."  An interface in Java specifies some methods that must be
defined in every class that implements the interface.  With all of these options, a class
definition might look something like this:</np>

<pre>public class MyGUI extends JPanel implements KeyListener, MouseListener { ...</pre>

<np>In fact, a class exactly like this one might be used in a <word>GUI</word> program.</np>

<p>A class can contain a <i>main</i>() method, and one of the classes that make up a program
must contain such a method.  The <i>main</i>() method is where program execution begins.
It has one parameter, of type <classname>String</classname><code>[]</code>, representing
an array of command-line arguments. There is a confusing distinction in Java between
<i>static</i> and <i>non-static</i> variables and methods, which we can mostly
ignore here.  The <i>main</i>() method is <i>static</i>.   
Often,  in a graphical program, <i>main</i> is the <b>only</b> 
thing that is static, so the distinction will
not be very important for us.  In a GUI program, the
<i>main</i> method usually just creates a window and makes it visible on the screen;
after that, the window takes care of itself.</p>

<p>A non-static method definition in a class actually defines a method for each object
that is created from that class.  Inside the method definition, the special variable
<i>this</i> can be used to refer to the object of which the method is a part.  You might
be familiar with the same special variable in JavaScript.  However,
unlike in JavaScript, the use of <i>this</i> is optional in Java, so that a variable that is part of
the same object might be referred to either as <i>x</i> or <i>this.x</i>, and a method
could be called from within the same class as <i>doSomething</i>() or <i>this.doSomething</i>().</p>

<p>Variables, methods and nested classes can be marked as <i>private</i>, <i>public</i>,
or <i>protected</i>.  Private
things can only be used in the class where they are defined. Public things can be
accessed from anywhere.  Protected things can be accessed in the same class and in
subclasses of that class.</p>

<p>The programs in this book use a main class that defines the window where the
graphical display will be seen. That class also contains the <i>main</i>() routine.  
(This is not particularly good style, but
it works well for small programs.)  In some cases, the program depends on other classes
that I have written; the files for those classes should be in the same folder
as the file that defines the main class.  The programs can then be compiled on the
command line, working in that folder, with the command</p>

<pre>javac  *.java</pre>

<np>To run the program whose main class is <i>MyClass</i>, use</np>

<pre>java  MyClass</pre>

<np>However, programs that use JOGL require some extra options in these commands. What you need
to know is explained in <localref href="gl1geom.6.2"/>.  (The Eclipse IDE has its own simple
commands for running a program.)</np>

<p>There are many standard classes that are available for use in programs.  A few of the
standard classes, such as <classname>Math</classname> and <classname>System</classname>,
are automatically available to any program.  Others have to be "imported" into a source
code file before they can be used in that file.  A class can be part of a package, which is
a collection of classes.  For example, class <classname>Graphics2D</classname> is defined in
the package <i>java.awt</i>.  This class can be imported into a source code file by adding
the line</p>

<pre>import java.awt.Graphics2D;</pre>

<np>to the beginning of the file, before the definition of the class.  
Alternatively, all of the classes in package <i>java.awt</i>
can be imported with</np>

<pre>import java.awt.*;</pre>

<np>It is possible to put your own classes into packages, but that adds some complications when
compiling and using them.  My sample programs in this book are not defined in named packages.  Officially,
they are said to be in the "default package."  Recent versions of Java also have "modules,"
which are collections of packages.  Again, using modules complicates things, and they are not
used in this textbook.</np>

<break/>

<p>Java is a strongly typed language.  Every variable has a type, and it can only hold values
of that type.  Every variable must be declared, and the declaration specifies the type of the
variable.  The declaration can include an initial value.  For example,</p>

<pre>String name;  // Declares name as a variable whose value must be a String.
int x = 17;   // x is a variable whose value must an int, with initial value 17.
Graphics2D g; // g is a variable whose value is an object of type Graphics2D.</pre>

<p>Java has eight "primitive" types, whose values are not objects:  <ptype>int</ptype>,
<ptype>long</ptype>, <ptype>short</ptype>, <ptype>byte</ptype>, <ptype>double</ptype>,
<ptype>float</ptype>, <ptype>char</ptype>, and <ptype>boolean</ptype>.  The first four
are integer types with different numbers of bits.  The real number types are
<ptype>double</ptype> and <ptype>float</ptype>.  A constant such as 3.7 is of type
<ptype>double</ptype>.  To get a constant of type <ptype>float</ptype>, you 
need to add an 'F': 3.7F.  (This comes up when programming in JOGL, where some methods
require parameters of type <ptype>float</ptype>.)  Constant <ptype>char</ptype> values
are enclosed in single quotes; for example, 'A' and&nbsp;'%'.  Double quotes are
used for strings, which are not primitive values in Java.</p>

<p>In addition to the eight primitive types, any class defines a type.  If the type of
a variable is a class, then the possible values of the variable are objects belonging
to that class.  An interface also defines a type, whose possible values are objects that
implement the interface.  An object, unlike a primitive value, contains variables and methods.  For example,
<classname>Point</classname> is a class.  An object of type <classname>Point</classname> 
contains <ptype>int</ptype> variables <i>x</i> and <i>y</i>.  A <classname>String</classname> is an object,
and it contains several methods for working with the string, including one
named <i>length</i>() that returns its length and another named
<i>charAt</i>(<i>i</i>) that returns the <i>i</i>-th character in the string.  Variables
and methods in an object are always accessed using the "." period operator:  If
<i>pt</i> is a variable of type <classname>Point</classname>, referring to an
object of type <classname>Point</classname>, then
<i>pt.x</i> and <i>pt.y</i> are names for the instance variables in that object.
If <i>str</i> is a variable of type <i>String</i>, then 
<i>str.length</i>() and <i>str.charAt</i>(<i>i</i>) are
methods in the <classname>String</classname> object to which <i>str</i> refers.</p>

<p>A method definition specifies the type of value that is returned by the
method and a type for each of its parameters.  It is usually marked as being
<i>public</i> or <i>private</i>.  Here is an example:</p>

<pre>public int countChars( String str, char ch ) {
    int count = 0;
    for ( int i = 0; i &lt; str.length(); i++) {
        if ( str.charAt(i) == ch )
            count++;
    }
    return count;
}</pre>

<np>Here, <i>countChars</i> is the name of the method.  It takes two parameters of
type <classname>String</classname> and <ptype>char</ptype>, and it returns a value of
type <ptype>int</ptype>.  For a method that does not return a value, the return type 
(<ptype>int</ptype> in the above example) is specified as <i>void</i>.</np>

<p>A method in Java can be used throughout the class where it is defined, even if the
definition comes after the point where it is used.  (This is in contrast to C, where
functions must be declared before they are used, but similar to JavaScript.)  The same is 
true for global variables, which are declared outside any method.  All programming code, such
as assignment statements and control structures, must be inside method definitions.</p>

<break/>

<p>Java has the same set of basic control structures as C and JavaScript:
<i>if</i> statements, <i>while</i> and <i>do<code>..</code>while</i> loops, 
<i>for</i> loops, and <i>switch</i> statements all take essentially the same form in 
the three languages.  Assignment statements are also the same.</p>

<p>Similarly, the three languages have pretty much the same set of operators, including
the basic arithmetic operators (<code>+</code>, <code>&minus;</code>, <code>*</code> and&nbsp;<code>/</code>),
the increment (<code>++</code>) and decrement (<code>--</code>) operators, the
logical operators (<code>||</code>, <code>&amp;&amp;</code>, and&nbsp;<code>!</code>),
the ternary operator (<code>?:</code>), and the bitwise operators (such as <code>&amp;</code>
and&nbsp;<code>|</code>).  A peculiarity of Java arithmetic, as in C, is that the
division operator, <code>/</code>, when applied to integer operands produces an integer
result.  So, 18/5 is 3 and 1/10 is&nbsp;0.</p>

<p>The <code>+</code> operator can be used to concatenate strings, so that "Hello" + "World"
has the value "HelloWorld".  If just one of the operands of <code>+</code> is a string,
then the other operand is automatically converted into a string.</p>

<p>Java's standard functions are defined in classes.  For example, the mathematical
functions include <i>Math.sin</i>(<i>x</i>), <i>Math.cos</i>(<i>x</i>), <i>Math.sqrt</i>(<i>x</i>), 
and <i>Math.pow</i>(<i>x,y</i>) for raising <i>x</i> to the power&nbsp;<i>y</i>.  <i>Math.random</i>()
returns a random number in the range 0.0 to 1.0, including 0.0 but not including 1.0.
The method <i>System.out.println</i>(<i>str</i>) outputs a string to the command line.  In graphical programs,
<i>System.out.println</i> is useful mainly for debugging. To output more than one item, use string
concatenation:</p>

<pre>System.out.println("The values are x = " + x + " and y = " + y);</pre>

<np>There is also a formatted output method, <i>System.out.printf</i>, which is
similar to C's <i>printf</i> function.</np>


</subsection>



<subsection title="Objects and Data Structures" id="proglang.1.2">


<p>In addition to the primitive types, Java has "object types" that represent values
that are objects.  A variable of object type
doesn't hold an object; it can only hold a pointer to an object.  (Sometimes it's
said that Java doen't use pointers, but it's more correct to say that it forces you to
use them.)  The name of a class or of an interface is an object type.
Objects are created from classes using the <b>new</b> operator.  For example,</p>

<pre>Point pt;  // Declare a variable of type Point.
pt = new Point( 100, 200 );  // Create an object of type Point.</pre>

<np>Here, the class is <classname>Point</classname>, which also acts as a type that can
be used to create variables.  A variable of type <classname>Point</classname> can refer
to an object belonging to the class <classname>Point</classname> or to any subclass
of that class.  The expression <i>new&nbsp;Point</i>(100,200) in the assignment statement
calls a special kind of routine in the <classname>Point</classname> class that 
is known as a <newword>constructor</newword>.  The purpose of
a constructor is to initialize an object.  In this case, the parameters to the constructor,
100 and 200, become the values of the variables <i>pt.x</i> and <i>pt.y</i> in the new object.
The effect of the above code is that the value of <i>pt</i> is a pointer to the newly 
created object.  We say that <i>pt</i> "refers" to that object.</np>

<p>Instead of referring
to an object, <i>pt</i> could have the special value <i>null</i>. When the value of a 
variable is <i>null</i>, the variable does not refer to any object.  If the value of
<i>pt</i> is <i>null</i>, then the variables <i>pt.x</i> and <i>pt.y</i> don't exist,
and an attempt to use them is an error.  
The error is called a <classname>NullPointerException</classname>.</p>

<p><classname>Strings</classname>, by the way, are special objects.  They are not created
with the <i>new</i> operator.  Instead, a string is created as a literal value, enclosed
in double quotes. For example</p>

<pre>String greeting = "Hello World!";</pre>

<p>Arrays are also special objects.  Any type in Java defines an array type.  An array
type is an object type.  From
the type <ptype>int</ptype>, for example, we get the array type <ptype>int</ptype><code>[]</code>.
From <classname>String</classname> and <classname>Point</classname>, we get the types
<classname>String</classname><code>[]</code> and <classname>Point</classname><code>[]</code>.
The value of a variable of type <ptype>int</ptype><code>[]</code> is an array of 
<ptype>ints</ptype> (or the value can be <i>null</i>).  
The value of a variable of type <classname>Point</classname><code>[]</code>
is an array of <classname>Points</classname>.  Arrays can be created with a version of the
<i>new</i> operator:</p>

<pre>int[] intList;  // Declare a variable that can refer to any array of ints.
intList = new int[100];  // Create an array that can hold 100 ints.</pre>

<np>An array has a fixed length that is set at the time it is created and cannot
be changed.  If <i>intList</i> refers to an array, then the length of that array
is given by the read-only variable <i>intList.length</i>.  The elements of the array
are <i>intList</i>[0], <i>intList</i>[1], and so on.  An attempt to use <i>intList</i>[<i>i</i>]
where <i>i</i> is outside the range from 0 to <i>intList.length</i>&nbsp;&minus;&nbsp;1 generates
an error of type <classname>ArrayIndexOutOfBoundsException</classname>.</np>

<p>The initial value for
array elements is "binary zero"; that is, 0 for numeric values, <i>false</i> for
<ptype>boolean</ptype>, and <i>null</i> for objects.</p>

<p>An array can be created and initialized to hold arbitrary values at the time it is created
using the syntax</p>

<pre>intList = new int[] {2, 3, 5, 7, 11, 13, 15, 17, 19};</pre>

<np>This version of the <i>new</i> operator creates an array of <ptype>ints</ptype> of
length nine that initially holds the nine specified values.  If the initialization of an array is
done as part of a variable declaration, then only the list of values, enclosed between {&nbsp;and&nbsp;},
is required:</np>

<pre>String[] commands = { "New", "Open", "Close", "Save", "Save As" };</pre>

<break/>

<p>Java comes with several standard classes that define common data structures, including
linked lists, stacks, queues, trees, and hash tables, which are defined by
classes in the package <i>java.util</i>.  The classes define "generic" or "parameterized"
types that will work for a variety of element types.  For example, an object of type
<classname>LinkedList</classname>&lt;<classname>String</classname>&gt; is a list of items of
type <classname>String</classname>.  Unfortunately, it is not possible to use these classes with
the primitive types;. There is no "linked list of <ptype>int</ptype>".  (However, you can have
<classname>LinkedList</classname>&lt;<classname>Integer</classname>&gt;, where an object of type
<classname>Integer</classname> is a "wrapper" for a primitive <ptype>int</ptype> value.)</p>

<p>Perhaps the most commonly used of the generic data structures
is the <classname>ArrayList</classname>.  Like an array, an <classname>ArrayList</classname>
contains a numbered sequence of items.  However, an <classname>ArrayList</classname> can grow
and shrink.  For example, to create an <classname>ArrayList</classname> that can hold
objects of type <classname>Point</classname>:</p>

<pre>ArrayList&lt;Point&gt;  pointList;
pointList = new ArrayList&lt;Point&gt;();</pre>

<np>This creates an initially empty list.  The method <i>pointList.add</i>(<i>pt</i>) can
be used to add a <classname>Point</classname> to the end of the list, increasing its length
by one.  The value of <i>pointList.size</i>() is the number of items currently in the list.
The method <i>pointList.get</i>(<i>i</i>) returns the <i>i</i>-th element of the
list, and <i>pointList.set</i>(<i>i,pt</i>) replaces the <i>i</i>-th element with <i>pt</i>.
Similarly, <i>pointList.remove</i>(<i>i</i>)
removes the <i>i</i>-th element, decreasing the length of the list by one.
For all of these methods, an error occurs if <i>i</i> is not in the range from 0 to
<i>pointList.size</i>()&nbsp;&minus;1.</np>


<p>It is also possible to build linked data structures directly, remembering that
the value of a variable whose type is given by a class is either <i>null</i> or is
a pointer to an object.  For example, a linked list of integer values can be
created using objects defined by the simple class</p>

<pre>class ListNode {
    int item;       // One of the integers in the list
    ListNode next;  // Pointer to next node in list, or null for end-of-list.
}</pre>

<p>A more useful data structure for this course is a <word>scene graph</word>, like the 
ones discussed in <localref href="graphics2d.4.2"/> and implemented in the sample
program <sourceref href="java2d/SceneGraphAPI2D.java"/>.  In that <word>API</word>,
a node in a scene graph is represented by an object belonging to the class
<classname>SceneGraphNode</classname> or to a subclass of that class.  For example,
a <classname>CompoundObject</classname> represents a graphical object made up of
subobjects.  It needs to store pointers to all of its subobjects.  They can
conveniently be stored in an <classname>ArrayList</classname>.  Then drawing
a <classname>CompoundObject</classname> just means drawing its subobjects.
The class can be defined as follows:</p>

<pre>class CompoundObject extends SceneGraphNode {
    ArrayList&lt;SceneGraphNode&gt; subobjects = new ArrayList&lt;SceneGraphNode&gt;();
    CompoundObject add(SceneGraphNode node) {
        subobjects.add(node);
        return this;
    }
    void doDraw(Graphics2D g) {
        for (SceneGraphNode node : subobjects)
           node.draw(g);
    }
}</pre>

<np>(The <i>for</i> loop in this class is one that is specific to Java.  It iterates
automatically through all of the objects in the list.)</np>

</subsection>



<subsection title="Windows and Events" id="proglang.1.3">

<p>Java comes with a set of standard classes for working with windows
and events.  I will mention some of the most common.  I will try to tell you
enough to understand and work with the sample programs in this book.  Writing programs from
scratch will require more in-depth knowledge.  All of the classes
that I discuss are part of the Swing GUI API, and are contained
in the packages <i>java.awt</i>, <i>javax.swing</i>,
and <i>java.awt.event</i>. Many of my programs begin with the following
<i>import</i> directives to make the classes that they contain available:</p>

<pre>import java.awt.*;
import java.awt.event.*;
import javax.swing.*;</pre>

<p>A window can be represented by an object of class <classname>JFrame</classname>.
A JFrame can hold a menu bar and a large content area known as its "content pane."
The content pane often belongs to a subclass of <classname>JPanel</classname>.
A <classname>JPanel</classname> can be used in two ways:  as a drawing surface or 
as a container for other components such as buttons, text input boxes, and nested
panels.</p>

<p>When a panel is to be used as a drawing surface, it is defined by a subclass that
includes a <i>paintComponent</i>() method.  The <i>paintComponent</i> method is
called when the panel first appears on the screen and when it needs to be
redrawn.  Its task is to completely redraw the panel.
It has a parameter of type <i>Graphics</i>, which is the graphics
context that is used to do the drawing.  It takes the form</p>

<pre>public void paintComponent(Graphics g) { ...</pre>

<np>The <i>paintComponent</i> method is discussed further in <localref href="graphics2d.5"/>.
In general, <b>all</b> drawing should be done in this method, and <i>paintComponent</i>
should only be called by the system.  When redrawing is necessary,
a call to <i>paintComponent</i> can be triggered by calling the panel's <i>repaint</i>()
method.  (For OpenGL programming in <localref href="gl1geom"/> and <localref href="gl1light"/>,
I use a <classname>GLJPanel</classname>, which is a subclass of <classname>JPanel</classname>.
In that case, the drawing is done in a <i>display</i>() method, instead of 
in <i>paintComponent</i>, but you can still call
<i>repaint</i>() to trigger a redraw.  See <localref href="gl1geom.6.2"/>.)</np>

<p>When a panel is to be used as a container for other components, those components
will usually be created and added to the panel in a constructor, a special routine
that is called to initialize an object when the object is created by the <i>new</i>
operator.  A constructor routine can be recognized by the fact that it has the same 
name as the class that contains it, and it has 
no return type.</p>

<p>The sizes and positions of the components in a panel will generally be set by
a "layout manager," which is an object that implements some policy for laying out
the components in a container.  For example, a <classname>BorderLayout</classname>
is a layout manager that puts one large component in the center of the panel, with
space for up to four additional components on the north, south, east, and west
edges of the panel.  And a <i>GridLayout</i> lays out components in rows and 
columns, with all components having the same size.  In addition to nested
panels, possible component types include typical interface components such as
<classname>JButton</classname>, <classname>JCheckBox</classname>, and
<classname>JRadioButton</classname>.  You will see examples of all of these
things in the sample programs.</p>

<break/>

<p>A GUI program must be able to respond to <b>events</b>, including low-level events
such as those generated when the user manipulates a mouse or keyboard, and high level events
such as those generated when the user selects an item from a menu or clicks on a
button.  To respond to events, a program defines event-handling methods, which
will be called when the event occurs.  In Java, an object that includes event-handling
methods is said to "listen" for those events.  For example, the basic mouse-event
handlers are specified by an interface named <classname>MouseListener</classname>.
An object that implements this interface can respond to mouse events.  It
must define methods such as <i>mousePressed</i>(), which will be called when the 
user presses a button on the mouse.  <classname>MouseListener</classname> defines
five methods in all.  A class that implements the interface would take the form</p>

<pre>class MouseHandler implements MouseListerner {
    public void mousePressed(MouseEvent evt) {
        .
        .  // respond when the user presses a mouse button
        .
    }
    public void mouseClicked(MouseEvent evt) { }
    public void mouseReleased(MouseEvent evt) { }
    public void mouseEntered(MouseEvent evt) { }
    public void mouseExited(MouseEvent evt) { }
}</pre>

<np>The <classname>MouseEvent</classname> parameter in each of these methods is an object that will contain
information about the event.  For example, 
<i>evt.getX</i>() and <i>evt.getY</i>() can be called in the event-handler method
to find the <i>x</i> and <i>y</i> coordinates of the mouse.</np>

<p>An event is usually associated with some component, called the "target" of the event.  
For example, a mouse press event is associated with the component that contained the mouse
when the user pressed the mouse button.  A button click event is associated with the button
that was clicked.  To receive events from a component, a program must register an
event-listening object with that component.  For example, if you want to respond
to mouse clicks on a <classname>JPanel</classname> named <i>panel</i>, you need to
create a <classname>MouseListener</classname> object and register it with the panel:</p>

<pre>MouseHandler handler = new MouseHandler(); // create the listener
panel.addMouseListener(handler);  // register it with the panel</pre>

<np>In many cases, I create a class, often a nested class, to define an event 
listener that I need.  However, any class, can implement an interface, and sometimes
I let my main class implement the listener interface:</np>

<pre>public class MyPanel extends JPanel implements MouseListener { ...</pre>

<np>Inside such a class, the panel and the listener are the same object, and the special
variable <i>this</i> refers to that object.  So, to register the panel to listen for
mouse events on itself, I would say</np>

<pre>this.addMouseListener( this );</pre>

<np>This statement can be shortened to simply <i>addMouseListener(this)</i>.</np>

<p>Other event types work similarly to mouse event types.  You need an object that
implements a listener interface for events of that type, and you need to register
that object as a listener with the component that will be the target of the events.</p>

<p>The <classname>MouseMotionListener</classname> interface defines methods that
handle events that are generated when the user moves or drags the mouse. It is separate
from the <classname>MouseListener</classname> interface for the sake of efficiency.
Responding to a mouse-drag action usually requires an object that acts both as a mouse 
listener and a mouse motion listener.</p>

<p>The <classname>KeyListener</classname> interface is used for handling keyboard events.
An event is generated when the user presses a key and when the user releases a key on
the keyboard.  Another kind of event is generated when the user types a character.
Typing a character such as upper case 'A' would generate several key-pressed and
key-released events as well as a character-typed event.</p>

<p>The <classname>ActionListener</classname> interface is used to respond to a variety
of user actions.  An <classname>ActionEvent</classname> is generated, for example, when the user
clicks a button, selects a command from a menu, or changes the setting of a checkbox.
It is also used in one context where the event doesn't come from the user:
A <classname>Timer</classname> is an object that can generate a sequence of <classname>ActionEvents</classname>
at regularly spaced intervals.  An <classname>ActionListener</classname> can respond to those
events to implement an animation.  See the sample program
<sourceref href="java2d/AnimationStarter.java"/> to see how its done.</p>

<p>Finally, I will note that <word>JOGL</word> uses an event listener of type
<classname>GLEventListener</classname> for working with OpenGL.  Its use
is explained in <localref href="gl1geom.6.2"/>.</p>

</subsection>


</section>
