<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../graphicstext.dtd" >

<section title="The C Programming Language" id="proglang.2">

<p1>C is the oldest programming language that we will encounter in this book.
Its basic syntax has been adopted by many other languages, including Java,
JavaScript and the OpenGL <word>shader</word> language.  C&nbsp;is not object-oriented.
It was the basis for the object-oriented language C++, but C is almost as different from
C++ as it is from Java.  While a large part of C will be familiar to any reader of
this book, to really master C, you need to know something about its less familiar
parts.</p1>

<p>My own experience with C is mostly limited to using it on Linux, where I can use
the <i>gcc</i> command to compile C programs.  If you want to use <i>gcc</i> on Windows,
you might consider installing the Linux Subsystem for Windows 
(<a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/wsl/">https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/wsl/</a>)
or Cygwin (<a href="https://cygwin.com/">https://cygwin.com/</a>). 
For Mac&nbsp;OS, you can write C programs using Apple's XCode development tools.
Using Cygwin or XCode tools for OpenGL programming is briefly covered in
<localref href="gl1geom.6.1"/>. </p>


<subsection title="Language Basics" id="proglang.2.1">


<p>A C program consists of a collection of functions and global variables, which
can be spread across multiple files.  (All subroutines in C are referred to as
"functions," whether or not they return a value.)
Exactly one of those functions must be a <i>main</i>() routine, whose 
definition generally takes the form</p>

<pre>int main(int argc, char **argv) {
   // main program code
}</pre>

<np>Execution of the program begins in the <i>main</i>() function.
As in Java, the parameters to <i>main</i>() contain information about
command line arguments from the command that was used to execute the program.
(The "**" has to do with C's implementation of pointers and arrays, which I
will discuss later.) The parameters can be omitted from the definition of <i>main</i> if the
program has no need for them.  The return value of <i>main</i>() is sent to the
operating system to indicate whether or not the program succeeded; a value of 0
indicates success, and any other value indicates that an error occurred.</np>

<p>C makes a distinction between "defining" a variable or function and
"declaring" it.  A&nbsp;variable or function can have only one definition, but it
can be declared any number of times.  A variable or function should be <b>declared</b> before
it is used, but does not have to be <b>defined</b> before it is used.  Any definition is
also a declaration.  A&nbsp;C&nbsp;compiler
will not look ahead to search for a declaration.  (More precisely, if it encounters
an undeclared variable, it will assume that it is of type <ptype>int</ptype>,
and if it encounters an undeclared function, it will try to deduce a declaration.
However, this is almost never what you want.)</p>


<p>A&nbsp;function definition takes a form similar to a method definition in Java.
The return type for the function must be specified, and a return type of <i>void</i>
is used for a function that does not return a value.  The type of each parameter must
be specified.  For example,</p>

<pre>int square( int x ) {
    return x * x;
}</pre>

<np>Since a definition is also a declaration, this also declares <i>square</i>().
To declare a function without defining it, leave out the body of the function.  
This is called a "prototype" for the function:</np>

<pre>int square(int x);</pre>

<np>For variables, a typical variable declaration, such as "<i>int&nbsp;x;</i>", is also a definition of the variable.
To get a variable declaration that is not a definition, add the word "extern".  For example:
"<i>extern&nbsp;int&nbsp;x;</i>".  You probably won't need to know this.</np>

<p>One reason for the distinction between declaration and definition is that, although C programs can consist
of several files, each file is compiled independently.  That is, when C is compiling a file,
it looks only at that file.  This is true even if several files are compiled with a single
command.  If file&nbsp;A wants to use a
function or variable that is <i>defined</i> in file&nbsp;B, then file&nbsp;A must include a <i>declaration</i>
of that function or variable.  
This type of cross-file reference is usually handled using
"header files" and the <i>#include</i> directive.  An include directive 
in a file tells the compiler to include a copy of the text from the included file
in the code that it compiles.  
A header file typically has a name that ends with&nbsp;".h" and contains only declarations.
For example, a C source file that wants to use standard input/output
will use the following directive at the beginning of the file:</p>

<pre>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;</pre>

<np>The <i>stdio.h</i> header file is one of several standard header files that should
be installed with any C compiler.  Other standard headers include <i>math.h</i> for common
mathematical functions, <i>string.h</i> for string manipulation functions, and
<i>stdlib.h</i> for some miscellaneous functions including memory management functions.</np>

<p>The compiler will also look in the current directory for header files.  In an include
directive, the name of such a header file should be enclosed in quotation marks instead of
angle brackets.  For example,</p>

<pre>#include "my-header.h"</pre>

<p>If you write a .c file that contains functions meant for use in other files, 
you will usually write a matching .h file containing declarations of those functions.</p>

<p>After all the files that make up a program have been compiled, they still have to
be "linked" together into a complete program.  The <i>gcc</i> compiler does the
linking automatically by default.  Even if all of the files have compiled successfully,
there can still be link errors.  A link error occurs if no definition is found for
a variable or function that has been declared, or if two definitions for the same thing
are found in different files.
For functions defined in standard
libraries, you might need to link the program with the appropriate libraries using the
"-l" option on the <i>gcc</i> compiler.  For example, a program that uses functions
from the <i>math.h</i> header file must be linked with the library named "m", like this:</p>

<pre>gcc my-program.c my-utils.c -lm</pre>

<np>It can be difficult to know what libraries need to be linked.  Most of my sample C
programs, such as <sourceref href="glut/first-triangle.c"/>, have a comment that tells
how to compile and link the program.</np>

<p>One more note about compiling with gcc.  By default, the name of the compiled program
will be <i>a.out</i>.  The "-o" option on the <i>gcc</i> command is used to specify a
different name for the compiled program.  For example,</p>

<pre>gcc  -o my-program  my-program.c my-utils.c -lm</pre>

<np>Here, the name of the compiled program will be <i>my-program</i>.
The name of the compiled program can be used like
any other command.  In Linux or MacOS, you can run the program on the command line
using a command such as</np>

<pre>./my-program</pre>

<np>The "./" in front of the name is needed to run a command from the current
directory.  You could also use a full path name to the command.</np>


<break/>

<p>C has most of the same basic types as Java:  <ptype>char</ptype>, 
<ptype>short</ptype>, <ptype>int</ptype>, <ptype>long</ptype>, <ptype>float</ptype>, <ptype>double</ptype>.
There is no <ptype>boolean</ptype> type,
but integers can be used as booleans, with 0 representing <i>false</i> and any
non-zero value representing <i>true</i>.
There is no "byte" data type, but <ptype>char</ptype> is essentially an 8-bit integer type
that can be used in place of <ptype>byte</ptype>.  
There are no guarantees about the number of bits used for the other numerical data types,
but usually <ptype>int</ptype> means 32-bit integers and <ptype>long</ptype> means 64-bit.
The integer types, including <ptype>char</ptype>, can 
be marked "signed" or "unsigned", where the unsigned types have
only positive values.  For example, <i>signed&nbsp;char</i> has values in the range
&minus;128 to 127, while <i>unsigned&nbsp;char</i> has values in the range 0 to 255.
Except for <ptype>char</ptype> the default for the integer types is <i>signed</i>.
(For <ptype>char</ptype>, the default is not specified in the standard.)
Since C is very profligate about converting one numeric type to another, we don't
have to worry too much about this.  (I should note that to avoid the ambiguities of
C data types, <word>OpenGL</word> defines its own set of data types such as <i>GLfloat</i> and
<i>GLint</i>, and to be completely correct, you can use them in your OpenGL programs
in place of C's usual type names.)</p>

<p>Operators and expressions are similar in C, Java, and JavaScript.  As in Java, integer
division in C produces an integer result, so that 17/3 is 5.  C&nbsp;does not use
"+" as a string concatenation operator; in fact, C has no such operator for strings.
String concatenation can be done using a function, <i>strcat</i>, from the
<i>string.h</i> header file.  We will see that some operators can be also used with pointers
in&nbsp;C, in ways that have no analog in Java or JavaScript.</p>

<p>The header file <i>stdio.h</i> declares C's standard input/output functions.  I mention
it here mostly for the function <i>printf</i>(), which outputs text to the command line
and is useful for writing debugging messages.  It is essentially the same function as
<i>System.out.printf</i> in Java.  For example:</p>

<pre>printf("The square root of %d is %f\n", x, sqrt(x));</pre>

<np>The function <i>sqrt</i>(x), by the way, is defined in the header file,
<i>math.h</i>, along with other mathematical functions such as <i>sin</i>(x), <i>cos</i>(x),
and <i>abs</i>(x).  (In C, <i>abs</i>(x) is always an <ptype>int</ptype>. For a floating-point
absolute value, use <i>fabs</i>(x).)</np>

<p>Control structures in C are similar to those in Java and JavaScript,
with a few exceptions.  The <i>switch</i>
statement in C works only with integer or character values.  There is no <i>try</i><code>..</code><i>catch</i>
statement.  Depending on your C compiler, you might not be able to declare variables in
<i>for</i> loops, as in <i>for&nbsp;(int&nbsp;i&nbsp;=&dots;</i>.
The original version of C had only one type of comment, starting with <code>/*</code>
and ending with <code>*/</code>.  Modern C also allows single line comments starting
with <code>//</code>, so your compiler should accept comments of either form.</p>

</subsection>



<subsection title="Pointers and Arrays" id="proglang.2.2">

<p>For programmers who have experience with Java or JavaScript, one of the
hardest things to get used to in C is its use of explicit pointers.  
For our purposes, you mostly need to know a little about how the unary operators "*" and
"&amp;" are used with pointers.  But if you want to use dynamic data structures in C,
you need to know quite a bit more.</p>

<p>In C, there is a data type <i>int*</i> that represents "pointer to int."  A value of type
<i>int*</i> is a memory address, and the memory location at that address is
assumed to hold a value of type <i>int</i>.  If <i>ptr</i> is a variable of
type <i>int*</i>, then <i>*ptr</i> represents the integer stored at
the address to which <i>ptr</i> points.  <i>*ptr</i> works like a variable of type
<i>int</i>:  You can use it in an expression to fetch the value of the integer from
memory, and you can assign a value to it to change the value in memory (for example,
"<i>*ptr&nbsp;=&nbsp;17;</i>").</p>

<p>Conversely, if <i>num</i> is a variable of type <i>int</i>, then
&amp;<i>num</i> represents a pointer that points to <i>num</i>.  That is,
the value of &amp;<i>num</i> is the address in memory where <i>num</i> is stored.
Note that &amp;<i>num</i> is an expression of type <i>int*</i>, and <i>*</i><code>&amp;</code><i>num</i>
is another name for <i>num</i>.  The expression
&amp;<i>num</i> can be read as "pointer to num" or "address of num."</p>

<p>Of course, the operators &amp; and * work with any types, not just with <ptype>int</ptype>.
There is also a data type named <i>void*</i> that represents untyped pointers.  A value of
type <i>void*</i> is a pointer that can point anywhere in memory, regardless of what is
stored at that location.</p>

<p>Pointer types are often used for function parameters.  If a pointer
to a memory location is passed to a function as a parameter, then the
function can change the value stored in that memory location.  For
example, consider</p>

<pre>void swap ( int *a, int *b ) {
   int temp = *a;
   *a = *b;
   *b = temp;
}</pre>

<np>The parameters <i>a</i> and <i>b</i> are of type <i>int*</i>, so any actual
values passed into the function must be of type pointer-to-int.  Suppose that
<i>x</i> and <i>y</i> are variables of type <ptype>int</ptype>:</np>

<pre>int x,y;</pre>

<np>Then &amp;<i>x</i> and &amp;<i>y</i> are pointers to int, so they can be passed
as parameters to <i>swap</i>:</np>

<pre>swap( &amp;x, &amp;y );</pre>

<np>Inside the function, <i>a</i> is a pointer to <i>x</i>, which makes
<i>*a</i> another name for <i>x</i>.  Similarly, <i>*b</i> is another name for <i>y</i>.
So, for example, the statement <i>*a&nbsp;=&nbsp;*b;</i> copies the value of <i>y</i>
into <i>x</i>.  The net result is to swap, or interchange, the values stored in <i>x</i> and in <i>y</i>.
In Java or JavaScript, it is impossible to write a similar method that swaps the
values of two integer variables.</np>

<p>Note, by the way, that in the declaration <i>int&nbsp;*a</i>, the * is associated with
<i>a</i> rather than with <i>int</i>.  The intent of the declaration is to say that
<i>*a</i> represents an <ptype>int</ptype>, which makes <i>a</i> a pointer to int.  It is
legal, but misleading, to write the declaration as <i>int*&nbsp;a</i>.  It is misleading
because</p>

<pre>int* a, b;</pre>

<np>declares <i>a</i> to be a pointer to int and b to be an int.  To declare two pointers,
you have to say</np>

<pre>int *a, *b;</pre>

<break/>

<p>Arrays and pointers are very closely related in C.  However, it is possible to use arrays
without worrying about pointers.  For example, to create an array of 5 <ptype>ints</ptype>,
you can say</p>

<pre>int A[5];</pre>

<np>(Note that the "[5]" is associated with the variable name, <i>A</i>, rather than with
the type name, "int".)
With this declaration, you can use the array elements A[0] through A[4] as integer variables.  Arrays in
C are not automatically initialized.  The contents of a new array are unknown.  You can provide
initial values for an array when you declare it.  For example, the statement</np>

<pre>int B[] = { 2, 3, 5, 7, 9, 11, 13, 17, 19 };</pre>

<np>creates an array of length 9 containing the numbers listed between {&nbsp;and&nbsp;}.
If you provide initial values for the array, you do not have to specify the array size;
it is taken from the list of values.  An array does not remember its length, and there is
no protection against trying to access array elements that actually lie outside of the array.</np>

<p>The address operator, &amp;, can be applied to array elements.  For example, if <i>B</i>
is the array from the above declaration, then &amp;<i>B</i>[3] is the address of the
location in memory where <i>B</i>[3] is stored.  The values of <i>B</i>[3] and <i>B</i>[4]
could be swapped by calling</p>

<pre>swap( &amp;B[3], &amp;B[4] );</pre>

<np>An array variable is considered to be a pointer to the array.   That is, the value of
an array variable <i>B</i> is the address of the array in memory.  This means that
<i>B</i> and &amp;<i>B</i>[0] are the same.  Furthermore, a pointer variable can be used
as if it is an array.  For example, if <i>p</i> is of type <i>int*</i>, then
<i>p</i>[3] is the third integer in memory after the integer to which <i>p</i> points.
And if we define</np>

<pre>int *p = &amp;B[3];</pre>

<np>then <i>p</i>[0] is the same as <i>B</i>[3], <i>p</i>[1] is the same as <i>B</i>[4], 
and so on.</np>

<p>An expression of the form <i>p</i>+<i>n</i>, where <i>p</i> is a pointer and
<i>n</i> is an integer represents a pointer. Its value is a pointer that points to the <i>n</i>-th item
after <i>p</i> in memory.  The type of "item" that is referred to here is the type to which
<i>p</i> points. For example, if <i>p</i> is a pointer-to-int, then
<i>p</i>+3 points to the third integer after the integer to which
<i>p</i> refers.  And the value of <i>*</i>(<i>p</i>+3) is that integer.
Note that the same integer can be referred to as <i>p</i>[3].  In fact, 
<i>p</i>[<i>n</i>] can be considered to be nothing more than shorthand for
<i>*</i>(<i>p</i>+<i>n</i>). (Although it probably takes us  farther into C than you want to go, 
I'll also mention that the operators <code>++</code> and <code>--</code> can be applied to pointer variables.
The effect is to advance the pointer one item forwards or backwards in memory.)</p>

<break/>

<p>A string in C is essentially an array of <i>char</i> but is usually thought of
as being of type <i>char*</i>, that is, pointer to <ptype>char</ptype>.  
By convention, a string always ends with a null
character (ASCII code&nbsp;0) to mark the end of the string.  This is necessary because
arrays do not have a defined length.  The null character is inserted automatically for
string literals.  You can initialize a variable of type <i>char*</i> with a
string literal:</p>

<pre>char *greet = "Hello World";</pre>

<np>The characters in the string are then given by <i>greet</i>[0], <i>greet</i>[1], &dots;,
<i>greet</i>[10].  The value of <i>greet</i>[11] is zero, to mark the end of the string.</np>

<p>String manipulation is done using functions that are defined in the standard header file
<i>string.h</i>.  For example, to test whether two strings are equal, you can use
<i>strcmp</i>(<i>s1,s2</i>).  And for copying strings, there is a function
<i>strcpy</i>(<i>s1,s2</i>).  Working with strings in C can be quite tricky,
because strings are represented as pointers or arrays, and 
C does no error checking for null pointers, bad pointers, or array indices out of bounds.</p>

<p>By the way, I can now explain the parameters to the <i>main</i>() routine,
<i>int&nbsp;argc</i> and <i>char&nbsp;**argv</i>.
The parameter <i>argv</i> of type <i>char**</i> is an array of strings (one * to mean array and
one * to mean string).  This array holds the command that was used to run the program, with
<i>argv</i>[0] holding the name of the program and the rest of the array holding any command line
arguments. The value of the first parameter, <i>argc</i>, is the length of the array.</p>



</subsection>



<subsection title="Data Structures" id="proglang.2.3">

<p>C does not have classes or objects.  However, it does have a way to represent complex
data types:  a <i>struct</i>.  A struct is similar to a class that contains only variables,
with no methods.  It is a way of grouping several variables into a unit.  For example,</p>

<pre>struct color {
   float r;
   float g;
   float b;
};</pre>

<np>With this definition, <i>struct color</i> becomes a type that can be used to declare
variables, parameters, and return types of functions.  For example,</np>

<pre>struct color bg;</pre>

<np>With this declaration, <i>bg</i> is a struct made up of three <ptype>float</ptype> variables that
can be referred to as <i>bg.r</i>, <i>bg.g</i>, and <i>bg.g</i>.  To avoid having the word "struct" as
part of the type name, a struct datatype can be declared using <i>typedef</i>:</np>

<pre>typedef struct {
   float r;
   float g;
   float b;
} color;</pre>

<np>This defines <i>color</i>, rather than <i>struct color</i>, to be the name of the
type, so that a variable can be declared as</np>

<pre>color bg;</pre>

<np>It is sometimes useful to work with pointers to structs.  For example, we can make a pointer
to the struct <i>bg</i>:</np>

<pre>color *ptr = &amp;bg;</pre>

<np>When this definition, <i>*ptr</i> is another name for <i>bg</i>.  The variables
in the struct can be referred to as <i>(*ptr).r</i>, <i>(*ptr).g</i>, and <i>(*ptr).b</i>.  The
parentheses are necessary because the operator "." has a higher precedence than&nbsp;&leftquote;*".
But the variables can also be referred to as <i>ptr</i><code>-&gt;</code><i>r</i>, 
<i>ptr</i><code>-&gt;</code><i>g</i>, and <i>ptr</i><code>-&gt;</code><i>b</i>.
When a pointer-to-struct is used to access the variables in a struct,
the operator <code>-&gt;</code> is used instead of the period (.) operator.</np>

<break/>

<p>To implement dynamic data structures in C, you need to be able to allocate memory dynamically.
In Java and JavaScript, that can be done using the <i>new</i> operator, but C does not use
<i>new</i>.  Instead, it has a function, <i>malloc</i>(<i>n</i>), which is declared in the standard
header file <i>stdlib.h</i>.  The parameter to <i>malloc</i> is an integer that specifies the number
of bytes of memory to be allocated. The return value is a pointer of type <i>void*</i> that points to the
newly allocated block of memory.  (A&nbsp;<i>void*</i> pointer can be assigned to any pointer variable.)
Furthermore, since C does not have "garbage collection," you are responsible for freeing any
memory that you allocate using <i>malloc</i>.  That can be done using <i>free</i>(<i>ptr</i>),
where <i>ptr</i> is a pointer to the block of memory that is being freed.  Rather than
discuss dynamic data structures in detail, I present a short program to show how they can
be used.  The program uses a linked list to represent a stack of integers:</p>

<pre>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;   // for the printf function
#include &lt;stdlib.h&gt;  // for the malloc and free functions

typedef struct node listnode; // Predeclare the listnode type, so it
                              // can be used for the type of next.
struct node {
   int item;       // An item in the list.
   listnode *next; // Pointer to next item in list.
};

listnode *list = 0;  // Pointer to head of list, initially null.

void push( int item ) {  // Add item to head of list
   listnode *newnode;  // Pointer to a new node to hold the item.
   newnode = malloc( sizeof(listnode) ); // Allocate memory for the node.
     // (sizeof(listnode) is the number of bytes for a value of type listnode)
   newnode-&gt;item = item;
   newnode-&gt;next = list;  
   list = newnode;  // Makes list point to the new node.
}

int pop() {  // Remove and return first item from list
   int item = list-&gt;item; // The item to be returned.
   listnode *oldnode = list;  // Save pointer to node that will be deleted.
   list = list-&gt;next;  // Advance list pointer to next item.
   free(oldnode); // Free the memory used by deleted node.
   return item;
}

int main() {
    int i;
    for (i = 1; i &lt; 1000000; i *= 2) {
           // Push powers of two onto the list.
        push(i);
    }
    while (list) {
          // Pop and print list items (in reverse order).
       printf("%d\n", pop());
    }
}</pre>

<p>A more complex data structure, such as a <word>scene graph</word> can contain several
different kinds of nodes.  For such structures, you need even more advanced techniques.
One approach is to design a struct that includes the following: data common to all nodes in the data
structure; an integer code number to say which of the several possible kinds of node it is; and
a <i>void*</i> pointer to link to the extra data needed by nodes of that type.  Using a <i>void*</i>
pointer means it can point to any kind of data structure, and the code number will tell
how to interpret the data that it points to.  A better alternative to using a <i>void*</i>
pointer is to learn about "union", something similar to a struct but more useful for
representing multiple data types.
But perhaps the real solution, if you want to work with complex data structures, is to
use C++ instead of&nbsp;C.</p>

</subsection>


</section>
