<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../graphicstext.dtd" >

<section title="Three.js Basics" id="threejs.1">

<p1><i>Three.js</i> is an object-oriented JavaScript library for 3D graphics.  It is an
open-source project originally created by Ricardo Cabello (who goes by the handle "mr.doob", 
<a href="https://mrdoob.com/">https://mrdoob.com/</a>), with contributions from other programmers.
It seems to be the most popular open-source JavaScript library for 3D web applications.
(Another popular option is <a href="https://www.babylonjs.com/">Babylon.js</a>.)
<i>Three.js</i> uses concepts
that you are already familiar with, such as geometric objects, transformations, lights,
materials, textures, and cameras.  But it also has additional features that build on 
the power and flexibility of WegGL.</p1>

<p>You can download <i>three.js</i> and read the documentation at its main web site,
<a href="https://threejs.org">https://threejs.org</a>.  The download is quite large,
since it includes many examples and support files.  This book uses Release 154 of the
software, from July, 2023. You should be aware that
some of the material about <i>three.js</i> that you might find on the Internet does not
apply to the most recent release.</p>

<p>The current release of <i>three.js</i> is a "modular" JavaScript library.  The older,
non-modular form is still available, but it is deprecated and is scheduled to be removed
in Release 160.  Previous versions of this textbook used the non-modular version.  Version 1.4
of the textbook has been updated to use <i>three.js</i> modules; aside from that, the <i>three.js</i>
material has been changed only to account for some minor differences between <i>three.js</i>
releases. (Notably, I found that I had to significantly increase the specular component of
material colors.)</p>

<p>Copies of all <i>three.js</i> scripts that are used in this textbook can be found in
the <sourceref href="threejs/script"/> folder in the <i>source</i> folder 
of this textbook's web site. The <i>three.js</i> license allows these files to be freely
redistributed.  But if you plan to do any serious work with <i>three.js</i>, you should read
the documentation on its web site about how to use it and how to deploy it.</p>

<p>The core features of <i>three.js</i> are defined in a single large JavaScript file named
"three.module.js", which can be found in a <i>build</i> directory in the three.js download.
There is also a smaller "minified" version, <i>three.module.min.js</i>, that contains the same definitions
in a format that is not meant to be human-readable.  It is the minified version that is usually
used on web pages.  In addition to this core, the <i>three.js</i> download has a directory containing many
examples and a variety of support files that are used in the examples.  The examples
use many features that are not part of the <i>three.js</i> core.  These add-ons can be
found in a folder named <i>jsm</i> inside the folder named <i>examples</i> in the <i>three.js</i>
download.  Several of the add-ons are used in this textbook and are included in the
<sourceref href="threejs/script"/> folder.</p>


<subsection title="About JavaScript Modules" id="threejs.1.0">

<p>The term "module" refers in general to a relatively independent component of a system.
Modules interact in limited, well-defined ways.  They are an important tool for building
complex systems.  In JavaScript, a module is a script that is isolated from other scripts,
except that a module can "export" identifiers that it defines.  Identifiers that are 
exported by one script can then be "imported" by another script. A module only has access
to an identifier from another module if the identifier is explicitly exported by one module
and imported by the other.  Modules can also access identifiers from non-modular
scripts, without having to import them.</p>

<p>A JavaScript module can export an identifier by adding the <code>export</code>
modifier to its declaration.  For example,</p>

<pre>export const RED="0xFF0000";
export function setColor(c) { . . .
export class FancyDraw { . . .</pre>

<np>Alternatively, it can list the identifiers that it wants to export in an
<code>export</code> statement.  For example,</np>

<pre>export { RED, setColor, FancyDraw };</pre>

<np>The <code>export</code> statement has many other options.  However, here we
are mostly interested in importing from <i>three.js</i> modules.</np>

<p>To use modular <i>three.js</i>, you will need to write a modular script.
You can do that on a web page by adding the attribute <code>type="module"</code>
to the <code>&lt;script&gt;</code> element:</p>

<pre>&lt;script type="module">
     .
     . 
     .
&lt;/script></pre>

<np>The script can then use <code>import</code> statements to access identifiers
from other modules.  For example,</np>

<pre>&lt;script type="module">
import { FancyDraw, setColor } from "./drawutil.js";
   .
   . // Use FancyDraw and setColor as usual!
   .
</pre>

<np>This assumes that the module that exports the identifiers is defined
in a script named <code>drawutil.js</code> in the same directory as the
web page.  Note that if the path to the script starts in the current
directory, then the script name must start with "<code>./</code>".</np>

<p>My <i>three.js</i> examples use the file <code>three.module.min.js</code>
from a directory named <code>script</code> in the same directory as the
web page.  They can import everything from that file using:</p>

<pre>import * as THREE from "./script/three.module.min.js";</pre>

<np>This form of the <code>import</code> statement gets all the 
exports from <code>three.module.min.js</code> and makes them properties
of a new object named <code>THREE</code>.  For example, the
exported identifier <code>Mesh</code> is imported as <code>THREE.Mesh</code>.
Again, the <code>import</code> statement has other forms, which are not
covered here.</np>

<break/>

<p>Many of my examples use add-ons that are not part of the main
<i>three.js</i> script.  I have placed the files that use them
in subdirectories of my <sourceref href="threejs/script">script&nbsp;directory</sourceref>.
All of the files come from the <code>examples/jsm</code> folder in the
<i>three.js</i> download.  I have used the same subdirectory structure as
that folder, because some of the files refer to files in other subdirectories
by name. One of the add-on scripts is "OrbitControls.js" in the "controls"
subdirectory.  It exports a class named <code>OrbitControls</code>, which 
can be imported using</p>

<pre>import { Orbitcontrols } from "./script/controls/OrbitControls.js";</pre>

<p>The add-on modules import many resources from the main <i>three.js</i>
module.  Unfortunately, they don't know where to find that file.  They
rely on something called an "import map" to specify its location.
An import map can be defined by another kind of script, with
<code>type="importmap"</code>.  So, you will see that the
scripts in many of my examples start something like this:</p>

<pre>&lt;script type="importmap">
  {
     "imports": {
        "three": "./script/three.module.min.js",
        "addons/": "./script/"
     }
  }
&lt;/script>
&lt;script type="module">
import * as THREE from "three";
import { OrbitControls } from "addons/controls/OrbitControls.js";
import { GLTFLoader } from "addons/loaders/GLTFLoader.js";</pre>

<np>The content of an "importmap" script is a <word>JSON</word> object.
The import map here defines "three" to refer to the main
<i>three.js</i> file, and it defines "addons/" to refer to the
script directory.  The add-on files refer to the main <i>three.js</i>
module as "three", so that mapping is necessary.  The
"addons/" mapping is actually not needed for my examples.</np>

<break/>

<p>I have given you only a very brief overview of JavaScript modules&mdash;enough, I hope
to let you understand my sample programs and write some similar programs of your own. For
more complex projects, you should look at what the <i>three.js</i> developers have to
say about setting up a development environment.
See the "Installation" section of the Manual at <a href="https://threejs.org/docs/">https://threejs.org/docs/</a>.</p>

</subsection>

<subsection title="Scene, Renderer, Camera" id="threejs.1.1">

<p><i>Three.js</i> works with the <word term="HTML canvas">HTML &lt;canvas&gt;</word> 
element, the same thing that we
used for 2D graphics in <localref href="graphics2d.6"/>.  In almost all web browsers, in
addition to its 2D Graphics API, a canvas also supports drawing in 3D
using WebGL, which is used by <i>three.js</i> and which is about as different 
as it can be from the 2D API.</p>

<p><i>Three.js</i> is an object-oriented <word>scene graph</word> API.
(See <localref href="graphics2d.4.2"/>.) The basic procedure is to build a scene graph
out of <i>three.js</i> objects, and then to <word term="rendering">render</word> an image
of the scene it represents.  Animation can be implemented by modifying 
properties of the scene graph between frames.</p>

<p>The <i>three.js</i> library is made up of a large number of classes.
Three of the most basic are
<classname>THREE.Scene</classname>, <classname>THREE.Camera</classname>,
and <classname>THREE.WebGLRenderer</classname>.  (There are actually several renderer
classes available.  <classname>THREE.WebGLRenderer</classname> is by far the most common.)
A&nbsp;<i>three.js</i> program
will need at least one object of each type.  Those objects are often stored in global variables</p>

<pre>let scene, renderer, camera;</pre>

<p>Note that almost all of the <i>three.js</i> classes and constants that we will use 
are properties  of an object named <i>THREE</i>,
and their names begin with "<classname>THREE.</classname>".  (The name "THREE" is defined in
the <code>import</code> statement that imports the <i>three.js</i> features; you can use a
different name.)  I will sometimes
refer to classes without using this prefix, and it is not usually used in the
<i>three.js</i> documentation, but the prefix must always be included in actual 
program code.</p>

<p>A <classname>Scene</classname> object is a holder for all the objects that make up a 3D world, including
lights, graphical objects, and possibly cameras.  It acts as a root node for the scene
graph.  A <classname>Camera</classname> is a special kind of object that represents a viewpoint from
which an image of a 3D world can be made.   It represents a combination of a
<word>viewing transformation</word> and a <word>projection</word>.   
A <classname>WebGLRenderer</classname> is an object that can create an image from a scene graph.</p>

<p>The scene is the simplest of the three objects.  A scene can be created as an object
of type <classname>THREE.Scene</classname> using a constructor with no parameters:</p>

<pre>scene = new THREE.Scene();</pre>

<np>The function <i>scene.add</i>(<i>item</i>) can be used to add cameras, lights,
and graphical objects to the scene. It is probably the only <i>scene</i> function that you
will need to call.  The function <i>scene.remove</i>(<i>item</i>), which removes an item
from the scene, is also occasionally useful.</np>

<break/>

<p>There are two kinds of camera, one using <word>orthographic projection</word> and one using
<word>perspective projection</word>.  They are represented by classes
<classname>THREE.OrthographicCamera</classname> and
<classname>THREE.PerspectiveCamera</classname>, which are subclasses
of <classname>THREE.Camera</classname>.  The constructors specify
the projection, using parameters that are familiar from OpenGL (see <localref href="gl1geom.3.3"/>):</p>

<pre>camera = new THREE.OrthographicCamera( left, right, top, bottom, near, far );</pre>

<np>or</np>

<pre>camera = new THREE.PerspectiveCamera( fieldOfViewAngle, aspect, near, far );</pre>

<np>The parameters for the orthographic camera specify the x, y, and z limits
of the view volume, in <word>eye coordinates</word>&mdash;that is, in a coordinate system in which the
camera is at (0,0,0) looking in the direction of the negative <i>z</i>-axis, with the <i>y</i>-axis
pointing up in the view.  The  <i>near</i> and <i>far</i> parameters give the z-limits in terms
of distance from the camera.  For an orthographic projection, <i>near</i> can be negative,
putting the "near" clipping plane in back of the camera.
The parameters are the same as for the OpenGL function <i>glOrtho</i>(), except for reversing
the order of the two parameters that specify the top and bottom clipping planes.</np>

<p>Perspective cameras are more common.  The parameters for the 
perspective camera come from the function <i>gluPerspective</i>()
in OpenGL's <word>GLU</word> library.  The first parameter determines the vertical extent of the
view volume, given as an angle measured in degrees.  The <i>aspect</i> is the ratio
between the horizontal and vertical extents; it should usually be set to the width of the
canvas divided by its height.  And <i>near</i> and <i>far</i> give the z-limits on the view
volume as distances from the camera.  For a perspective projection, 
both must be positive, with <i>near</i> less
than <i>far</i>.  Typical code for creating a perspective camera would be:</p>

<pre>camera = new THREE.PerspectiveCamera( 45, canvas.width/canvas.height, 1, 100 );</pre>

<np>where <i>canvas</i> holds a reference to the &lt;canvas&gt; element
where the image will be rendered.
The near and far values mean that only things between 1 and 100 units in front of the
camera are included in the image.  Remember that using an unnecessarily large value for
<i>far</i> or an unnecessarily small value for <i>near</i> can interfere 
with the accuracy of the <word>depth test</word>.</np>

<p>A camera, like other objects, can be added to a scene, but it does not have
to be part of the scene graph to be used.  You might add it to the scene graph if
you want it to be a parent or child of another object in the graph.
In any case, you will generally want to apply a <word>modeling transformation</word>
to the camera to set its position and orientation in 3D space.
I will cover that later when I talk about transformations more generally.</p>

<break/>


<p>A renderer is an instance of the class <classname>THREE.WebGLRenderer</classname>.
Its constructor has
one parameter, which is a JavaScript object containing settings that
affect the renderer.  The settings you are most likely to specify are
<i>canvas</i>, which tells the renderer where to draw, and
<i>antialias</i>, which asks the renderer to use <word>antialiasing</word> if possible:</p>

<pre>renderer = new THREE.WebGLRenderer( {
                         canvas: theCanvas,
                         antialias: true
                     } );</pre>

<np>Here, <i>theCanvas</i> would be a reference to the &lt;canvas&gt;
element where the renderer will display the images that it produces.
(Note that the technique of having a JavaScript object as a parameter
is used in many <i>three.js</i> functions.  It makes it possible to
support a large number of options without requiring a long list of parameters that
must all be specified in some particular order.  Instead, you only need to
specify the options for which you want to provide non-default values,
and you can specify those options by name, in any order.)</np>

<p>The main thing that you want to do with a renderer is render an image.
For that, you also need a scene and a camera.
To render an image of a given <i>scene</i> from the point of view of a given <i>camera</i>,
call</p>

<pre>renderer.render( scene, camera );</pre>

<np>This is really the central command in any <i>three.js</i> application.</np>

<p>(I should note that most of the examples that I have seen do not provide
a canvas to the renderer; instead, they allow the renderer to create it.
The canvas can then be obtained from the renderer and added to
the page.  Furthermore, the canvas typically fills the entire browser window.
The sample program <sourceref href="threejs/full-window.html"/> shows how to do that.
However, all of my other examples use an existing canvas, with the renderer constructor shown above.)</p>

</subsection>


<subsection title="THREE.Object3D" id="threejs.1.2">

<p>A <i>three.js</i> scene graph is made up of objects of type
<classname>THREE.Object3D</classname> (including objects that belong to
subclasses of that class).  Cameras, lights, and visible objects are all
represented by subclasses of <classname>Object3D</classname>.
In fact, <classname>THREE.Scene</classname> itself is also a subclass of <classname>Object3D</classname>.</p>

<p>Any <classname>Object3D</classname> contains
a list of child objects, which are also of type <classname>Object3D</classname>.
The child lists define the structure of the scene graph.  If <i>node</i> and <i>object</i> are of type
<classname>Object3D</classname>, then the method <i>node.add</i>(<i>object</i>) adds
<i>object</i> to the list of children of <i>node</i>.  The method <i>node.remove</i>(<i>object</i>)
can be used to remove an object from the list.</p>

<p>A <i>three.js</i> scene graph must, in fact, be a tree.  That is, every node
in the graph has a unique parent node, except for the root node, which has no
parent.  An <classname>Object3D</classname>, <i>obj</i>, has a property
<i>obj.parent</i> that points to the parent of <i>obj</i> in the scene graph, 
if any.  You should never set this property directly.  It is set automatically when the node
is added to the child list of another node.  If <i>obj</i> already has a parent when it
is added as a child of <i>node</i>, then <i>obj</i> is first removed from the child list of
its current parent before it is added to the child list of <i>node</i>.</p>

<p>The children of an <classname>Object3D</classname>, <i>obj</i>, are stored in a 
property named <i>obj.children</i>, which is an ordinary JavaScript array.  However, you
should always add and remove children of <i>obj</i> using the methods <i>obj.add</i>()
and <i>obj.remove</i>().</p>

<p>To make it easy to duplicate parts of the structure of a scene graph,
<classname>Object3D</classname> defines a <i>clone</i>() method.  This method
copies the node, including the recursive copying of the children of that node.
This makes it easy to include multiple copies of the same structure in a scene
graph:</p>

<pre>let node = THREE.Object3D();
      .
      .  // Add children to node.
      .
scene.add(node);
let nodeCopy1 = node.clone();
      .
      .  // Modify nodeCopy1, maybe apply a transformation.
      .
scene.add(nodeCopy1)
let nodeCopy2 = node.clone();
      .
      .  // Modify nodeCopy2, maybe apply a transformation.
      .
scene.add(nodeCopy2);</pre>

<p>An <classname>Object3D</classname>, <i>obj</i>, has an associated transformation,
which is given by properties <i>obj.scale</i>, <i>obj.rotation</i>, and <i>obj.position</i>.
These properties represent a modeling transformation to be applied to the object and its
children when the object is rendered.  The object is first scaled, then rotated, then
translated according to the values of these properties.  (Transformations are actually 
more complicated than this, but we will keep things simple for now and will return
to the topic later.)</p>

<p>The values of <i>obj.scale</i> and <i>obj.position</i> are objects of type
<classname>THREE.Vector3</classname>.  A&nbsp;<classname>Vector3</classname> represents a <word>vector</word> or point in 
three dimensions.  (There are similar classes <classname>THREE.Vector2</classname>
and <classname>THREE.Vector4</classname> for vectors in 2 and 4 dimensions.)
A <classname>Vector3</classname> object can be constructed from three numbers
that give the coordinates of the vector:</p>

<pre>let v = new THREE.Vector3( 17, -3.14159, 42 );</pre>

<np>This object has properties <i>v.x</i>, <i>v.y</i>, and <i>v.z</i> representing
the coordinates.  The properties can be set individually; for example: <i>v.x&nbsp;=&nbsp;10</i>.
They can also be set all at once, using the method <i>v.set</i>(<i>x,y,z</i>).
The <classname>Vector3</classname> class also has many methods implementing vector operations such as
addition, dot product, and cross product.</np>

<p>For an <classname>Object3D</classname>, the properties <i>obj.scale.x</i>, 
<i>obj.scale.y</i>, and <i>obj.scale.z</i> give the amount of scaling of the object in
the x, y, and z directions.  The default values, of course, are&nbsp;1.  Calling</p>

<pre>obj.scale.set(2,2,2);</pre>

<np>means that the object will be subjected to a uniform scaling factor of 2 
when it is rendered.  Setting</np>

<pre>obj.scale.y = 0.5;</pre>

<np>will shrink it to half-size in the y-direction only (assuming that
<i>obj.scale.x</i> and <i>obj.scale.z</i> still have their default values).</np>

<p>Similarly, the properties <i>obj.position.x</i>, <i>obj.position.y</i>, and
<i>obj.position.z</i> give the translation amounts that will be applied to the object
in the x, y, and z directions when it is rendered.  For example, since a camera is 
an <classname>Object3D</classname>, setting</p>

<pre>camera.position.z = 20;</pre>

<np>means that the camera will be moved from its default position at the origin to the
point (0,0,20) on the positive <i>z</i>-axis.  This modeling transformation on the camera
becomes a viewing transformation when the camera is used to render a scene.</np>

<p>The object <i>obj.rotation</i> has properties <i>obj.rotation.x</i>, 
<i>obj.rotation.y</i>, and <i>obj.rotation.z</i> that represent rotations about
the x-, y-, and z-axes.   The angles are measured in radians.
The object is rotated first about the x-axis, then  about the y-axis, then about the z-axis. 
(It is possible to change this order.)  The value of <i>obj.rotation</i> is not
a vector.  Instead, it belongs to a similar type, <classname>THREE.Euler</classname>,
and the angles of rotation are called <newword>Euler angles</newword>.</p>

</subsection>


<subsection title="Object, Geometry, Material" id="threejs.1.3">

<p>A visible object in <i>three.js</i> is made up of either
points, lines, or triangles.  An individual object corresponds to
an OpenGL <word term="geometric primitive">primitive</word> such as
<i>GL_POINTS</i>, <i>GL_LINES</i>, or <i>GL_TRIANGLES</i>
(see <localref href="gl1geom.1.1"/>).  There are five classes to
represent these possibilities:  <classname>THREE.Points</classname> for points,
<classname>THREE.Mesh</classname> for triangles, and three classes for
lines: <classname>THREE.Line</classname>, which uses the <i>GL_LINE_STRIP</i>
primitive; <classname>THREE.LineSegments</classname>, which uses the <i>GL_LINES</i>
primitive; and <classname>THREE.LineLoop</classname>, which uses the <i>GL_LINE_LOOP</i>
primitive.</p>

<p>A visible object is made up of some geometry plus a <word>material</word> that
determines the appearance of that geometry.  In <i>three.js</i>, the
geometry and material of a visible object are themselves represented by
JavaScript classes <classname>THREE.BufferGeometry</classname> and
<classname>THREE.Material</classname>.</p>

<p>An object of type <classname>THREE.BufferGeometry</classname> 
can store <word>vertex</word> coordinates and their <word term="attribute">attributes</word>.
(In fact, the vertex coordinates are also considered to be an "attribute" of the geometry.)
These values must be stored in a form suitable for use with the OpenGL functions 
<i>glDrawArrays</i> and <i>glDrawElements</i>
(see <localref href="gl1geom.4.2"/>).  For JavaScript,
this means that they must be stored in <word term="typed array">typed arrays</word>.
A typed array is similar to a normal JavaScript array, except that its length
is fixed and it can only hold numerical values of a certain type.
For example, a <classname>Float32Array</classname> holds 32-bit floating point
numbers, and a <classname>UInt16Array</classname> holds unsigned 16-bit integers.  A
typed array can be created with a constructor that specifies the length of
the array.  For example,</p>

<pre>vertexCoords = new Float32Array(300);  // Space for 300 numbers.</pre>

<np>Alternatively, the constructor can take an ordinary JavaScript array of numbers as its
parameter.  This creates a typed array that holds the same numbers.  For example,</np>

<pre>data = new Float32Array( [ 1.3, 7, -2.89, 0, 3, 5.5 ] );</pre>

<np>In this case, the length of <i>data</i> is six, and it contains copies of the
numbers from the JavaScript array.</np>

<p>Specifying the vertices for a <classname>BufferGeometry</classname> is a multistep
process.  You need to create a typed array containing the coordinates of the vertices.
Then you need to wrap that array inside an object of type
<classname>THREE.BufferAttribute</classname>.  Finally, you can add the attribute
to the geometry.  Here is an example:</p>

<pre>let vertexCoords = new Float32Array([ 0,0,0, 1,0,0, 0,1,0 ]);
let vertexAttrib = new THREE.BufferAttribute(vertexCoords, 3);
let geometry = new THREE.BufferGeometry();
geometry.setAttribute( "position", vertexAttrib );</pre>

<np>The second parameter to the <classname>BufferGeometry</classname> constructor
is an integer that tells <i>three.js</i> the number of coordinates of each 
vertex.  Recall that a vertex can be specified by 2, 3, or 4 coordinates,
and you need to specify how many numbers are provided in the array for
each vertex.  Turning to the <i>setAttribute</i>() function, a <classname>BufferGeometry</classname>
can have attributes specifying color, <word term="normal vector">normal vectors</word>,
and <word>texture coordinates</word>, as well as other custom attributes.  The first
parameter to <i>setAttribute</i>() is the name of the attribute.  Here, "position"
is the name of the attribute that specifies the coordinates, or position, of the 
vertices.</np>

<p>Similarly, to specify a color for each vertex, you can put the <word term="RGB color">RGB</word>
components of the colors into a <classname>Float32Array</classname>, and use that to specify
a value for the <classname>BufferGeometry</classname> attribute named "color".</p>

<p>For a specific example, suppose that we want to represent a primitive of type
<i>GL_POINTS</i>, using a <i>three.js</i> object of type <classname>THREE.Points</classname>.
Let's say we want 10000 points placed at random inside the unit sphere, where 
each point can have its own random color.  Here is some code that creates the necessary
<classname>BufferGeometry</classname>:</p>

<pre>
let pointsBuffer = new Float32Array( 30000 );  // 3 numbers per vertex!
let colorBuffer = new Float32Array( 30000 );
let i = 0;
while ( i &lt; 10000 ) {
    let x = 2*Math.random() - 1;
    let y = 2*Math.random() - 1;
    let z = 2*Math.random() - 1;
    if ( x*x + y*y + z*z &lt; 1 ) {  
            // only use points inside the unit sphere
        pointsBuffer[3*i] = x;
        pointsBuffer[3*i+1] = y;
        pointsBuffer[3*i+2] = z;
        colorBuffer[3*i] = 0.25 + 0.75*Math.random();
        colorBuffer[3*i+1] = 0.25 + 0.75*Math.random();
        colorBuffer[3*i+2] = 0.25 + 0.75*Math.random();
        i++;
    }
}
let pointsGeom = new THREE.BufferGeometry();
pointsGeom.setAttribute("position", 
                        new THREE.BufferAttribute(pointsBuffer,3));
pointsGeom.setAttribute("color", 
                        new THREE.BufferAttribute(colorBuffer,3));</pre>
                      
<break/>

<p>In <i>three.js</i>, to make some geometry into a visible object, we also need an
appropriate material.
For example, for an object of type <classname>THREE.Points</classname>, 
we can use a material of type <classname>THREE.PointsMaterial</classname>,
which is a subclass of <classname>Material</classname>.  The material can specify
the color and the size of the points, among other properties:</p>

<pre>let pointsMat = new THREE.PointsMaterial( {
              color: "yellow",
              size: 2,
              sizeAttenuation: false
          } );</pre>

<np>The parameter to the constructor is a JavaScript object whose properties are used
to initialize the material.  With the <i>sizeAttenuation</i> property set to <i>false</i>,
the size is given in pixels; if it is <i>true</i>, then <i>size</i> represents the
size in world coordinates and the point is scaled to reflect distance from the viewer.  
If the <i>color</i> is omitted, a default value of white is used.
The default for <i>size</i> is&nbsp;1 and for <i>sizeAttenuation</i> is <i>true</i>. 
The parameter to the constructor can be omitted entirely, to use all the defaults.
A <classname>PointsMaterial</classname>
is not affected by lighting; it simply shows the color specified by its <i>color</i> property.</np>

<p>It is also possible to assign values to properties of the material after the object has
been created.  For example,</p>

<pre>let pointsMat = new THREE.PointsMaterial();
pointsMat.color = new THREE.Color("yellow");
pointsMat.size = 2;
pointsMat.sizeAttenuation = false;</pre>

<np>Note that the color is set as a value of type <i>THREE.Color</i>, which is constructed
from a string, "yellow".  When the color property is set in the material constructor,
the same conversion of string to color is done automatically.</np>

<p>Once we have the geometry and the material, 
we can use them to create the visible object, of type <classname>THREE.Points</classname>,
and add it to a scene:</p>

<pre>let sphereOfPoints = new THREE.Points( pointsGeom, pointsMat );
scene.add( sphereOfPoints );</pre>

<np>This will show a cloud of yellow points.  But we wanted each point to have
its own color!  Recall that the colors for the points are stored in the
geometry, not in the material.  We have to tell the material to use the
colors from the geometry, not the material's own color property.  This is
done by setting the value of the material property <i>vertexColors</i>
to <i>true</i>.  So, we could create the material using</np>

<pre>let pointsMat = new THREE.PointsMaterial( {
              color: "white",
              size: 2,
              sizeAttenuation: false,
              vertexColors: true
          } );</pre>

<p>White is used here as the material color because the vertex colors are
actually multiplied by the material color, not simply substituted for it.</p>

<demo src="c5/point-cloud.html" width="650" height="370"><p><tex>The on-line
demo <demoref href="c5/point-cloud.html"/> shows an animated point cloud,
where the user can choose between yellow points and randomly colored points.</tex><web>The following
demo shows a point cloud.  You can control whether the points are all yellow or
are randomly colored.  You can animate the points, and you can control the size
and number of points.  Note that points are rendered as squares.</web>
</p></demo>


<break/>

<p>The color parameter in the above material was specified by the string "yellow".  Colors
in <i>three.js</i> can be represented by values of type <classname>THREE.Color</classname>.
The class <classname>THREE.Color</classname> represents an <word>RGB color</word>.
A <classname>Color</classname> object <i>c</i> has properties <i>c.r</i>, <i>c.g</i>,
and <i>c.b</i> giving the red, blue, and green color components as floating point numbers in the
range from 0.0 to 1.0. Note that there is no <word term="alpha color component">alpha</word>
component; <i>three.js</i> handles transparency separately from color.</p>

<p>There are several ways to construct a <classname>THREE.Color</classname> object.  The constructor
can take three parameters giving the RGB components as real
numbers in the range 0.0 to 1.0.  It can take a single string parameter
giving the color as a CSS color string, like those used in the 2D canvas graphics API;
examples include "white", "red", "rgb(255,0,0)", and "#FF0000".  Or the color constructor can take
a single integer parameter in which each color component is given as an eight-bit field
in the integer.  Usually, an integer that is used to represent a color in this way is
written as a hexadecimal literal, beginning with "0x".  Examples include 0xff0000 for
red, 0x00ff00 for green, 0x0000ff for blue, and 0x007050 for a dark blue-green.  Here are some
examples of using color constructors:</p>

<pre>let c1 = new THREE.Color("skyblue");
let c2 = new THREE.Color(1,1,0);  // yellow
let c3 = new THREE.Color(0x98fb98);  // pale green</pre>

<p>In many contexts, such as the <classname>THREE.Points</classname> constructor,
<i>three.js</i> will accept a string or integer where a color
is required; the string or integer will be fed through the <classname>Color</classname> 
constructor.  As another example, a <classname>WebGLRenderer</classname> object has a
"clear color" property that is used as the background color when the renderer renders a
scene.  This property could be set using any of the following commands:</p>

<pre>renderer.setClearColor( new THREE.Color(0.6, 0.4, 0.1) );
renderer.setClearColor( "darkgray" );
renderer.setClearColor( 0x99BBEE );</pre>

<break/>

<p>Turning next to lines, an object of type <classname>THREE.Line</classname> represents
a line strip&mdash;what would be a primitive of the type
called <i>GL_LINE_STRIP</i> in OpenGL.  To get the same strip of connected line segments,
plus a line back to the starting vertex, we can use an object of type <classname>THREE.LineLoop</classname>.  
For the outline of a triangle, for
example, we could provide a <classname>BufferGeometry</classname> holding coordinates
for three points and use a <classname>LineLoop</classname>.</p>

<p>We will also need a material.  For lines, the material can be represented
by an object of type <classname>THREE.LineBasicMaterial</classname>.
As usual, the parameter for the constructor is a JavaScript
object, whose properties can include <i>color</i> and <i>linewidth</i>.  For example:</p>

<pre>let lineMat = new THREE.LineBasicMaterial( {
    color:  0xA000A0,  // purple; the default is white
    linewidth: 2       // 2 pixels; the default is 1
} );</pre>

<np>(The <code>linewidth</code> property might not be respected. According to the
specification, a WebGL implementation can set the maximum line width to&nbsp;1.)</np>

<p>As with points, it is possible to specify a different color for each purpose
by adding a "color" attribute to the geometry and setting the value of the
<i>vertexColors</i> material property to <i>true</i>.  Here is a complete example
that makes a triangle with vertices colored red, green, and blue:</p>


<pre>let positionBuffer = new Float32Array([
        -2, -2,   // Coordinates for first vertex.
         2, -2,   // Coordinates for second vertex.
         0,  2    // Coordinates for third vertex.
    ]);
let colorBuffer = new Float32Array([
        1, 0, 0,  // Color for first vertex (red).
        0, 1, 0,  // Color for second vertex (green).
        0, 0, 1   // Color for third vertex (blue).
   ]);    
let lineGeometry = new THREE.BufferGeometry();
lineGeometry.setAttribute(
        "position",
        new THREE.BufferAttribute(positionBuffer,2)
    );
lineGeometry.setAttribute(
        "color",
        new THREE.BufferAttribute(colorBuffer,3)
    );
let lineMaterial = new THREE.LineBasicMaterial( {
        linewidth: 3,
        vertexColors: true
    } );
let triangle = new THREE.LineLoop( lineGeometry, lineMaterial );
scene.add(triangle);
</pre>

<np>This produces the image:</np>

<img src="threejs-triangle-vertexcolors.png" width="152" height="144" 
      bordered="true" tex="threejs-triangle-vertexcolors.eps" texscale="0.6"/>

<p>The "Basic" in <classname>LineBasicMaterial</classname>
indicates that this material uses basic colors that do not require lighting
to be visible and are not affected by lighting.  This is generally what
you want for lines.</p>

<break/>
    
<p>A mesh object in <i>three.js</i> corresponds to the OpenGL primitive
<i>GL_TRIANGLES</i>.  
The geometry object for a mesh must specify which vertices are part of which triangles.
We will see how to do that in the <localref href="threejs.2">next section</localref>. However,
<i>three.js</i> comes with classes to represent common mesh geometries, such as a sphere,
a cylinder, and a torus.  For these built-in classes, you just need to
call a constructor to create the appropriate geometry.  For example, the class 
<classname>THREE.CylinderGeometry</classname>
represents the geometry for a cylinder, and its constructor takes the form</p>

<pre>new THREE.CylinderGeometry(radiusTop, radiusBottom, height,
           radiusSegments, heightSegments, openEnded, thetaStart, thetaLength)</pre>

<np>The geometry created by this constructor represents an approximation for a cylinder
that has its axis lying along the <i>y</i>-axis.  It extends
from &minus;<i>height</i>/2 to <i>height</i>/2 along that axis.
The radius of its circular top is <i>radiusTop</i> and of its
bottom is <i>radiusBottom</i>.  The two radii
don't have to be the same; when the are different, you get a truncated cone rather
than a cylinder as such.  Using a value of zero for <i>radiusTop</i> makes an actual cone.
The parameters <i>radiusSegments</i> and <i>heightSegments</i>
give the number of subdivisions around the circumference of the cylinder and
along its length respectively&mdash;what are called slices and stacks in the 
<word>GLUT</word> library for OpenGL.
The parameter <i>openEnded</i> is a boolean value that indicates
whether the top and bottom of the cylinder are to be drawn; use the value <i>true</i>
to get an open-ended tube.  Finally, the last two parameters allow you to make
a partial cylinder.  Their values are given as angles, measured in radians, about 
the <i>y</i>-axis.  Only the part of the cylinder beginning at <i>thetaStart</i>
and ending at <i>thetaStart</i> plus <i>thetaLength</i> is rendered.  For example,
if <i>thetaLength</i> is <i>Math.PI</i>, you will get a half-cylinder.</np>

<p>The large number of parameters to the constructor gives a lot of flexibility.
The parameters are all optional.  The default value for each of the first three
parameters is one.
The default for <i>radiusSegments</i> is 8, which gives a poor approximation
for a smooth cylinder.  Leaving out the last three parameters will give
a complete cylinder, closed at both ends.</p>

<p>Other standard mesh geometries are similar.  Here are some constructors, listing
all parameters (but keep in mind that most of the parameters are optional):</p>

<pre>new THREE.BoxGeometry(width, height, depth,
                         widthSegments, heightSegments, depthSegments)
                                
new THREE.PlaneGeometry(width, height, widthSegments, heightSegments)

new THREE.RingGeometry(innerRadius, outerRadius, thetaSegments, phiSegments,
                         thetaStart, thetaLength)

new THREE.ConeGeometry(radiusBottom, height, radiusSegments, 
                         heightSegments, openEnded, thetaStart, thetaLength)

new THREE.SphereGeometry(radius, widthSegments, heightSegments,
                         phiStart, phiLength, thetaStart, thetaLength)
                         
new THREE.TorusGeometry(radius, tube, radialSegments, tubularSegments, arc)</pre>

<p>The class <classname>BoxGeometry</classname>
represents the geometry of a rectangular box centered at the origin.  Its constructor
has three parameters to give the size of the box in each direction; their default value
is one.  The last three parameters give the number of subdivisions
in each direction, with a default of one; values greater than one will cause the faces
of the box to be subdivided into smaller triangles.</p>

<p>The class <classname>PlaneGeometry</classname> represents the
geometry of a rectangle lying in the <i>xy</i>-plane, centered at the origin.
Its parameters are similar to those for a cube.  A <classname>RingGeometry</classname>
represents an annulus, that is, a disk with a smaller disk removed from its center.
The ring lies in the <i>xy</i>-plane, with its center at the origin.
You should always specify the inner and outer radii of the ring.</p>

<p>The constructor for <classname>ConeGeometry</classname>  has exactly the same
form and effect as the constructor for <classname>CylinderGeometry</classname>, with
the <i>radiusTop</i> set to zero.  That is, it constructs a cone with axis along
the y-axis and centered at the origin.</p>

<p>For <classname>SphereGeometry</classname>, all parameters
are optional.  The constructor creates a sphere centered at the origin,
with axis along the <i>y</i>-axis.  The first parameter, which gives the radius of the sphere,
has a default of one.  The next two parameters
give the numbers of slices and stacks, with default values 32 and 16.
The last four parameters allow you to make a piece of a sphere; the default values
give a complete sphere.  The four parameters are angles measured in radians.  <i>phiStart</i>
and <i>phiLength</i> are measured in angles around the equator and give the extent in
longitude of the spherical shell that is generated.  For example,
</p>

<pre>new THREE.SphereGeometry( 5, 32, 16, 0, Math.PI )</pre>

<np>creates the geometry for the "western hemisphere" of a sphere.  The
last two parameters are angles measured along a line of latitude from the north pole
of the sphere to the south pole.  For example, to get the sphere's "northern hemisphere":</np>

<pre>new THREE.SphereGeometry( 5, 32, 16, 0, 2*Math.PI, 0, Math.PI/2 )</pre>

<p>For <classname>TorusGeometry</classname>, the constructor creates a torus
lying in the <i>xy</i>-plane, centered at the origin, with the <i>z</i>-axis passing through
its hole.  The parameter <i>radius</i> is the distance from
the center of the torus to the center of the torus's tube, while <i>tube</i>
is the radius of the tube.  The next two parameters give the number of subdivisions in
each direction.  The last parameter, <i>arc</i>, allows you to make just part of a torus.
It is an angle between 0 and <i>2*Math.PI</i>, measured along the circle at the center of the
tube.
</p>

<p>There are also geometry classes representing the 
<word term="regular polyhedron">regular polyhedra</word>:
<classname>THREE.TetrahedronGeometry</classname>,
<classname>THREE.OctahedronGeometry</classname>,
<classname>THREE.DodecahedronGeometry</classname>, and
<classname>THREE.IcosahedronGeometry</classname>.  (For a cube use a
<classname>BoxGeometry</classname>.)  The constructors for these four classes
take two parameters.  The first specifies the size of the polyhedron, with a default
of 1.  The size is given as the radius of the sphere that contains the polyhedron.
The second parameter is an integer called <i>detail</i>.  The default value, 0, gives
the actual regular polyhedron.  Larger values add detail by adding additional faces.
As the detail increases, the polyhedron becomes a better approximation for a sphere.
This is easier to understand with an illustration:
</p>

<img src="icosahedron-detail.png" width="499" height="126" tex="icosahedron-detail.eps" texscale="0.75"/>

<np>The image shows four mesh objects that use icosahedral geometries with
detail parameter equal to 0, 1, 2, and&nbsp;3.</np>

<break/>
    
<p>To create a mesh object, you need a material as well as a geometry.  There are
several kinds of material suitable for mesh objects, including  <classname>THREE.MeshBasicMaterial</classname>,
<classname>THREE.MeshLambertMaterial</classname>, and <classname>THREE.MeshPhongMaterial</classname>.
(There are more mesh materials, including two newer ones, <classname>THREE.MeshStandardMaterial</classname>
and <classname>THREE.MeshPhysicalMaterial</classname>, that implement techniques associated
with <word term="PBR">physically based rendering</word>, an approach to improved rendering that
has become popular.  However, I will not cover them here.)</p>  
<p>A <classname>MeshBasicMaterial</classname> represents a color that
is not affected by lighting; it looks the same whether or not there are lights in the
scene, and it is not shaded, giving it a flat rather than 3D appearance.
The other two classes represent materials that need to be lit to be seen.  They implement
models of lighting known as <newword>Lambert shading</newword> and
<newword>Phong shading</newword>.  The major difference
is that <classname>MeshPhongMaterial</classname> has a specular color but
<classname>MeshLambertMaterial</classname> does not.  Both can have diffuse
and emissive colors.  For all three material classes, the constructor has one
parameter, a JavaScript object that specifies values for properties of the
material.  For example:
</p>

<pre>let mat = new THREE.MeshPhongMaterial( {
          color: 0xbbbb00,     // reflectivity for diffuse and ambient light
          emissive: 0,         // emission color; this is the default (black)
          specular: 0x303030,  // reflectivity for specular light
          shininess: 50        // controls size of specular highlights
    } );</pre>

<np>This example shows the four color parameters for a Phong material.  The parameters
have the same meaning as the five <word>material</word> properties in OpenGL (<localref href="gl1light.1.1"/>).
A Lambert material lacks <i>specular</i> and <i>shininess</i>, and a basic mesh
material has only the <i>color</i> parameter.</np>

<p>There are a few other material properties that you might need to set in the constructor.
Except for <i>flatShading</i>, these apply to all three kinds of mesh material:</p>

<ul>
    <li><code>vertexColors</code> &mdash; a boolean property that can be set to <i>true</i>
    to use vertex colors from the geometry.  The default is <i>false</i>.</li>
    <li><code>wireframe</code> &mdash; a boolean value that indicates whether the mesh
      should be drawn as a wireframe model, showing only the outlines of its faces.  The
      default is <i>false</i>. A <i>true</i> value works best with <classname>MeshBasicMaterial</classname>.</li>
    <li><code>wireframeLinewidth</code> &mdash; the width of the lines used to draw the
    wireframe, in pixels.  The default is&nbsp;1.  (Non-default values might not be
    respected.)</li>
    <li><code>visible</code> &mdash; a boolean value that controls 
    whether the object on which it is used is
    rendered or not, with a default of <i>true</i>.</li>
    <li><code>side</code> &mdash; has value <i>THREE.FrontSide</i>, <i>THREE.BackSide</i>,
    or <i>THREE.DoubleSide</i>, with the default being <i>THREE.FrontSide</i>.  This determines
    whether faces of the mesh are drawn or not, depending on which side of the face is visible.  
    With the default value, <i>THREE.FrontSide</i>, a face
    is drawn only if it is being viewed from the front.  <i>THREE.DoubleSide</i> will draw
    it whether it is viewed from the front or from the back, and <i>THREE.BackSide</i> only
    if it is viewed from the back.  For closed objects, such as a cube or a complete sphere,
    the default value makes sense, at least as long as the viewer is outside of the object.
    For a plane, an open tube, or a partial sphere, the value should be set to
    <i>THREE.DoubleSide</i>.  Otherwise, parts of the object that should be in view won't
    be drawn.</li>
    <li><code>flatShading</code> &mdash; a <i>boolean</i> value,
    with the default being <i>false</i>.  This does not work for <classname>MeshBasicMaterial</classname>.
    For an object that is supposed to look "faceted," with flat sides, it is
    important to set this property to <i>true</i>.  That would be the case, for
    example, for a cube or for a cylinder with a small number of sides.</li>
</ul>

<np>As an example, let's make a shiny, blue-green, open, five-sided tube with flat sides:</np>

<pre>let mat = new THREE.MeshPhongMaterial( {
       color: 0x0088aa, 
       specular: 0x003344, 
       shininess: 100,
       flatShading: true,  // for flat-looking sides
       side: THREE.DoubleSide  // for drawing the inside of the tube
    } );
let geom = new THREE.CylinderGeometry(3,3,10,5,1,true);
let obj = new THREE.Mesh(geom,mat);
scene.add(obj);</pre>

<demo src="c5/mesh-objects.html" width="610" height="370"><p><tex>The on-line demo
<demoref href="c5/mesh-objects.html"/> lets you view a variety of <i>three.js</i>
mesh objects with several different materials.</tex><web>You can use the following
demo to view several <i>three.js</i> mesh objects, using a variety of geometries
and materials.  Drag your mouse on the object to rotate it.
You can also explore the level of detail for the regular polyhedron
geometries.</web></p>
</demo>

<p>The demo can show a wireframe version of an object overlaid on a solid version.
In <i>three.js</i>, the wireframe and solid versions are actually two objects that
use the same geometry but different materials.  Drawing two objects at exactly the
same depth can be a problem for the <word>depth test</word>.  You might remember from 
<localref href="gl1geom.4.1"/> that OpenGL uses <word>polygon offset</word> to solve the problem.
In <i>three.js</i>, you can apply polygon offset to a material.  In the demos, this
is done for the solid materials that are shown at the same time as wireframe materials.  
For example,</p>

<pre>mat = new THREE.MeshLambertMaterial({
      polygonOffset: true,  
      polygonOffsetUnits: 1,
      polygonOffsetFactor: 1,
      color: "yellow",
      side: THREE.DoubleSide
  });</pre>
  
<np>The settings shown here for <i>polygonOffset</i>, <i>polygonOffsetUnits</i>, and
<i>polygonOffsetFactor</i> will increase the depth of the object that uses this material
slightly so that it doesn't interfere with the wireframe version of the same object.</np>

<p>One final note: You don't always need to make new materials and geometries
to make new objects.  You can reuse the same materials and geometries in multiple
objects.</p>


</subsection>



<subsection title="Lights" id="threejs.1.4">


<p>Compared to geometries and materials, lights are easy!  <i>Three.js</i>
has several classes to represent lights.  Light classes are subclasses of <i>THREE.Object3D</i>.
A light object can be added to a scene and will then illuminate objects in the scene.
We'll look at <word term="directional light">directional lights</word>,
<word term="point light">point lights</word>,
<word term="ambient light">ambient lights</word>, and <word term="spotlight">spotlights</word>.</p>

<p>The class <classname>THREE.DirectionalLight</classname> represents
light that shines in parallel rays from a given direction, like the light from
the sun.  The <i>position</i> property of a directional light gives the direction
from which the light shines.  (This is the same <i>position</i> property, of type
<classname>Vector3</classname>, that all scene graph objects have, but the meaning
is different for directional lights.)  Note that the light shines from the given position 
towards the origin.  The default position is
the vector (0,1,0), which gives a light shining down the <i>y</i>-axis.  The
constructor for this class has two parameters:</p>

<pre>new THREE.DirectionalLight( color, intensity )</pre>

<np>where <i>color</i> specifies the color of the light, given as a <classname>THREE.Color</classname> object,
or as a hexadecimal integer, or as a CSS color string.   Lights do not have separate
diffuse and specular colors, as they do in OpenGL.  The <i>intensity</i> is a non-negative number
that controls the brightness of the light, with larger values making the light
brighter.  A light with intensity zero gives no light at all.  The parameters
are optional.  The default for <i>color</i> is white (0xffffff) and for <i>intensity</i> 
is&nbsp;1.  The intensity can be greater than 1, but values less than 1 are usually preferable,
to avoid having too much illumination in the scene.</np>

<p>Suppose that we have a camera on the positive <i>z</i>-axis,
looking towards the origin, and we would like a light that shines in the same
direction that the camera is looking.  We can use a directional light whose
position is on the positive <i>z</i>-axis:</p>

<pre>let light = new THREE.DirectionalLight(); // default white light
light.position.set( 0, 0, 1 );
scene.add(light);</pre>


<p>The class <classname>THREE.PointLight</classname>  represents a light
that shines in all directions from a point.  The location of the point is given
by the light's <i>position</i> property.  The constructor has three optional
parameters:</p>

<pre>new THREE.PointLight( color, intensity, cutoff )</pre>

<np>The first two parameters are the same as for a directional light,
with the same defaults.  The <i>cutoff</i> is a non-negative number.
If the value is zero&mdash;which is the default&mdash;then the illumination from the
light extends to infinity, and intensity does not decrease with distance.  While
this is not physically realistic, it generally works well in practice.  If <i>cutoff</i>
is greater than zero, then the intensity falls from a maximum value at the light's position
down to an intensity of zero at a distance of <i>cutoff</i> from the light;
the light has no effect on objects that are at a distance greater than <i>cutoff</i>.  
This falloff of light intensity with distance is referred to as
<newword>attenuation</newword> of the light source.</np>

<p>A third type of light is <classname>THREE.AmbientLight</classname>.
This class exists to add ambient light to a scene.  An ambient light has
only a color:</p>

<pre>new THREE.AmbientLight( color )</pre>

<np>Adding an ambient light object to a scene adds ambient light of the specified color
to the scene.  The color components of an ambient light should be rather
small to avoid washing out colors of objects.</np>

<p>For example, suppose that we would like a yellowish point light at (10,30,15) whose illumination
falls off with distance from that point, out to a distance of 100 units.  We also want to
add a bit of yellow ambient light to the scene:</p>

<pre>let light = new THREE.PointLight( 0xffffcc, 1, 100 );
light.position.set( 10, 30, 15 );
scene.add(light);
scene.add( new THREE.AmbientLight(0x111100) );</pre>

<break/>

<p>The fourth type of light, <classname>THREE.SpotLight</classname>, is something new
for us.  An object of that type represents a <newword>spotlight</newword>, 
which is similar to a point light, except that instead of shining in all directions, a spotlight
only produces a cone of light.  The vertex of the cone is located at the position of the light.
By default, the axis of the cone points from that location towards the origin (so unless you
change the direction of the axis, you should move the position of the light away from the origin).
The constructor adds two parameters to those for a point light:</p>

<pre>new THREE.SpotLight( color, intensity, cutoff, coneAngle, exponent )</pre>

<np>The <i>coneAngle</i> is a number between 0 and <i>Math.PI/2</i>
that determines the size of the cone of light.  It is the angle between the
axis of the cone and the side of the cone.  The default value is <i>Math.PI/3</i>.
The <i>exponent</i> is a non-negative number that determines how fast the intensity
of the light decreases as you move from the axis of the cone toward the side.  The default
value, 10, gives a reasonable result. An <i>exponent</i> of zero gives no
falloff at all, so that objects at all distances from the axis are evenly illuminated.</np>

<p>The technique for setting the direction of a <i>three.js</i> spotlight is a little
odd, but it does make it easy to control the direction.
An object <i>spot</i> of type <classname>SpotLight</classname> has a property
named <i>spot.target</i>.  The target is a scene graph node.  The cone of light from
the spotlight is pointed in the direction from spotlight's position towards the
target's position.  When a spotlight is first created, its target is a new, empty 
<i>Object3D</i>, with position at (0,0,0).  However, you can set the target to be
any object in the scene graph, which will make the spotlight shine towards that object.
For <i>three.js</i> to calculate the spotlight direction, a target whose position is
anything other than the origin must actually be a node in the scene graph.
For example, suppose we want a spotlight located at the point (0,0,5) and pointed
towards the point (2,2,0):</p>

<pre>spotlight = new THREE.SpotLight();
spotlight.position.set(0,0,5);
spotlight.target.position.set(2,2,0);
scene.add(spotlight);
scene.add(spotlight.target);</pre>



</subsection>

<subsection title="A Modeling Example" id="threejs.1.5">

<p>In the rest of this chapter, we will go much deeper into <i>three.js</i>, but you
already know enough to build 3D models from basic geometric objects.  An example
is in the sample program <sourceref href="threejs/diskworld-1.html"/>, which shows
a very simple model of a car driving around the edge of a cylindrical base.  The car
has rotating tires.  The diskworld is shown in the picture on the left below.
The picture on the right shows one of the axles from the car, with a tire on
each end.</p>


<img src="diskworld-1.png" width="637" height="192" tex="diskworld-1.eps" texscale="0.6"/>

<np>I will discuss some of the code that is used to build these models.  If you want
to experiment with your own models, you can use the program <sourceref href="threejs/modeling-starter.html"/>
as a starting point.</np>

<p>To start with something simple, let's look at how to make a tree from a
brown cylinder and a green cone.  I use an <classname>Object3D</classname>
to represent the tree as a whole, so that I can treat it as a unit.  The
two geometric objects are added as children of the <classname>Object3D</classname>.</p>

<pre>let tree = new THREE.Object3D();

let trunk = new THREE.Mesh(
    new THREE.CylinderGeometry(0.2,0.2,1,16,1),
    new THREE.MeshLambertMaterial({
        color: 0x885522
    })
);
trunk.position.y = 0.5;  // move base up to origin

let leaves = new THREE.Mesh(
    new THREE.ConeGeometry(.7,2,16,3),
    new THREE.MeshPhongMaterial({
        color: 0x00BB00,
        specular: 0x002000,
        shininess: 5
    })
);
leaves.position.y = 2;  // move bottom of cone to top of trunk

tree.add(trunk);
tree.add(leaves);</pre>

<np>The trunk is a cylinder with height equal to 1.  Its axis lies along the <i>y</i>-axis,
and it is centered at the origin.  The plane of the diskworld lies in the <i>xz</i>-plane,
so I want to move the bottom of the trunk onto that plane.  This is done by setting the
value of <i>trunk.position.y</i>, which represents a translation to be applied to
the trunk. Remember that objects have their own modeling coordinate system.
The properties of objects that specify transformations, such as <i>trunk.position</i>, 
transform the object in that coordinate system.  In this case, the trunk is part of
a larger, compound object that represents the whole tree.  When the scene is
rendered, the trunk is first transformed by its own modeling transformation.
It is then further transformed by any modeling transformation that is applied to
the tree as a whole.  (This type of <word>hierarchical modeling</word> was first 
covered in <localref href="graphics2d.4.1"/>.)</np>

<p>Once we have a tree object, it can be added to the model that represents the
diskworld.  In the program, the model is an object of type <classname>Object3D</classname>
named <i>diskworldModel</i>.  The model will contain several trees, but the trees
don't have to be constructed individually.  I can
make additional trees by cloning the one that I have already created.  For example:</p>

<pre>tree.position.set(-1.5,0,2);
tree.scale.set(0.7,0.7,0.7);
diskworldModel.add( tree.clone() );

tree.position.set(-1,0,5.2);
tree.scale.set(0.25,0.25,0.25);
diskworldModel.add( tree.clone() );</pre>

<np>This adds two trees to the model, with different sizes and positions.  When the
tree is cloned, the clone gets its own copies of the modeling transformation properties,
<i>position</i> and <i>scale</i>.  Changing the values of those properties in the
original tree object does not affect the clone.</np>

<p>Lets turn to a more complicated object, the axle and wheels.  I start by creating
a wheel, using a torus for the tire and using three copies of a cylinder for the spokes.  
In this case, instead of making a new <classname>Object3D</classname> to hold all 
the components of the wheel, I add the cylinders as children of the torus.  Remember that any screen
graph node in <i>three.js</i> can have child nodes.</p>

<pre>let wheel = new THREE.Mesh(  // the tire; spokes will be added as children
    new THREE.TorusGeometry(0.75, 0.25, 16, 32),
    new THREE.MeshLambertMaterial({ color: 0x0000A0 })
);
let yellow = new THREE.MeshPhongMaterial({
        color: 0xffff00,
        specular: 0x101010,
        shininess: 16
    });
let cylinder = new THREE.Mesh(  // a cylinder with height 1 and diameter 1
    new THREE.CylinderGeometry(0.5,0.5,1,32,1),
    yellow
);

cylinder.scale.set(0.15,1.2,0.15); // Make it thin and tall for use as a spoke.

wheel.add( cylinder.clone() );  // Add a copy of the cylinder.
cylinder.rotation.z = Math.PI/3;  // Rotate it for the second spoke.
wheel.add( cylinder.clone() );
cylinder.rotation.z = -Math.PI/3; // Rotate it for the third spoke.
wheel.add( cylinder.clone() );</pre>

<np>Once I have the wheel model, I can use it along with one more cylinder
to make the axle. For the axle, I use a cylinder lying along the <i>z</i>-axis.
The wheel lies in the <i>xy</i>-plane.  It is facing in the correct direction,
but it lies in the center of the axle.  To get it into its correct position at
the end of the axle, it just has to be translated along the <i>z-axis</i>.</np>

<pre>axleModel = new THREE.Object3D(); // A model containing two wheels and an axle.
cylinder.scale.set(0.2,4.3,0.2);  // Scale the cylinder for use as an axle.
cylinder.rotation.set(Math.PI/2,0,0); // Rotate its axis onto the z-axis.
axleModel.add( cylinder );
wheel.position.z = 2;  // Wheels are positioned at the two ends of the axle.
axleModel.add( wheel.clone() );
wheel.position.z = -2;
axleModel.add( wheel );</pre>

<np>Note that for the second wheel, I add the original wheel model rather than a
clone.  There is no need to make an extra copy.  With the <i>axleModel</i> in hand,
I can build the car from two copies of the axle plus some other components.</np>

<p>The diskworld can be animated.  To implement the animation, properties of
the appropriate scene graph nodes are modified before each frame of the animation
is rendered.  For example, to make the wheels on the car rotate, the rotation
of each axle about its <i>z</i>-axis is increased in each frame:</p>

<pre>carAxle1.rotation.z += 0.05;
carAxle2.rotation.z += 0.05;</pre>

<np>This changes the modeling transformation that will be applied to the axles
when they are rendered.  In its own coordinate system, the central axis of an axle lies along
the <i>z</i>-axis.  The rotation about the <i>z</i>-axis rotates the axle,
with its attached tires, about its axis.</np>

<p>For the full details of the sample program, see the <sourceref href="threejs/diskworld-1.html">source code</sourceref>.</p>

</subsection>




</section>

