<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section SYSTEM "../graphicstext.dtd" >

<section title="Other Features" id="threejs.3">

<p1>We will finish this chapter with a look at a few additional features
of <i>three.js</i>.  In the process, you will learn about some new aspects
of 3D graphics.</p1>


<subsection title="Instanced Meshes" id="threejs.3.1">

<p>The class <classname>THREE.InstancedMesh</classname> makes it possible to 
quickly render several objects, possibly a large number of objects, that
use the same geometry but differ in the transformations that
are applied to them and, possibly, in their material color.  Each copy of the
object is called an "instance," and the process of creating all of the
copies is called <word>instanced drawing</word> or instancing. 
In WebGL&nbsp;2.0 (and in WebGL&nbsp;1.0 with an extension), it is possible to draw all of the
instances with a single function call, making it very efficient.</p>

<p><classname>InstancedMesh</classname> is fairly easy to use.  Along with
the geometry and material for the mesh, the constructor specifies
the maximum number of instances that it can support:
</p>

<p>instances = new THREE.InstancedMesh(geometry, material, count)</p>

<np>To set the transformation for instance number <i>i</i>,
you can call</np>

<pre>instances.setMatrixAt( i, matrix );</pre>

<np>where <i>matrix</i> is an object of type <classname>THREE.Matrix4</classname>
representing the modeling transformation.  Similarly, you can set the
color for instance number <i>i</i> with</np>

<pre>instances.setColorAt( i, color );</pre>

<np>where <i>color</i> is of type <classname>THREE.Color</classname>.
Instance colors are optional.  If provided, they replace the color
property of <i>material</i>.</np>

<p>The <classname>Matrix4</classname> class includes methods that make
it easy to create a transformation matrix. The constructor</p>

<pre>matrix = new THREE.Matrix4();</pre>

<np>creates an
identity matrix, which can then be modified.  For example,
the method <i>matrix.makeTranslation</i>(<i>dx,dy,dz</i>) replaces the
current matrix with the transformation matrix for a translation by
the vector (<i>dx,dy,dz</i>).  There are functions for making scaling
and rotation matrices.  To make more complex transformations, there
is a function for multiplying matrices.</np>

<p>The sample program <sourceref href="threejs/instanced-mesh.html"/>
uses a single <classname>InstancedMesh</classname> to make 1331 spheres, arranged
in an 11-by-11-by-11 cube.  To move the spheres into position, different
translations are applied to each instance.  An instance color is also
set for each instance.</p>

<img src="instanced-mesh.png" width="237" height="234" tex="instanced-mesh.eps" texscale="0.6"/>


</subsection>


<subsection title="User Input" id="threejs.3.2">

<p>Most real programs require some kind of user interaction.  For a web application,
of course, the program can get user input using HTML widgets such as buttons and text input boxes.
But direct mouse interaction with a 3D world is more natural in many programs.</p>

<p>The most basic example is using the mouse to rotate the scene.  In <i>three.js</i>,
rotation can be implemented using the class <classname>TrackballControls</classname> or the
class <classname>OrbitControls</classname>. Note that both classes support touchscreen
as well as mouse interaction.  The main difference between the classes
is that with <i>OrbitControls</i>,
the rotation is constrained so that the positive <i>y</i>-axis is always the up direction
in the view.  <i>TrackballControls</i>, on the other hand, allows completely free
rotation.  Another difference is that <i>TrackballControls</i> is meant to be used
only with a scene that is continuously animated.  <i>OrbitControls</i> is used for rotation in
most of my sample programs and demos.  <i>TrackballControls</i> is used only in
<sourceref href="threejs/full-window.html"/> and <sourceref href="threejs/curves-and-surfaces.html"/>.</p>


<p>The two control classes are not part of the main <i>three.js</i> JavaScript file.
They can be imported from the modules "OrbitControls.js" and "TrackballControls.js",
which can be found
in the <sourceref href="threejs/script/controls"/> folder in the <i>source</i> folder for this textbook,
or in the <code>examples/jsm/loaders</code> folder in the <i>three.js</i> download.</p>

<p>The two classes are used in a similar way.  I will discuss <classname>OrbitControls</classname> first.
In my examples, I create a camera and move it away from the origin. I usually add a light object
to the camera object, so that the light will move along with the camera, providing some
illumination to anything that is visible to the camera.  The <classname>OrbitControls</classname>
object is used to rotate the camera around the scene.  The constructor for the
control object has two parameters, the camera and the canvas on which the scene is rendered.
Here is typical setup:</p>

<pre>camera = new THREE.PerspectiveCamera(45, canvas.width/canvas.height, 0.1, 100);
camera.position.set(0,15,35);
camera.lookAt( new THREE.Vector3(0,0,0) ); // camera looks toward origin

let light = new THREE.PointLight(0xffffff, 0.6);
camera.add(light);  // viewpoint light moves with camera
scene.add(camera);

controls = new OrbitControls( camera, canvas );</pre>

<np>The constructor installs listeners on the <i>canvas</i> so that the controls can respond
to mouse events.  If an animation is running, the only other thing that you need to
do is call</np>

<pre>controls.update();</pre>

<np>before rendering the scene. The
user will be able to rotate the scene by dragging on it with the left mouse button.
The controls will also do "panning" (dragging the scene in the plane of the screen)
with the right mouse button and "zooming" (moving the camera forward and backward) with the middle mouse button
or scroll wheel.   To disable zooming and panning, you can set</np>

<pre>controls.enablePan = false;
controls.enableZoom = false;</pre>

<np>And you can return the original view of the scene by calling
<i>controls.reset</i>().</np>

<p>If your program is not running a continuous animation,
you need a way to re-render the scene in response to user actions.
When the user drags the mouse, the <i>controls</i> object
generates a "change" event.  You can add a listener for that
event, to respond to the event by redrawing the scene.  To
do that, just call</p>

<pre>controls.addEventListener( "change", callback );</pre>

<np>Where <i>callback</i>() is the function that should be called
when the event occurs.  If you have a function <i>render</i>() that
renders your scene, you can simply pass <i>render</i> as the
value of <i>callback</i>.</np>

<p>Unfortunately, a <classname>TrackballControls</classname> object
does not emit "change" events, and there does not seem to be any way to
use it without having an animation running.  With an animation,
<i>TrackballControls</i> are used in the same way as <i>OrbitControls</i>,
except that the properties for panning and zooming 
are <i>controls.noPan</i> and <i>controls.noZoom</i>; they 
should be set to <i>true</i> to disable panning and zooming.
One nice feature of <classname>TrackballControls</classname>
is that they implement inertia: When the user releases the mouse
after dragging, the motion of the scene will slow to a stop instead
of stopping abruptly.</p>

<break/>

<p>A much more interesting form of mouse interaction is to let the user select objects
in the scene by clicking on them.  The problem is to determine which object the
user is clicking.  The general procedure is something like this:  Follow a ray from
the camera through the point on the screen where the user clicked and find the first
object in the scene that is intersected by that ray.  That's the object that is visible
at the point where the user clicked.  Unfortunately, the procedure involves a lot
of calculations.  Fortunately, <i>three.js</i> has a class that can do the work for
you:  <classname>THREE.Raycaster</classname>.</p>

<p>A <classname>Raycaster</classname> can be used to find intersections of a ray with
objects in a scene.  (A ray is just half of a line, stretching from some given starting
point in a given direction towards infinity.)  You can make one raycaster object to use
throughout your program:</p>

<pre>raycaster = new THREE.Raycaster();</pre>

<np>To tell it which ray to use, you can call</np>

<pre>raycaster.set( startingPoint, direction );</pre>

<np>where both of the parameters are of type <classname>THREE.Vector3</classname>.
Their values are in terms of <word>world coordinates</word>, the same coordinate
system that you use for the scene as a whole.  The <i>direction</i> must
be a <word>normalized vector</word>, with length equal to one.
For example, suppose that you want to fire a laser gun&dots;.  The 
<i>startingPoint</i> is the location of the gun, and the <i>direction</i>
is the direction that the gun is pointing.  Configure the raycaster 
with those parameters, and you can use it to find out what object is struck
by the laser beam.</np>

<p>Alternatively, and more conveniently
for processing user input, you can express the ray in terms of the camera and
a point on the screen:</p>

<pre>raycaster.setFromCamera( screenCoords, camera );</pre>

<np>The <i>screenCoords</i> are given as a <classname>THREE.Vector2</classname> expressed
in <word>clip coordinates</word>.  This means the horizontal coordinate ranges from
&minus;1 on the left edge of the viewport to 1 on the right, and the vertical coordinate ranges from
&minus;1 at the bottom to 1 on the top.  (Clip coordinates are called "normalized device
coordinates" in <i>three.js</i>.)  So, we need to convert from pixel coordinates on a
canvas to clip coordinates.  Here's one way to do it, given a mouse event, <i>evt</i>:</np>

<pre>let r = canvas.getBoundingClientRect();
let x = evt.clientX - r.left; // convert mouse location to canvas pixel coords
let y = evt.clientY - r.top;

let a = 2*x/canvas.width - 1; // convert canvas pixel coords to clip coords
let b = 1 - 2*y/canvas.height;

raycaster.setFromCamera( new THREE.Vector2(a,b), camera );</pre>

<p>Once you have told the raycaster which ray to use, it is ready to find
intersections of that ray with objects in the scene.  This can be
done with the function</p>

<pre>raycaster.intersectObjects( objectArray, recursive );</pre>

<np>The first parameter is an array of <classname>Object3D</classname>.
The raycaster will search for intersections of its current ray with objects in the array.
If the second parameter is <i>true</i>, it will also search descendants of those
objects in the <word>scene graph</word>; if it is <i>false</i> or is omitted, then only the
objects in the array will be searched.  For example, to search for intersections
with all objects in the scene, use</np>

<pre>raycaster.intersectObjects( scene.children, true );</pre>

<p>The return value from <i>intersectObjects</i> is an array of JavaScript objects.
Each item in the array represents an intersection of the ray with an <classname>Object3D</classname>.
The function finds all such intersections, not just the first.  If no intersection is
found, the array is empty.  The array is sorted by increasing distance from the starting 
point of the ray.  If you just want the first intersection, use the first element of the array.</p>

<p>Each element in the array is an object whose properties contain information about the
intersection.  Suppose that <i>item</i> is one of the array elements.  Then the most useful
properties are:  <i>item.object</i>, which is the <classname>Object3D</classname> that 
was intersected by the ray; and <i>item.point</i>, which  is the point of intersection, 
given as a <classname>Vector3</classname> in world coordinates.  That information is
enough to implement some interesting user interaction.</p>

<demo src="c5/raycaster-input.html" width="620" height="430"><p><tex>The demo
<demoref href="c5/raycaster-input.html"/></tex><web>The following demo</web>
uses some basic mouse interaction to let the user edit a scene.  The scene shows
a number of tapered yellow cylinders standing on a green base.  The user can
drag the cylinders, add and delete cylinders, and rotate the scene.  A set of 
radio buttons lets the user select which action should be performed by the mouse.<tex>
Here's a screenshot from the program:</tex></p></demo>

<texdiv><img tex="raycaster-demo.eps" texscale="0.5"/></texdiv>

<p>Let's look at how the actions are implemented.   The only objects are the base and the
cylinders.  In the program, the base is referred to as <i>ground</i>, and all the objects
are children of an <classname>Object3D</classname> named <i>world</i>.  (I use the <i>world</i>
object to make it easy to rotate the set of all visible objects without moving the camera or lights.)
For all drag, add, and delete actions, I look for intersections of these objects with
a ray that extends from the camera through the mouse position:</p>

<pre>raycaster.setFromCamera( new THREE.Vector2(a,b), camera );
let intersects = raycaster.intersectObjects( world.children );</pre>

<np>If <i>intersects.length</i> is zero, there are no intersections, and there is nothing
to do.  Otherwise, I look at <i>intersects</i>[0], which represents an intersection with
the object that is visible at the mouse position.  So, <i>intersects</i>[0]<i>.object</i>
is the object that the user clicked, and <i>intersects</i>[0]<i>.point</i> is the
point of intersection.</np>

<p>The Delete action is the simplest to implement:  When the user clicks a cylinder, the cylinder should be 
removed from the scene.  If the first intersection is with the <i>ground</i>, then 
nothing is deleted.  Otherwise, the clicked object was a cylinder and should be deleted:</p>

<pre>if ( intersects[0].object != ground ) {
    world.remove( intersects[0].object );
    render();
}</pre>

<p>For an Add action, we should add a cylinder only if the user clicked the ground. In that case,
the point of intersection tells where the cylinder should be added.  An interesting issue
here is that we get the point of intersection in world coordinates, but in order to
add the cylinder as a child of <i>world</i>, I need to know the point of intersection
in the local coordinate system for <i>world</i>.  The two coordinate systems will be different
if the world has been rotated.  Fortunately, every <classname>Object3D</classname>
has a method <i>worldToLocal</i>(<i>v</i>) that can be used to transform a <classname>Vector3</classname>,
<i>v</i>, from world coordinates to local coordinates for that object.  This method does not
return a value; it modifies the coordinates of the vector&nbsp;<i>v</i>.  (There is also a
<i>localToWorld</i> method.)  So, the Add action can be implemented like this:</p>

<pre>item = intersects[0];
if (item.object == ground) {
    let locationX = item.point.x;  // world coords of intersection point
    let locationZ = item.point.z;
    let coords = new THREE.Vector3(locationX, 0, locationZ); // y is always 0
    world.worldToLocal(coords); // transform to local coords
    addCylinder(coords.x, coords.z); // adds a cylinder at corrected location
    render();
}</pre>

<p>For a Drag action, we can determine which cylinder was clicked using the same test as for delete.
However, the problem of moving the cylinder as the user drags the mouse raises a new issue:
how do we know where to put the cylinder when the mouse moves?  We somehow have to transform a new mouse
position into a new position for the cylinder.   For that, we can use the raycaster
again.  My first thought was to create a ray from the camera through the new mouse position, use that ray
to find its intersection with the ground, and then to move the cylinder to that 
point of intersection.  Unfortunately, this puts the <b>base</b> of the cylinder at the
mouse position, and it made the cylinder jump to the wrong position as soon as I started moving
the mouse.  I realized that I didn't want to track the intersection with the ground; I needed to
track the intersection with a plane that lies at the same height as the original point of intersection.
To implement this, I add an invisible plane at that height just during dragging,
and I use intersections with that plane instead of intersections with the ground.
(You can have invisible objects in <i>three.js</i>&mdash;just set the <i>visible</i> 
property of the material to <i>false</i>.)</p>


</subsection>



<subsection title="Shadows" id="threejs.3.3">

<p>One thing that has been missing in our 3D images is shadows.  Even if you didn't
notice the lack consciously, it made many of the images look wrong.
Shadows can add a nice touch of realism to a scene, but OpenGL, including WebGL, 
cannot generate shadows automatically.  There are ways to compute shadows that 
can be implemented in OpenGL, but they are tricky to use and they are not completely
realistic physically.  One method, which is called <newword>shadow mapping</newword>,
is implemented in <i>three.js</i>.  Shadow mapping in <i>three.js</i> is certainly not trivial to use,
but it is easier than trying to do the same thing from scratch.</p>

<demo src="c5/shadows.html" width="560" height="520"><p><web>Here is
a demo that</web><tex>The online demo <demoref href="c5/shadows.html"/></tex>
shows a <i>three.js</i> scene that uses shadow mapping.  The lights that
cast the shadows can be animated, so you can watch the shadows change
as the lights move.<tex>  Here is an image from the demo:</tex></p></demo>

<texdiv><img tex="threejs-shadows.eps" texscale="0.6"/></texdiv>

<p>The basic idea of shadow mapping is fairly straightforward: To tell what parts
of a scene are in shadow, you have to look at the scene from the point of view of
the light source.  Things that are visible from the point of view of the light
are illuminated by that light.  Things that are not visible from the light are
in shadow.  (This is ignoring the possibility of transparency and indirect, reflected
light, which cannot be handled by shadow mapping.)  To implement this idea, place a camera at the light source and take a picture.
In fact, you don't need the picture itself.  What you need is the <word>depth buffer</word>.  After the
picture has been rendered, the value stored in the depth buffer for a given pixel
contains, essentially, the distance from the light to the object that is visible from
the light at that point.  That object is illuminated by the light. If an object
is at greater depth than the value stored in the depth buffer, then that object is
in shadow.  The depth buffer is the shadow map.  Now, go back to the point of view of the camera,
and consider a point on some object as it is rendered from the camera's point of view.  Is that
point in shadow or not?  You just have to transform that point from the camera's viewing coordinates
to the light's viewing
coordinates and check the depth of the transformed point.  If that depth is greater than
the corresponding value in the shadow map, then the point is in shadow.  Note that if there
are several lights, each light casts its own shadows, and you need a shadow map for each light.</p>

<p>It is computationally expensive to compute shadow maps and to apply them, and
shadows are disabled by default in <i>three.js</i>.  To get shadows, you need to do
several things.  You need to enable shadow computations in the WebGL renderer by
saying</p>

<pre>renderer.shadowMap.enabled = true;</pre>

<np>Only <classname>DirectionalLights</classname> and
<classname>SpotLights</classname> can cast shadows.  To get
shadows from a light, even after enabling shadows in the renderer, you have to set
the light's <i>castShadow</i> property to <i>true</i>:</np>

<pre>light.castShadow = true;  // This light will cast shadows.</pre>

<np>Furthermore, shadows have to be enabled for each object that
will cast or receive shadows.  "Receiving" a shadow means that shadows will
be visible on that object.  Casting and receiving are enabled separately for
an object.</np>

<pre>object.castShadow = true;     // This object will cast shadows.
object.receiveShadow = true;  // Shadows will show up on this object.</pre>

<p>Even this might not make any shadows show up, and if they do they might
look pretty bad.  The problem is that you usually have to configure the
cameras that are used to make the shadow maps.</p>

<p>Each <classname>DirectionalLight</classname> or
<classname>SpotLight</classname> has its own
shadow camera, which is used to create the shadow
map from the point of view of that light.  (A <classname>DirectionalLight</classname>
has a property named <i>shadow</i> of type <classname>THREE.DirectionalLightShadow</classname>,
which in turn has a property named <i>camera</i> of type <classname>THREE.OrthographicCamera</classname>
that holds the shadow camera.  So, the shadow camera for a directional light <i>dl</i> is
<i>dl.shadow.camera</i>.)   The shadow camera for a directional
light uses an <word>orthographic projection</word>.  An orthographic projection is 
configured by view volume limits
<i>xmin</i>, <i>xmax</i>, <i>ymin</i>, <i>ymax</i>, <i>near</i>, and
<i>far</i> (see <localref href="gl1geom.3.3"/>).   
For a directional light, <i>dl</i>, these limits correspond to
the properties <i>dl.shadow.camera.left</i>, <i>dl.shadow.camera.right</i>, <i>dl.shadow.camera.bottom</i>,
<i>dl.shadow.camera.top</i>, <i>dl.shadow.camera.near</i>,  and <i>dl.shadow.camera.far</i>.
These values are in view coordinates for the shadow camera; that is, they are relative to <i>dl.position</i>.  
It is important to make sure that
all the objects in your scene, or at least those that cast shadows, are within the view volume of
the shadow camera.  Furthermore,
you don't want the limits to be too big: If the scene occupies only a small part
of the camera's view volume, then only a small part of the shadow map contains
useful information&mdash;and then since there is so little information about shadows, your
shadows won't be very accurate.  The default values assume a very large scene.
For a relatively small scene, you might set:</p>

<pre>dl.shadow.camera.left = -20;
dl.shadow.camera.right = 20;
dl.shadow.camera.bottom = -20;
dl.shadow.camera.top = 20;
dl.shadow.camera.near = 1;
dl.shadow.camera.far = 30;</pre>

<p>The shadow camera for a spotlight is of type <classname>THREE.PerspectiveCamera</classname> 
and uses a <word>perspective projection</word>.  (The use of
a camera with a limited view is why you can have shadows from spotlights but not from
point lights.)  For a spotlight <i>sl</i>, the shadow camera is configured by the
properties <i>sl.shadow.camera.near</i>, <i>sl.shadow.camera.far</i>,
and  <i>sl.shadow.camera.fov</i> (where "fov" is the vertical
field of view angle, given in degrees rather than radians).  The default value
for <i>fov</i> is probably OK, except that if you change the spotlight's cutoff angle,
you will want to change the <i>fov</i> to match.  But you should be sure to set appropriate values
for <i>near</i> and <i>far</i>, to include all of your scene and as little extra as is practical.
Again, <i>near</i> and <i>far</i> are distances from <i>sl.position</i>.</p>

<p>To get more accurate shadows, you might want to increase
the size of the shadow map.  The shadow map is a kind of texture image which by default is 512 by 512
pixels.  You can increase the accuracy of the shadows by using a larger shadow map.
To do that for a light, <i>light</i>, set the values of the properties
<i>light.shadow.mapSize.width</i> and <i>light.shadow.mapSize.height</i>.  For example,</p>

<pre>light.shadow.mapSize.width = 1024;
light.shadow.mapSize.height = 1024;</pre>

<np>I'm not sure whether power-of-two values are absolutely required here, but
they are commonly used for textures.</np>

</subsection>



<subsection title="Cubemap Textures and Skyboxes" id="threejs.3.4">

<p>We have created and viewed simple scenes, shown on a solid-colored background.
It would be nice to put our scenes in an "environment" such as the interior of a building,
a nature scene, or a public square.  It's not practical to build representations of
such complex environments out of geometric primitives, but we can get a reasonably
good effect using textures.  The technique that is used in <i>three.js</i> is called a
<newword>skybox</newword>.  A skybox is a large cube &mdash; effectively, infinitely large &mdash;
where a different texture is applied to each face of the cube.  The textures are images
of some environment.  For a viewer inside the cube, the six texture images on the cube fit together to provide
a complete view of the environment in every direction.  The six texture images
together make up what is called a <newword>cubemap texture</newword>.
The images must match up along the edges of the cube to form a seamless view of
the environment.</p>

<p>A cube map of an actual physical environment can be made by taking six pictures
of the environment in six directions: left, right, up, down, forward, and back.  (More realistically,
it is made by taking enough photographs to cover all directions, with overlaps, and then using software to "stitch"
the images together into a complete cube map.)  The six
directions are referred to by their relation to the coordinate axes as:
positive&nbsp;x, negative&nbsp;x, positive&nbsp;y, negative&nbsp;y, positive&nbsp;z, and negative&nbsp;z,
and the images must be listed in that order when you specify the cube map.
Here is an example.  The first picture shows the six images of a cube map laid
out next to each other.  The positive y image is at the top, the negative y image is at the
bottom.  In between are the negative x, positive z, positive x, and negative z images
laid out in a row.  The second picture shows the images used to texture a cube, viewed here from 
the outside.  You
can see how the images match up along the edges of the cube:</p>

<img src="cubemap.png" width="650" height="283" tex="cubemap.eps" texscale="0.6"/>

<np>(This cube map, and others used in this section, are by Emil Persson, who has made a 
large number of cube maps available for download
at <a href="http://www.humus.name/index.php?page=Textures">http://www.humus.name/index.php?page=Textures</a>
under a creative commons license.)</np>

<p>For a skybox, conceptually, a very large cube would be used.  
The camera, lights, and any objects that are to be part
of the scene would be inside the cube. 
It is possible to construct a skybox by hand in just this way.</p>

<p>However, <i>Three.js</i> makes it very easy to use a skybox as the background for a scene.
It has the class <classname>THREE.CubeTexture</classname> to represent 
cube maps, and you can enclose your scene in a skybox simply by assigning
a <classname>CubeTexture</classname> as the value of the property
<i>scene.background</i>.  (The value of that property could also be a normal
<classname>Texture</classname> or a <classname>Color</classname>.)</p>

<p>A <classname>CubeTexture</classname> can be created by a <classname>CubeTextureLoader</classname>,
which can load the six images that make up the cube map.  The loader has
a method named <i>load</i>() that works in the same way as the <i>load</i>()
method of a <classname>TextureLoader</classname> (<localref href="threejs.2.3"/>), 
except that the first parameter
to the method is an array of six strings giving the URLs of the six images
for the cube map.  For example:</p>

<pre>let textureURLs = [  // URLs of the six faces of the cube map 
        "cubemap-textures/park/posx.jpg",   // Note:  The order in which
        "cubemap-textures/park/negx.jpg",   //   the images are listed is
        "cubemap-textures/park/posy.jpg",   //   important!
        "cubemap-textures/park/negy.jpg",  
        "cubemap-textures/park/posz.jpg",   
        "cubemap-textures/park/negz.jpg"
   ];
loader = new THREE.CubeTextureLoader();
cubeTexture = loader.load( textureURLs, onLoad, undefined, onError );</pre>

<np>Here, <i>onLoad</i> is a function that will be called after the
texture has finished loading. The function could, for example,
set <i>scene.background</i> equal to <i>cubeTexture</i> and re-render
the scene with the new background.  The last parameter <i>onError</i>
is a function that will be called if the texture cannot be loaded.
Only the first parameter is required.</np>


<p>The sample program <sourceref href="threejs/skybox.html"/>
shows two WebGL scenes.  The first scene shows a cube with the six
images from a cube map applied as normal textures to the six faces of
a cube.  The second scene uses the same cube map as a skybox.  If you rotate
the view of the second scene, you can look at all parts of the skybox and
see how it forms a seamless environment that completely encloses the scene.
</p>


</subsection>



<subsection title="Reflection and Refraction" id="threejs.3.5">

<p>A reflective surface shouldn't just reflect light&mdash;it should reflect its
environment.  <i>Three.js</i> can use <newword>environment mapping</newword>
to simulate reflection.  (Environment mapping is also called "reflection mapping.")
Environment mapping uses a cube map texture.  Given a
point on a surface, a ray is cast from the camera position to that point,
and then the ray is reflected off the surface.  The point where the reflected
ray hits the cube determines which point from the texture should be mapped to the point on the
surface.  For a simulation of perfect, mirror-like reflection, the surface
point is simply painted with the color from the texture.
Note that the surface does not literally reflect other objects in the scene.
It reflects the contents of the cube map texture.  However,
if the same cube map texture is used on a skybox, and if the skybox is
the only other object in the scene,  then it will look like
the surface is a mirror that perfectly reflects its environment.</p>

<p>This type of reflection is very easy to do in <i>three.js</i>.  You only need to
make a mesh material and set its
<i>envMap</i> property equal to the cubemap texture object.  For example,
if <i>cubeTexture</i> is the texture object obtained using
a <classname>THREE.CubeTextureLoader</classname>, as in the skybox example above, we can make a sphere that
perfectly reflects the texture by saying:</p>

<pre>let geometry = new THREE.SphereGeometry(1,32,16);
let material = new THREE.MeshBasicMaterial( { 
        color: "white",  // Color will be multiplied by the environment map. 
        envMap: cubeTexture  // CubeTexture to be used as an environment map.
    } );
let mirrorSphere = new THREE.Mesh( geometry, material );</pre>

<np>For the effect to look good, you would want to use the
same texture as the <i>scene</i> background.  Note that no lighting would be 
necessary in the scene, since
the sphere uses a <classname>MeshBasicMaterial</classname>.
The colors seen on the sphere come entirely from the environment map and
the basic color of the sphere material.  The environment map color is multiplied
by the basic color.  In this example, the basic <i>color</i> of the
material is white, and the sphere color is exactly equal to the color
from the texture.  With a different base color, the environment map texture would be "tinted"
with that color.  You could even apply a regular texture map to the sphere, to be used in place of
the color, so that the reflection of the skybox would be combined with the texture.</np>

<p>The sample program <sourceref href="threejs/reflection.html"/> demonstrates
environment mapping.  It can show a variety of environment-mapped objects, with
a variety of skybox textures, and it has several options for the base color of the
object.  Here are two images from that program.  The one on the left shows a reflective
arrowhead shape with a white base color.  On the right, the object is a model
of a horse (taken from the <i>three.js</i> download) whose base color is pink:</p>

<img src="threejs-reflection.png" width="650" height="328" tex="threejs-reflection.eps" texscale="0.6"/>

<demo src="c5/reflection-demo.html" width="600" height="525"><np><tex>A very similar program is available as a demo
in the on-line version of this section.</tex>
<web>Here is a demo that is very similar to the sample program.  In the demo, you can choose
to view just the skybox or just the reflective object, and you can see that the object only
seems to be reflecting its actual environment.  Use your mouse to rotate the scene to see
how the reflection changes as the orientation of the object changes.</web></np></demo>

<p><i>Three.js</i> can also do <newword>refraction</newword>.  Refraction
occurs when light passes through a transparent or translucent object.  A ray of light will be
bent as it passes between the inside of the object and the outside.  The amount
of bending depends on the so-called "indices of refraction" of the material outside
and the material inside the object.  More exactly, it depends on the ratio between
the two indices.  Even a perfectly transparent object will be visible because of
the distortion induced by this bending (unless the ratio is 1, meaning that there
is no bending of light at all).</p>

<p>In <i>three.js</i>, refraction is implemented using environment maps.  As with reflection,
a refracting object does not show its actual environment; it refracts the cubemap texture
that is used as the environment map.  For refraction, a special
"mapping" must be used for the environment map texture.  The <i>mapping</i> property 
of a texture tells how that texture will be mapped to a surface.  For a cubemap
texture being used for refraction, it should be set to <i>THREE.CubeRefractionMapping</i>.  
(The default value of this property in a cubemap texture is 
appropriate for reflection rather than refraction.)  Here is an example of
loading a cubemap texture and setting its mapping property for use with refraction:</p>

<pre>cubeTexture = new THREE.CubeTextureLoader().load( textureURLs );
cubeTexture.mapping = THREE.CubeRefractionMapping;</pre>

<np>In addition to this, the <i>refractionRatio</i> property of the material
that is applied to the refracting object should be set.  The value is a number
between 0 and&nbsp;1; the closer to 1, the less bending of light.  The default value
is so close to 1 that the object will be almost invisible. This example uses
a value of 0.6:</np>

<pre>let material = new THREE.MeshBasicMaterial( { 
        color: "white",
        envMap: cubeTexture,
        refractionRatio: 0.6
    } );</pre>

<np>This gives a strong refractive effect.  If you set the material color to
something other than white, you will get something that looks like tinted glass.
Another property that you might set is the <i>reflectivity</i>.  For a refractive
object, this value tells how much light is transmitted through the object rather than reflected
from its surface.
The default value, 1, gives 100% transmission of light; smaller values make objects
look like they are made out of "cloudy" glass that blocks some of the light.</np>

<p>The sample program <sourceref href="threejs/refraction.html"/>
is a copy of <i>reflection.html</i> that has been modified to
do refraction instead of reflection.  The objects look like they are made of glass instead
of mirrors.  The program has a checkbox that makes the glass look cloudy and one
that increases the <i>refractionRatio</i> from 0.6 to&nbsp;0.9.
The following images are
from that program.  A perfectly transmissive arrowhead is shown in the first image, and a cloudy
sphere in the second.  Notice how the sphere shows an inverted image of the objects
behind it:</p>

<img src="threejs-refraction.png" width="650" height="324" tex="threejs-refraction.eps" texscale="0.6"/>

<p>In my reflection and refraction examples, the environment is a skybox, and there is a single
object that reflects or refracts that environment.  But what if a scene includes more than one
object?  The objects won't be in the cubemap texture.  If you use the cubemap texture on
the objects, they won't reflect or refract <b>each other</b>.  There is no complete solution
to this problem in WebGL.  However, you can make an object reflect or refract other objects
by making an environment map that includes those objects.  If the objects are moving, this means
that you have to make a new environment map for every frame.  Recall that an environment map
can be made by taking six pictures of the environment from different directions.  <i>Three.js</i> has a kind of camera that
can do just that, <classname>THREE.CubeCamera</classname>.  I won't go into the
full details, but a CubeCamera can take a
six-fold picture of a scene from a given point of view and make a cubemap texture from
those images.  To use the camera, you have to place it at the location of an object&mdash;and make the
object invisible so it doesn't show up in the pictures.  Snap the picture, and apply it
as an environment map on the object.  For animated scenes, you have to do this in every frame,
and you need to do it for every reflective/refractive object in the scene.  Obviously, this
can get very computationally expensive!  And the result still isn't perfect.  For one thing,
you won't see multiple reflections, where objects reflect back and forth on each other several
times. For that, you need a different kind of rendering from the one used by OpenGL.
We will return to the topic of dynamic cubemaps in <localref href="webgl3d.4.4"/> and
to alternative rendering techniques in <localref href="advanced"/>.</p>


</subsection>





</section>