<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE glossary SYSTEM "graphicstext.dtd">

<glossary>

<gitem term="pixel">A digital image is made up of rows and columns of small rectangles called pixels.
To specify a digital image, a color is assigned to each pixel in the image.</gitem>
<gitem term="grayscale">Refers to a color scheme or image in which each color is a shade of gray (where the
term "shade of gray" here includes black and white).  Typically, 256 shades of gray are used.
Grayscale is also called "monochrome."</gitem>
<gitem term="indexed color">A color scheme in which colors are selected from a limited palette of colors.
For example, if the palette contains 256 colors, then a color can be specified by an eight-bit integer,
giving its position, or index, in the list of colors.</gitem>
<gitem term="frame buffer">A region of memory that contains color data for a digital image.  Most often
refers to the memory containing the image that appears on the computer's screen.</gitem>
<gitem term="raster graphics">Pixel-based graphics in which an image is specified by assigning a color
to each pixel in a grid of pixels.</gitem>
<gitem term="vector graphics">Shape-based graphics in which an image is specified as a list of the shapes or
objects that appear in the image.</gitem>
<gitem term="attribute">A property, such as color, of a graphical object.  An image can be specified
by the geometric shapes that it contains, together with their attributes.</gitem>
<gitem term="display list">A list of graphics primitives and attributes which can be traversed to create all or part 
of an image.  Display lists were used in some early vector-graphics hardware.  They were also available
in traditional OpenGL.</gitem>
<gitem term="painting program">A computer program for creating images using raster-style graphics, where the user creates the image
by controlling the colors of each pixel.</gitem>
<gitem term="drawing program">A computer program for creating images using vector-style graphics, where the user creates the image
by specifying shapes that make up the image and their attributes.</gitem>
<gitem term="lossless data compression">A scheme for reducing the size of a dataset without losing any of the
information in that dataset.  The original data can be recovered exactly from the compressed data.
The image formats GIF and PNG use lossless data compression to reduce the size of the image file.</gitem>
<gitem term="lossy data compression">A scheme for reducing the size of a dataset in which some of the information
in the dataset can be lost.  The data that is recovered from the compressed data can differ from the original data.
The image format JPEG use lossy data compression to reduce the size of the image file.</gitem>
<gitem term="coordinate system">A way of assigning numerical coordinates to geometric points.  In two
dimensions, each point corresponds to a pair of numbers.  In three dimensions, each point corresponds
to a triple of numbers.</gitem>
<gitem term="geometric modeling">Creating a scene by specifying the geometric objects contained
in the scene, together with geometric transforms to be applied to them and attributes that
determine their appearance.</gitem>
<gitem term="hierarchical modeling">Creating complex geometric models in a hierarchical fashion,
starting with geometric primitives, combining them into components that can then be further
combined into more complex components, and so on.</gitem>
<gitem term="geometric primitive">Geometric objects in a graphics system, such as OpenGL, that are
not made up of simpler objects.  Examples in OpenGL include points, lines, and triangles,
but the set of available primitives depends on the graphics system.  (Note that as the term
is used in OpenGL, a single primitive can be made up of many points, line segments, or triangles.)</gitem>
<gitem term="geometric transform">A coordinate transformation; that is, a function that can
be applied to each of the points in a geometric object to produce a new object.  Common
transforms include scaling, rotation, and translation. </gitem>
<gitem term="scaling">A geometric transform that multiplies each coordinate of a point by
a number called the scaling factor.  Scaling increases or decreases the size of an object,
but also moves its points closer to or farther from the origin. Scaling can be uniform&mdash;the same
in every direction&mdash;or non-uniform&mdash;with a different scaling factor in each coordinate
direction.  A negative scaling factor can be used to apply a reflection.</gitem>
<gitem term="rotation">A geometric transform that rotates each point by a specified angle
about some point (in 2D) or axis (in 3D).</gitem>
<gitem term="translation">A geometric transform that adds a given translation amount to
each coordinate of a point.  Translation is used to move objects without changing their
size or orientation.</gitem>
<gitem term="projection">A transformation that maps coordinates in 3D to coordinates in 2D.
Projection is used to convert a three-dimensional scene into a two-dimensional image.</gitem>
<gitem term="viewing">Setting the position and orientation of the viewer in a 3D world, which determine what will
be visible when the 2D image of a 3D world is rendered.</gitem>
<gitem term="lighting">Using light sources in a 3D scene, so that the appearance of objects in
the scene can be computed based on the interaction of light with the objects' material properties.</gitem>
<gitem term="material">The properties of an object that determine how that object interacts
with light in the environment.  Material properties in OpenGL include, for example, diffuse
color, specular color, and shininess.</gitem>
<gitem term="texture">Variation in some property from point-to-point on an object.  The most common type
is image texture.  When an image texture is applied to a surface, the surface color varies from
point to point.</gitem>
<gitem term="image texture">An image that is applied to a surface as a texture, so that it looks
at if the image is "painted" onto the surface.</gitem>
<gitem term="rasterization">The process of creating a raster image, that is one made of pixels,
from other data that specifies the content of the image.  For example, a vector graphics image
must be rasterized in order to be displayed on a computer screen.</gitem>
<gitem term="rendering">The process of producing a 2D image from a 3D scene description.</gitem>
<gitem term="animation">A sequence of images that, when displayed quickly one after the other,
will produce the impression of continuous motion or change.  The term animation also refers
to the process of creating such image sequences.</gitem>
<gitem term="CPU">The Central Processing Unit in a computer, the component that actually
executes programs.  The CPU reads machine language instructions from the computer's memory
and carries them out.</gitem>
<gitem term="GPU">Graphics Processing Unit, a computer hardware component that performs graphical
computations that create and manipulate images.  Operations such as drawing a line on the screen 
or rendering a 3D image are done in the GPU, which is optimized to perform such operations very
quickly.</gitem>
<gitem term="shader">A program to be executed at some stage of the rendering pipeline.  OpenGL
shaders are written in the GLSL programming languages.  For WebGL, only vertex shaders
and fragment shaders are supported.  WebGPU also has compute shaders, which are used
in compute pipelines.</gitem>
<gitem term="vertex shader">A shader program that will be executed once for each vertex in a primitive.
A vertex shader must compute the vertex coordinates in the clip coordinate system.
It can also compute other properties, such as color.</gitem>
<gitem term="fragment shader">A shader program that will be executed once for
each pixel in a primitive.  A fragment shader must compute a color for the pixel,
or discard it.  Fragment shaders are also called pixel shaders.</gitem>
<gitem term="GLSL">OpenGL Shader Language, the programming language that is used to write
shader programs for use with OpenGL.</gitem>
<gitem term="vertex">One of the points that define a geometric primitive, such as the
two endpoints of a line segment or the three vertices of a triangle.  (The plural is "vertices.")
A vertex can be specified in a coordinate system by giving its x and y coordinates in
2D graphics, or its x, y, and z coordinates in 3D graphics.</gitem>

<gitem term="antialiasing">A technique used to reduce the jagged or "staircase" appearance
of diagonal lines, text, and other shapes that are drawn using pixels.  When a pixel is only partly
covered by a geometric shape, then the color of the pixel is a blend of the color of the shape and
the color of the background, with the degree of blending depending on the fraction of the
pixel that is covered by the geometric shape.</gitem>
<gitem term="color model">A way of specifying colors numerically.  Each color that can represented
in a color model is assigned one or more numerical component values.  An example is the RGB color
model, where a color is specified by three numbers giving the red, green, and blue components
of the color.</gitem>
<gitem term="aspect ratio">The ratio of the width, w, of a rectangle to the height, h, of the rectangle, 
expressed either as a ratio w:h or as a fraction w/h.</gitem>
<gitem term="color gamut">The color gamut of a display device, such as a printer or computer screen, 
is the set of colors can be displayed by the device. </gitem>
<gitem term="RGB color">A color specified by three numbers giving the amount of red, green, and blue
in the color.</gitem>
<gitem term="RGBA color">An RGB color&mdash;specified by red, green, and blue component values&mdash;together
with an alpha component.  The alpha component is most often take to specify the degree of transparency
of the color, with a maximal alpha value giving a fully opaque color.</gitem>
<gitem term="HSV color">A color specified by three numbers giving the hue, saturation, and value
of the component.  The hue represents the basic color.
The saturation is the purity of the color, with a saturation value of zero producing a shade of gray, 
that is a color with no actual hue at all.  The value represents the brightness of the color,
with a value of zero giving black.  (Value is also called brightness, and the name HSB is sometimes
used instead of HSV.)</gitem>
<gitem term="HSL color">A color specified by three numbers giving the hue, saturation, and lightness
of the component.  The HSL color model is similar to the HSV color model.  The main difference is that
in HSL, pure spectral colors occur when L=0.5, while in HSV, they occur when V=1.</gitem>
<gitem term="color component">One of the numbers used in a color model to specify a color.
For example, in the RGB color model, a color is specified by three color components representing
the amounts of red, green, and blue in the color.</gitem>
<gitem term="alpha color component">An extra component (that is, one of the numbers that are used
to specify a color) in a color model that is not part of the actual color specification.  The
alpha component is extra information.  It is most often used to specify the degree of
transparency of a color.</gitem>
<gitem term="alpha blending">Using the alpha component of a color to blend the color with
a background color, when the color is drawn over the background color.  That is, the new color 
of a pixel is obtained by blending the drawing color with the current color, with the degree of 
blending depending on the alpha component of the drawing color.  Alpha blending is most
commonly used to simulate transparency.</gitem>

<gitem term="Bresenham's line algorithm">A specific algorithm for deciding which pixels to color
to represent a geometric line segment, using only integer arithmetic.  The algorithm can
be implemented very efficiently in computer hardware</gitem>
<gitem term="HTML canvas">A canvas element on a web page. The canvas appears as a rectangular area on the page.
The JavaScript programming language can use a canvas element as a drawing surface.  
HTML is a language for specifying the content of a web page.  JavaScript is the
programming language for web pages.  The canvas element supports a 2D graphics API.
In many browsers, it also supports the 3D graphics API, WebGL.</gitem>
<gitem term="stroking a shape">Drawing the outline of a shape, as if a pen is dragged along the
boundary of the shape.  For a shape with no interior, such as a line segment, stroking the
shape simply means dragging the pen along the shape.</gitem>
<gitem term="filling a shape">Drawing the interior of a shape, by coloring the pixels that
lie inside the shape.  Filling does not apply to shapes, such as lines, that have no
interior.</gitem>
<gitem term="winding number">The winding number of a path about a point that does not lie on the path
is the number of times that the path winds around the point, counting each 360-degree rotation in the positive direction
about the point as one and each 360-degree turn in the negative direction as minus one.  To compute the
winding number, draw a ray extending from the point to infinity.  Each crossing of the ray by the
path counts as 1 if it crosses the ray going in the positive direction and as negative 1 if it 
crosses in the negative direction.</gitem>
<gitem term="pattern fill">Using copies of an image to fill the interior of a two-dimensional shape. The image
can be repeated horizontally and vertically as necessary to cover the shape.</gitem>
<gitem term="gradient">A pattern of color produced by assigning colors to certain reference points and
computing color for other points by interpolating or extrapolating colors from the reference points.
The effect is a color progression along line segments between reference points.  Different rules
for extending the colors beyond those lines produce different types of gradient, such as
linear gradients and radial gradients.</gitem>
<gitem term="radial gradient">A color gradient pattern in which there are concentric circles, or sometimes
ellipses, of constant color, with a color variation along the radius of the circles.</gitem>
<gitem term="linear gradient">A color gradient pattern in which there is a color variation along
a certain line, with constant color along lines perpendicular to that line.</gitem>
<gitem term="interpolation">Given values for some quantity at certain reference points, computing
a value for that quantity at other points by some kind of averaging applied to the values at
the reference points.</gitem>
<gitem term="convex">A convex geometric shape has the property that whenever two points are
contained in the shape, then the line segment between those two points is entirely contained
in the shape.</gitem>
<gitem term="Bezier curve">A smooth curve between two points defined by parametric
polynomial equations.  A cubic Bezier curve segment is defined by its two endpoints P1 and P2 and
by two control points C1 and C2.  The tangent to the curve (its direction and speed) at P1 is
given by the line from P1 to C1.  The tangent vector to the curve at P2 is given by 
the line from C2 to P2.  A quadratic Bezier curve is defined by its two endpoints and
a single control point C.  The tangent at each endpoint is the line between that endpoint
and&nbsp;C.</gitem>
<gitem term="control point">A point that does not lie on the curve but that is used to help control
the shape of the curve.  For example, a control point for a Bezier curve segment is used to specify the
tangent vector (direction and speed) of the curve at an endpoint.</gitem>
<gitem term="polygon">A multi-sided shape lying in a plane and 
specified by a list of points, called its vertices, and made up
of the line segments from each point in the list to the next point in the list, plus a line
segment from the last point in the list to the first point.  All the points are required to
lie in the same plane.  Sometimes the term "polygon" includes the interior of the shape as well
as its boundary.</gitem>
<gitem term="regular polygon">A polygon in which all the sides have the same length and all the
angles between consecutive sides are equal.  Usually the term is restricted to simple polygons,
which have sides that do not intersect except at their endpoints.</gitem>
<gitem term="API">Application Programming Interface.  A collection of related classes, functions,
constants, etc., for performing some task.  An API is an "interface" in the sense that it
can be used without understanding how its functionality is actually implemented.</gitem>

<gitem term="view window">As used in this book, the window, or view window, for 2D graphics
is the rectangle in the xy-plane that contains the portion of the plane that will be displayed
in the image.  (The corresponding term in 3D graphics is "view volume.")</gitem>
<gitem term="viewport">The rectangular area in which the image for 2D or 3D graphics is 
displayed.  The coordinates on the viewport are pixel coordinates, more properly called 
device coordinates since they are actual physical coordinates on the device where the 
image is being displayed.</gitem>
<gitem term="world coordinates">The coordinate system in which a scene is defined.  The image 
that is produced of the scene will show the contents of the world coordinate system that
lie within some view volume (for 3D) or view window (for 2D).  Objects are defined
in their own object coordinate system. Modeling transformations are then applied to place 
objects into the scene; that is, they transform object coordinates to world coordinates.</gitem>
<gitem term="object coordinates">The coordinate system in which the coordinates for points in an 
object are originally specified, before they are transformed by any modeling or other transform that
will be applied to the object.</gitem>
<gitem term="modeling transformation">A transformation that is applied to an object to
map that object into the world coordinate system or into the object coordinate system for
a more complex, hierarchical object.</gitem>
<gitem term="affine transform">A transform that preserves parallel lines.
That is, when the transform is applied to a pair of lines that are parallel, then the
resulting transformed lines are also parallel.  An affine transform, T, has the property
that the transform of the line segment between a point (x1,y1) and a point (x2,y2) is
the line between the points T(x1,y1) and T(x2,y2).  Effectively, the transform of a line
segment can be computed just by transforming its two endpoints.  This makes affine
transforms very efficient for computer graphics.  Any affine transform can be represented
as a composition of rotations, translations, and scalings.</gitem>
<gitem term="uniform scaling">A scaling transformation in which the scaling factors in all
directions are the same.  Uniform scaling changes the size of an object without distorting
its shape.</gitem>
<gitem term="Euclidean transform">A transform that preserves distances and angles.  A Euclidean
transform represents a "rigid motion."  That is, the transform of an object is an exact
copy of the object, with the same size and shape.  Any Euclidean transform can be 
represented as a composition of rotations and translations.</gitem>
<gitem term="shear transform">A shear transformation in 2D leaves some line, L, fixed, and lines perpendicular
to L are "tilted" relative to L by the same angle.  Another description is that a line parallel to L is
mapped to itself, but is moved by an amount proportional to its distance from L.  In 3D, a shear
transformation leaves some plane, P, fixed, and it maps a plane parallel to P to itself, but
moved by an amount proportional to its distance from P.</gitem>

<gitem term="identity transform">A transform that has no effect on its argument.  For example,
the identity transform in 2D is given by the formula I(x,y) = (x,y).  The identity transform I
has the property that if T is any transform, then I followed by T is the same as T, and T followed
by I is the same as T.</gitem>
<gitem term="vector">An element of a vector space.  Elements of a vector space can
be added and can be multiplied by constants. For computer graphics, a vector is
just a list or array containing two, three, or four numbers.  Vectors in that sense are often
used to represent points in 2D, 3D, or 4D space.  Properly, however, a vector represents a
quantity that has a length and a direction; a vector used in this way can be visualized
as an arrow.</gitem>
<gitem term="matrix">A rectangular array of numbers.  A matrix can be represented as a
two-dimensional array, with numbers arranged in rows and columns.   An N-by-N matrix
represents a linear transformation from N-dimensional space to itself.</gitem>
<gitem term="linear algebra">The field of mathematics that studies vector spaces and
linear transformations between them.  Linear algebra is part of the essential mathematical foundation
of computer graphics.</gitem>
<gitem term="linear transformation">A function from one vector space to another that preserves
vector addition and multiplication by constants.  Linear transformations can be represented
by matrices.  In computer graphics, they are used to implement geometric operations such
as rotation and translation.</gitem>
<gitem term="JavaScript">A programming language for web pages.  JavaScript code on a web
page is executed by a web browser that displays the page, and it can interact with the contents
of the web page and with the user.  There are JavaScript APIs for 2D and for 3D graphics</gitem>
<gitem term="stack">A data structure with the operations push() and pop().  Pushing an item
onto a stack just adds that item to the stack.  Popping from the stack will remove and
return the item that was most recently pushed onto the stack.</gitem>
<gitem term="scene graph">A data structure that represents the objects in a scene, together
with attributes of the objects and the modeling transformations that are applied to the
objects.  An image of the scene is created by traversing the scene graph data structure.
A scene graph might exist only conceptually, or it might be an actual data structure
in a program.</gitem>
<gitem term="WebGL">A 3D graphics API for use on web pages.  WebGL programs are written
in the JavaScript programming language and display their images in HTML canvas
elements.  WebGL is based on OpenGL ES, the version of OpenGL for embedded systems, with
a few changes to adapt it to the JavaScript language and the Web environment.</gitem>
<gitem term="abstract class">In object-oriented programming, a class that is meant to be used
only as a basis for subclasses. Objects can be created from the subclasses, but not from
the abstract class itself.  The purpose of an abstract class is to define the properties
and behaviors that all of its subclasses have in common.</gitem>
<gitem term="inverse transform">Given a transform T, the inverse transform of T is a transform
that reverses the operation of T.  For example, for a 2D transform, for R to be the inverse of T
means that R(T(x,y)) = (x,y).  Scaling by 0.5 is the inverse of scaling by 2.  Translation by
(-3,5) is the inverse of translation by (3,-5).  Not every transform has an inverse.  For example,
scaling by a factor of zero has no inverse.</gitem>
<gitem term="off-screen canvas">My term for a segment of the computer's memory that can be
used as a drawing surface, for drawing images that are not visible on the screen.  Some method
should exist for copying the image from an off-screen canvas onto the screen.  In Java, for example, an
off-screen canvas can be implemented as an object of type BufferedImage.</gitem>
<gitem term="typed array">In JavaScript, an array type that is limited to holding numerical values
of a single type.  For example, the type Float32Array represents arrays that can hold 32-bit floating
point values, and Uint8Array arrays can hold only 8-bit integer values.  Such arrays are more efficient
than general JavaScript arrays for numerical calculations.  The were introduced into JavaScript
along with HTML canvas graphics and WebGL.</gitem>

<gitem term="HTML">HyperText Markup Language.   A language that is used for specifying
the content of web pages.  An HTML document is made  up of text, along with "elements" for adding
other content, such as images, and for defining the structure of the document.  Because of
nesting of elements, the document can be represented by a tree-like data structure.</gitem>
<gitem term="CSS">Cascading Style Sheets.  A language that is used for specifying the style,
or presentation, of the content of web pages.  CSS can control things like colors, backgrounds,
fonts, shadows, borders, and the size and position of elements of the page.</gitem>
<gitem term="DOM">Document Object Model.  A specification for representing a web page (and other kinds of
structured document) as a tree-like data structure.  Can also refer to the data structure itself,
as in "the DOM for this web page."  A web page can be modified dynamically by manipulating its
DOM, using the JavaScript programming language.</gitem>
<gitem term="XML">eXtensible Markup Language.  Not a single language as such, but a class of languages
that follow certain syntax rules.  For example, SVG is an XML language because it follows those
rules, but it also has further restrictions on its syntax that make it appropriate for specifying
2D graphics.  XML documents, like HTML documents, have a tree-like structure defined by "elements."
However, HTML is not an XML language since it does not follow all the syntax rules.  XHTML is an
alternative language for web pages that is similar to HTML but follows XML syntax rules.</gitem>
<gitem term="SVG">Scalable Vector Graphics.  An XML language for specifying 2D vector graphics.
SVG is a scene description language. It is designed to integrate into web pages.</gitem>
<gitem term="scene description language">A language that can be used to specify graphics images
by stating what's in the image.  That is, the scene is created "declaratively," by stating what
it contains, as opposed to being created "procedurally," by a program.  A document written in
a scene description language can be used to generate a scene graph for the scene.</gitem>
<gitem term="keyframe animation">An animation technique in which the value of some quantity
is given explicitly only at certain times during the animation.  The times when the quantity
is specified are called keyframes.  Between keyframes, the value of the quantity is obtained
by interpolating between the values specified for the keyframes.</gitem>

<gitem term="unsigned byte">A data type representing 8-bit non-negative integer values, taking
values in the range from 0 to 255.</gitem>
<gitem term="color buffer">In OpenGL, the region of memory that holds the color data for the
image.  It acts as the drawing surface where images are rendered.</gitem>
<gitem term="hidden surface problem">The problem in 3D graphics of deciding which object is
visible at each pixel in an image.  When one object is behind another object from the point
of view of the viewer, only the front object should appear in the image. A rendering
algorithm for 3D graphics must satisfy this constraint.  Algorithms that solve the hidden
surface problem include the painter's algorithm and the depth test algorithm.</gitem>
<gitem term="depth test">A solution to the hidden surface problem that involves keeping
track of the depth, or distance from the viewer, of the object currently visible at each
pixel in the image.  When a new object is drawn at a pixel, the depth of the new object
is compared to the depth of the current object to decide which one is closer to the viewer.
The advantage of the depth test is that objects can be rendered in any order.  A disadvantage
is that only a limited range of depths can be represented in the image.</gitem>
<gitem term="depth buffer">A region of memory that stores the information needed for the depth test
in 3D graphics, that is, a depth value for each pixel in the image.  Also called the "z-buffer."</gitem>
<gitem term="painter's algorithm">A solution to the hidden surface algorithm that involves
drawing the objects in a scene in order from back to front, that is, in decreasing order of 
distance from the viewer.  A disadvantage is that the order is usually not well-defined
unless some objects are decomposed into smaller sub-objects.  Another issue is that the
order of drawing has to change when objects move or when the point of view changes.</gitem>
<gitem term="OpenGL">A family of computer graphics APIs that is implemented in many graphics
hardware devices.  There are several versions of the API, and there are implementations,
or "bindings" for several different programming languages.  Versions of OpenGL for embedded
systems such as mobile phones are known as OpenGL ES.  WebGL is a version for use on 
Web pages.  OpenGL can be used for 2D as well as for 3D graphics, but it is most commonly
associated with 3D.</gitem>
<gitem term="JOGL">A Java implementation of OpenGL.  JOGL is very complicated, since it 
attempts to support all versions of OpenGL in one programming system.  JOGL integrates
seamlessly with Java's Swing and AWT graphics.</gitem>
<gitem term="GLUT">The OpenGL Utility Toolkit.  A platform-independent library for writing
OpenGL applications.  OpenGL does not include support for windows or events.  GLUT adds
such support.  It also has functions for drawing 3D shapes such as spheres and polyhedra
(not to mention a teapot).  GLUT is written in the C programming language and is used
with the C API for OpenGL.  However, many GLUT functions are also available in JOGL,
the Java API for OpenGL.  A newer, and somewhat improved, version of the toolkit named
"FreeGLUT" is commonly used in place of the original version.</gitem>
<gitem term="GLU">The OpenGL Utility library.  Defines several functions for use with older
versions of OpenGL, including gluPerspective and gluLookAt.  Not to be confused with GLUT.
GLU is a standard part of OpenGL.</gitem>

<gitem term="projection transformation">In 3D graphics, a transformation that maps
a scene in 3D space onto a 2D image.  In OpenGL 1.1, the projection maps the view
volume (that is, the region in 3D space that is visible in the image) 
to clip coordinates, in which the values of x, y, and z range from -1 to 1.
The x- and y-coordinates are then mapped to the image, while the z coordinate provides
depth information.</gitem>
<gitem term="view volume">In OpenGL 1.1, the region is 3D space that is visible in
the rendered image.  For orthographic projections, the view volume is a rectangular solid.
For perspective projection, the view volume is a frustum (truncated pyramid).</gitem>
<gitem term="viewing transformation">The transformation in 3D graphics that maps world
coordinates to eye coordinates.  The viewing transform establishes the position, orientation,
and scale of the viewer in the world.</gitem>
<gitem term="modelview transformation">In OpenGL 1.1, a transform that combines the
modeling transform with the viewing transform.  That is, it is the composition of
the transformation from object coordinates to world coordinates and the transformation
from world coordinates to eye coordinates.  Because of the equivalence between
modeling and viewing transformations, world coordinates are not really meaningful for
OpenGL, and only the combined transformation is tracked.</gitem>
<gitem term="viewport transformation">In OpenGL 1.1, the final transformation from
clip coordinates to device coordinates.  The viewport transformation maps the
clipping cube (the cube in 3D given by x, y, and z coordinates in the range from -1 to 1)
to the viewport (the rectangle in the drawing surface where the image is rendered).</gitem>
<gitem term="clip coordinates">The default coordinate system in OpenGL.  The projection transform
maps the 3D scene to clip coordinates.  The rendered image will show the contents of the
cube in the clip coordinate system that contains x, y, and z values in the range from -1 to 1; anything
outside that range is "clipped" away.</gitem>
<gitem term="eye coordinates">The coordinate system on 3D space defined by the viewer.
In eye coordinates in OpenGL 1.1, the viewer is located at the origin, looking in the
direction of the negative z-axis, with the positive y-axis pointing upwards, and the
positive x-axis pointing to the right. The modelview transformation maps objects into
the eye coordinate system, and the projection transform maps eye coordinates to clip coordinates.</gitem>
<gitem term="device coordinates">The coordinate system used on a display device or rendered image,
often using pixels as the unit of measure.</gitem>
<gitem term="right-handed coordinate system">A coordinate system on 3D space in which the
x, y, and z-axes satisfy this property:  If you point the thumb of your right hand in
the direction of the positive z-axis, then your fingers will curl from the positive x-axis
towards the positive y-axis.</gitem>
<gitem term="right-hand rule">A rule that is used to determine the positive direction of rotation 
about an axis in 3D space: If you point the thumb of your right hand in the direction of the
axis, then your fingers will curl in the direction of positive angles of rotation.  Note that
this assumes that the axis has a direction; in OpenGL, an axis of rotation is determined
by the point (0,0,0) and another point (x,y,z), and the direction of the axis is from
(0,0,0) towards (x,y,z).</gitem>
<gitem term="axis of rotation">Rotation in 3D space is rotation about a line, which is called
the axis of rotation.  The axis of rotation remains fixed, while everything else moves
in circles around the axis.</gitem>

<gitem term="perspective projection">A projection from 3D to 2D that projects objects along
lines radiating out from a viewpoint.  A perspective projection attempts to simulate 
realistic viewing.  A perspective projection preserves perspective;
that is, objects that are farther from the viewpoint are smaller in the projection.
In OpenGL 1.1, the view volume for a perspective projection is a frustum, or truncated pyramid.</gitem>
<gitem term="orthographic projection">A projection from 3D to 2D that simply discards the
z-coordinate.  It projects objects along lines that are orthogonal (perpendicular) to the
xy-plane.  In OpenGL 1.1, the view volume for an orthographic projection is a
rectangular solid.</gitem>
<gitem term="matrix mode">In OpenGL 1.1, a state variable that determines which one of several
transformation matrices will be affected by functions such as glRotatef and glFrustum.  The matrix
mode is set with the function glMatrixMode.  Possible values include GL_MODELVIEW, GL_PROJECTION,
and GL_TEXTURE.</gitem>
<gitem term="camera">In 3D computer graphics, an object that combines the projection and
viewing transforms into an abstraction that imitates a physical camera or eye.</gitem>
<gitem term="frustum">A truncated pyramid; that is, a pyramid from which the top has
been cut off.  In OpenGL 1.1, the view volume for a perspective projection is a frustum.</gitem>
<gitem term="quad">A quadrilateral, that is a four-sided figure in the plane.  OpenGL 1.1 has
the primitives GL_QUADS and GL_QUAD_STRIP for drawing quads, but it assumes without checking
that the vertices that are provided are in fact planar and define quadrilaterals that are convex.</gitem>
<gitem term="indexed face set"> (IFS). A data structure that represents a polyhedron or polygonal
mesh.  The data structure includes a numbered list of vertices and a list of faces.  A face
is specified by listing the indices of the vertices of the face; that is, a face is given as 
a list of numbers where each number is an index into the list of vertices.</gitem>
<gitem term="polyhedron">A closed 3D figure whose faces, or sides, are polygons.  Usually, it is
assumed that the faces of a polyhedron do not intersect, except along their edges.</gitem>
<gitem term="polygonal mesh"> A collection of polygons, where the polygons can be joined together
along their edges.  A polygonal mesh can represent a polyhedron, or can
be used as an approximation for a curved surface.  A polygonal mesh can be represented as
an indexed face set.</gitem>

<gitem term="vertex array">In OpenGL, an array that is used to store coordinates or other
attribute values for vertices, to be used with the functions glDrawArrays and glDrawElements.
A vertex array exists on the "client side" of OpenGL, and it must be transmitted to the
GPU to be used.  In Java's JOGL API for OpenGL, nio buffers are used instead of arrays.</gitem>
<gitem term="VBO">Vertex Buffer Object.  A block of memory that can hold the
coordinates or other attributes for a set of vertices.  A VBO can be stored on a GPU.
VBOs make it possible to send
such data to the GPU once and then reuse it several times.  In OpenGL, VBOs are
used with the functions glDrawArrays and glDrawElements.</gitem>
<gitem term="nio buffer">A Java object belonging to the class java.nio.Buffer or one of its
subclasses.  Nio buffers are similar to arrays, but they are optimized for input/output operations.
Nio buffers are used instead of arrays for certain purposes in Java's JOGL API for OpenGL.</gitem>

<gitem term="length of a vector">A vector is defined by its length and its direction, so length
is a fundamental property.  When a vector is represented as an arrow, its length is just the length
of that arrow.  For a 2D vector given by coordinates (x,y), the length is the square root of
x*x+y*y.  For a 3D vector given as (x,y,z), the length is the square root of x*x+y*y+z*z.</gitem>
<gitem term="norm of a vector">Another term for the length of the vector.  For a 3D vector given as (x,y,z), 
the norm is the square root of x*x+y*y+z*z.</gitem>
<gitem term="dot product">The dot product of two vectors is the sum of the products of corresponding
coordinates.  For 3D vectors v=(x,y,z) and w=(a,b,c), the dot product of v and w is
x*a+y*b+z*c.  The dot product is equal to the cosine of the angle between the vectors,
divided by the product of their lengths.</gitem>
<gitem term="scalar product">The product of a number and a vector.
The scalar product of a number s and vector v is the vector obtained by multiplying
each coordinate of v by s.  In 3D, if s is a number and
v=(x,y,z), then the scalar product of s times v is the vector (sx,sy,sz).</gitem>
<gitem term="cross product">A vector product of two 3D vectors.  The cross product of
v and w is a vector that is perpendicular to both v and w and whose length is equal to
the absolute value of the sine of the angle between v and w.  If v=(x,y,z) and
w=(a,b,c), then their cross product is the vector (yc-zb,za-xc,xb-ya).</gitem>
<gitem term="unit vector">A vector of length one.</gitem>
<gitem term="normalized vector">The result of dividing a non-zero vector by its length, giving
a unit vector, that is, a vector of length one.  (Note that "normalized vector" and
"normal vector" are, confusingly, unrelated terms!)</gitem>
<gitem term="normal vector">A normal vector to a surface at a point on that 
surface is a vector that is perpendicular to the surface at that point.
Normal vectors to curves are defined similarly.  Normal vectors are important
for lighting calculations.</gitem>
<gitem term="unit normal">A normal vector of length one; that is, a unit vector that is
perpendicular to a curve or surface at a given point on the curve or surface.</gitem>
<gitem term="identity matrix">The n-by-n identity matrix is an n-by-n matrix which has
ones on the diagonal and zeros elsewhere.  Multiplication of any matrix B by the identity
matrix, in either order, leaves B unchanged.  Multiplication of an n-dimensional vector
by the n-by-n identity matrix leaves the vector unchanged; that is, the identity matrix
is the matrix for the identity transformation.</gitem>
<gitem term="homogeneous coordinates">A way of representing n-dimensional vectors as
(n+1)-dimensional vectors where two (n+1) vectors represent the same n-dimensional vector
if they differ by a scalar multiple.  In 3D, for example, if w is not zero, then the
homogeneous coordinates (x,y,z,w) are equivalent to homogeneous coordinates 
(x/w,y/w,z/w,1), since they differ by
multiplication by the scalar w.  Both sets of coordinates represent the 3D vector (x/w,y/w,z/w)</gitem>

<gitem term="double buffering">A graphics technique in which an image is drawn off-screen, in a region
of memory called an off-screen buffer or "back buffer."  When the image is drawn, it can be copied to
the buffer that represents the contents of the screen, which is also known as the "front buffer."
In true double buffering, the image doesn't have to be copied; instead, the buffers can be
"swapped" so that the back buffer becomes the front buffer, and the front buffer becomes the
back buffer.</gitem>
<gitem term="single buffering">As opposed to double buffering, a graphics technique in which
the image is drawn directly to the screen (that is, to the buffer that serves as the source
for the screen image).  The disadvantage of single buffering is that, for a complex image, 
the user can observe the process of drawing the image.</gitem>
<gitem term="wireframe">A style of drawing a polyhedron or polygonal mesh in which only the
edges are drawn, resulting in an image made up of line segments.</gitem>
<gitem term="regular polyhedron">A polyhedron in which each face is a regular polygon, and all the
faces and angles are identical.  There are only five regular polyhedra: the tetrahedron with 4 triangular
faces, the cube with 6 square faces, the octahedron with 8 triangular faces, the dodecahedron with
12 pentagonal faces, and the icosahedron, with 20 triangular faces.</gitem>
<gitem term="torus">A 3D geometric object having the shape of a doughnut (or bagel).</gitem>
<gitem term="texture coordinates">Refers to the 2D coordinate system on a texture image, or to
similar coordinate systems for 1D and 3D textures.  Texture coordinates typically range from 0 to 1
both vertically and horizontally, with (0,0) at the lower left corner of the image.  The
term also refers to coordinates that are given for a surface and that are used to specify
how a texture image should be mapped to the surface.</gitem>

<gitem term="real-time graphics">The type of computer graphics that is needed for computer
animation or other applications where the images must be rendered quickly, at the time
when they are viewed.  For computer animation, real-time graphics generally requires the
ability to render the scene sixty times per second.</gitem>
<gitem term="specular reflection">Mirror-like reflection of light rays from a surface.  A ray
of light is reflected as a ray in the direction that makes the angle of reflection equal
to the angle of incidence.  A specular reflection can only be seen by a viewer whose
position lies on the path of the reflected ray.</gitem>
<gitem term="specular highlight">Illumination of a surface produced by specular reflection.
A specular highlight is seen at points on the surface where the angle from the surface to
the viewer is approximately equal to the angle from the surface to a light source.</gitem>
<gitem term="diffuse reflection">Reflection of incident light in all directions from a surface,
so that diffuse illumination of a surface is visible to all viewers, independent of the
viewer's position.</gitem>
<gitem term="ambient light">Directionless light that exists in an environment but does not
seem to come from a particular source in the environment.  An approximation for light
that has been reflected so many times that its original source can't be identified.
Ambient light illuminates all objects in a scene equally.</gitem>
<gitem term="ambient color">A material property that represents the proportion of
ambient light in the environment that is reflected by a surface.</gitem>
<gitem term="diffuse color">A material property that represents the proportion of
incident light that is reflected diffusely from a surface.</gitem>
<gitem term="specular color">A material property that represents the proportion of
incident light that is reflected specularly by a surface.</gitem>
<gitem term="emission color">A material property that represents color that is intrinsic
to a surface, rather than coming from light from other sources that is reflected
by the surface.  Emission color can make the object look like it is glowing, but
it does not illuminate other objects.  Emission color is often called "emissive color."</gitem>
<gitem term="shininess">A material property that determines the size and sharpness
of specular highlights.  Also called the "specular exponent" because of the way it is
used in lighting calculations.  In OpenGL, shininess is a number in the range 0 to 128.</gitem>
<gitem term="specular exponent">A material property that determines the size and sharpness
of specular highlights.  Called "shininess" in OpenGL.</gitem>
<gitem term="reflectivity">The proportion or fraction of incident light that is reflected
by an object.  An object can have different reflectivities at different wavelengths.
The color of an object is determined by its reflectivities at all wavelengths.</gitem>
<gitem term="intensity of a light source">A light source emits light at various wavelengths.
The intensity of a light at a given wavelength is the amount of energy in the light
at that wavelength.  The total intensity of the light is its total energy at all wavelengths.
The color of a light is determined by its intensities at all wavelengths.</gitem>
<gitem term="point light">A light source whose light rays emanate from a single point.  Also
called a "lamp," since a lamp approximates a point source of light. Also called a positional
light.</gitem>
<gitem term="directional light">A light source whose light rays are parallel, all arriving from
the same direction.  Can be considered to be a light source at an effectively infinite distance.
Also called a "sun," since the Sun is an example of a directional light source.</gitem>
<gitem term="front face">One of the two sides of a polygon in 3D.
A polygon has two sides. One is taken to be the front face, and the other is the back face.  In OpenGL, the
difference is determined by the order in which the vertices of the polygon are
enumerated.  The default is that, seen from the front, the vertices are enumerated
in counterclockwise order around the polygon.</gitem>
<gitem term="back face">One of the two sides of a polygon in 3D.
A polygon has two sides. One is taken to be the front face, and the other is the back face.  In OpenGL, the
difference is determined by the order in which the vertices of the polygon are
enumerated.  The default is that, seen from the back, the vertices are enumerated
in clockwise order around the polygon.</gitem>

<gitem term="two-sided lighting">An option in OpenGL that allows the back face of a polygon to
have different material properties from the front face.  Also, when this option is on, the
normal vector that is used in lighting calculations for the back face is taken to be the
negative of the vector for the front face.  (The negative of a vector points in the opposite
direction.)</gitem>
<gitem term="global ambient intensity">In OpenGL, ambient light that is present in the environment
independent of any light source.  Total ambient light is the sum of the global ambient light plus
the ambient light intensity of each enabled light source.</gitem>
<gitem term="lighting equation">The equation that is used in OpenGL to compute the visible color of
a point on a surface from the material properties of the surface, the normal vector for that
point, the direction to the viewer, the ambient light level, and the direction and intensity
of light sources.</gitem>

<gitem term="texture target">In OpenGL, one of several kinds of texture, such as 2D image
texture, 1D texture, and cube map texture.  A texture target is specified by a constant
such as GL_TEXTURE_2D or GL_TEXTURE_CUBE_MAP_POSITIVE_X.  The texture target is a parameter to
many OpenGL functions that work with textures.</gitem>
<gitem term="minification filter">An operation that is used when applying a texture to an object,
when the texture has to be shrunk to fit the object.  For an image texture, a minification filter
is applied to compute the color of a pixel when that pixel covers several pixels in the image.</gitem>
<gitem term="magnification filter">An operation that is used when applying a texture to an object,
when the texture has to be stretched to fit the object.  For an image texture, a magnification filter
is applied to compute the color of a pixel when that pixel covers just a fraction of a pixel in the image.</gitem>
<gitem term="mipmap">One of a series of reduced-size copies of a texture image, of decreasing width and height.
Starting from the original image, each mipmap is obtained by dividing the width and height of
the previous image by two (unless it is already 1).  The final mipmap is a single pixel.  Mipmaps
are used for more efficient mapping of the texture image to a surface, when the image has to be
shrunk to fit the surface.</gitem>
<gitem term="power-of-two texture">A texture image whose width and height are powers of two.  In some
graphics systems, this is a requirement of any image that is to be used as a texture.</gitem>
<gitem term="texel">A pixel in a texture image.</gitem>
<gitem term="texture transformation">A transformation that is applied to texture coordinates before
they are used to sample data from a texture.  The effect is to translate, rotate, or scale the
texture on the surface to which it is applied.</gitem>
<gitem term="texture object">A data structure that can potentially be stored
on the graphics card, and which can hold a texture image, a set of mipmaps, 
and configuration data such as the current setting for the minification and magnification
filters.  Using texture objects makes it possible to switch rapidly between textures
without having to reload the data into the graphics card.</gitem>

<gitem term="directed acyclic graph"> Also called a "dag." A linked data structure in which there are no cycles.
That is, it is not possible to find a sequence of nodes where each node links to the next and
the last node links back to the first.</gitem>

<gitem term="Eclipse">An integrated development environment for writing programs in Java (and other
programming languages).  Eclipse is a free program that can be downloaded from 
http://eclipse.org.</gitem>
<gitem term="constructor">In object-oriented programming, a subroutine that is used to create
objects.  A constructor for a class creates and initializes objects belonging to that
class.</gitem>
<gitem term="GUI">(Graphical User Interface.) A user interface for a program where the user
interacts with the program using components such as windows, menus, buttons, and
text-input boxes.</gitem>

<gitem term="three.js">A JavaScript library for 3D graphics.  The library implements an
object-oriented scene graph API.  While it is used primarily with WebGL, three.js can
also render 3D scenes using the 2D canvas graphics API.</gitem>
<gitem term="attenuation">Refers to the way that illumination from a point light or
spot light decreases with distance from the light.  Physically, illumination should
decrease with the square of the distance, but computer graphics often uses a linear
attenuation with distance, or no attenuation at at all.</gitem>
<gitem term="Euler angles">Express the rotation of an object in its own coordinate system,
given as individual rotations about the x, y, and z axes in that coordinate system.  
The cumulative effect of rotations about the three coordinate axes depends on the order in
which the rotations are applied.</gitem>
<gitem term="Phong shading">A technique for computing pixel colors on a primitive using
a lighting equation that takes into account ambient, diffuse, and specular reflection.
In Phong shading, the lighting equation is applied at each pixel.  Normal vectors are
specified only at the vertices of the primitive.  The normal vector that 
is used in the lighting equation at a pixel is obtained by interpolating the
normal vectors for the vertices. Phong shading is named after 
Bui Tuong Phong, who developed the theory in the 1970s.</gitem>
<gitem term="Lambert shading">A technique for computing pixel colors on a primitive using
a lighting equation that takes into account ambient and diffuse reflection.
In Lambert shading, the lighting equation is applied only at the vertices of the
primitive.  Color values for pixels in the primitive are  calculated by interpolating the
values that were computed for the vertices.  Lambert shading is named after Johann Lambert,
who developed the theory on which it is based in the eighteenth century.</gitem>

<gitem term="flat shading">A lighting computation for the faces of a polygon or polygonal
mesh that uses the same normal vector at each point in the polygon, giving the polygon a flat
or faceted appearance.</gitem>
<gitem term="smooth shading">A lighting computation for the faces of a polygon or polygonal
mesh that uses a different normal vector at each vertex of the polygon.  When two polygons
share a vertex, both polygons use the same normal vector for that vertex, resulting in a
smooth appearance at that vertex.  Smooth shading is appropriate when a polygonal mesh is
used as an approximation for a smooth surface.</gitem>
<gitem term="spotlight"> A light that emits a cone of illumination.  A spotlight is
similar to a point light in that it has a position in 3D space, and light radiates from
that position.  However, the light only affects objects that are in the spotlight's
cone of illumination.</gitem>
<gitem term="Blender"> A free and open source 3D modeling and animation program.</gitem>
<gitem term="JSON"> (JavaScript Object Notation.) A syntax for representing JavaScript objects
as strings, similar to the object literal syntax that is used in JavaScript.  JSON objects
cannot contain functions, but they can contain strings, numbers, and booleans.  JSON has
become a popular standard for storage and transmission of structured data.</gitem>
<gitem term="URL">Uniform Resource Locator. An address of some resource on the World Wide Web.
For example, "http://math.hws.edu/grahicsbook".</gitem>
<gitem term="quaternion">A vector in the quaternion algebra, which is a four dimensional vector space
in which two vectors, in addition to being added, can be multiplied.  In computer graphics, quaternions of 
length one are often used to represent rotations.  An advantage is that in the quaternion representation,
it is possible to smoothly interpolate between two rotations.</gitem>

<gitem term="lathing">A technique for producing a surface by rotating a planar curve about a line
that lies in the same plane as the curve. As each point rotates about the line, it generates a circle.
The surface is the union of the circles generated by all the points on the curve. Lathing imitates
shapes that can be produced by a mechanical lathe.</gitem>
<gitem term="extrusion">A technique for producing a solid from a 2D shape by
moving the shape along a curve in 3D.  The solid is the set of points through which
the shape passes as it moves along the curve.  The most common case is moving the shape
along a line segment that is perpendicular to the plane that contains the shape.  In practice,
in computer graphics, the object that is produced by extrusion is just the surface of
the extruded solid.</gitem>

<gitem term="anaglyph stereo">A technique for combining stereographic images of a scene, one for the
left eye and one for the right eye, into a single image.  Typically, the image for the left eye is
drawn using only shades of red, and the image for the right eye contains only blue and green
color components.  The 3D effect can be seen by viewing the combined image through
red/cyan glasses, which allow each eye to see only the image that is intended for that eye.</gitem>
<gitem term="shadow mapping">A technique for determining which parts of a scene are illuminated
and which are in shadow from a given light source.  The technique involves rendering the scene
from the point of the view of the light source, but uses only the depth buffer from that
rendering.  The depth buffer is the "shadow map."   Along a given direction from the light
source, the object that is illuminated by the light is the one that is closest to the light.
The distance to that object is essentially encoded in the depth buffer.  Objects at
greater distance are in shadow.</gitem>
<gitem term="cubemap texture">A texture made up of six images, one for each of the directions
positive x, negative x, positive y, negative y, positive z, and negative z.  The images
are intended to include everything that can be seen from a given point. Cubemap textures
are used for environment mapping and skyboxes.</gitem>
<gitem term="skybox">A large cube that surrounds a scene and is textured with images that
form a background for that scene, in all directions.</gitem>
<gitem term="reflection mapping">Another name for environment mapping.</gitem>
<gitem term="environment mapping">A way of simulating mirror-like reflection from the surface
of an object.  The environment that is to be reflected from the surface 
is represented as a cubemap texture.  To determine what point in the texture
is visible at a given point on the object,
a ray from the viewpoint is reflected from the surface point, and the reflected ray
is intersected with the texture cube.  Environment mapping is also called reflection mapping.</gitem>
<gitem term="refraction">The bending of light as it passes from one transparent or translucent
medium into another.</gitem>

<gitem term="pipeline">A sequence of computational stages in a GPU that are applied to
incoming data to produce some result.  Some of the stages can be programmable shaders,
such as vertex shaders, fragment shaders, and compute shaders.  In a graphics rendering 
pipeline, the output is the colors of the pixels in an image.</gitem>
<gitem term="fixed-function pipeline">A graphics processing pipeline with a fixed set of processing
stages that cannot be modified by a programmer.  Data for an image passes through a sequence of
processing stages, with the image as the end product.  The sequence is called a "pipeline."
With a fixed-function pipeline, the programmer can enable and disable stages and set options
that control the processing but cannot add to the functionality.</gitem>
<gitem term="programmable pipeline">A graphics processing pipeline in which some of the processing
stages can or must be implemented by programs.  Data for an image passes through a sequence of
processing stages, with the image as the end product.  The sequence is called a "pipeline."
Programmable pipelines are used in modern GPUs to provide more flexibility and control to the
programmer.  The programs for a programmable pipeline are known as shaders and are written in 
a shader programming language such as GLSL.</gitem>
<gitem term="attribute variable">Variables that represent input to the vertex shader in a 
programmable graphics pipeline.  An attribute variable can take on a different value for 
each vertex in a primitive.</gitem>
<gitem term="uniform variable">Variables that represent input to a shader program in a
programmable graphics pipeline.  A uniform variable has the same value at every vertex
and at every pixel of a primitive.</gitem>
<gitem term="varying variable"> A variable that is used to communicate values from the
vertex shader to the fragment shader in the WebGL or OpenGL ES 2.0 graphics pipeline.
A varying variable is assigned a value in the vertex shader.  The value of the variable in
the fragment shader for a pixel in the primitive is obtained by interpolating the values 
from the vertices of the primitive.  (In newer versions of GLSL, which support additional
shader stages, the term "varying variable" is replaced by the more general terms "in variable" 
and "out variable," which refer to variables that are used for input to or output from a shader.)</gitem>

<gitem term="swizzler">In GLSL and WGSL, a notation such as v.yzx, where v is a vector and
v.yzx represents the three-component vector made up of the y, z, and x components of v.  Technically,
any use of the dot notation with vectors is considered to be a swizzler.</gitem>
<gitem term="column-major order">Column-by-column ordering of the elements of a two-dimensional
matrix; that is, an ordering that starts with the elements in the first column,
followed by the elements in the second column, and so on.  Column-major order is used for
matrices in OpenGL and GLSL.</gitem>
<gitem term="storage qualifier">In GLSL, one of the following modifiers on a variable declaration:
uniform, attribute, varying, or const.</gitem>
<gitem term="precision qualifier">In GLSL, one of the following modifiers on a numeric variable declaration:
lowp, mediump, or highp.  A precision modifier specifies the minimum number of bits or range
of values for the variable.</gitem>
<gitem term="invariant qualifier">In GLSL, a modifier that ensures that when the same expression
is used to compute the value of a variable in two different shaders, the value will be the
same in both shaders.  This can be important for multi-pass algorithms, where several shader
programs are applied in succession to render one image.</gitem>
<gitem term="multi-pass algorithm">A rendering algorithm that draws a scene several times
and combines the results somehow to compute the final image.  A simple example is
anaglyph stereo, in which a left-eye and right-eye image of the scene are rendered
separately and combined.</gitem>

<gitem term="texture unit">A hardware component in a GPU that does texture
lookup. (Can also refer to an abstraction for such a component, whether or not it is
actually implemented in hardware.)  
That is, it maps texture coordinates to colors from an image texture.  This is 
the operation called "sampling," and texture units are associated with sampler variables in
GLSL shader programs.</gitem>
<gitem term="TMU">Texture Mapping Unit, another name for texture unit (perhaps with a stronger
implication of actual hardware support).  Also called a TPU (Texture Processing Unit).</gitem>
<gitem term="sampling">The operation of mapping texture coordinates to colors from a texture,
including using mipmaps if available and applying a minification or magnification filter if
necessary.</gitem>
<gitem term="sampler variable">In GLSL, a variable in a shader program that can be used
to do lookup in an image texture.  The value of a sampler variable specifies the texture
unit that will be used to do the lookup.  In WebGL, sampler variables are of type "sampler2D"
or "samplerCube."</gitem>

<gitem term="texture repeat mode">Determines how texture coordinates outside the range 0.0 to 1.0
are treated when sampling an image texture.  The texture image itself has vertical and
horizontal coordinates in the range
0.0 to 1.0. For coordinates outside that range, the texture repeat mode CLAMP or
CLAMP_TO_EDGE, for example, clamps the coordinates to the range 0.0 to 1.0, essentially extending the color
at the edge of the image indefinitely in all directions. Other repeat modes include
REPEAT and MIRRORED_REPEAT.</gitem>
<gitem term="luminance">A quantity representing the perceived brightness of a color. For
an RGB color, it is a weighted average of the red, green, and blue components of the
color. The usual formula is 0.3*red + 0.59*green + 0.11*blue.</gitem>

<gitem term="glMatrix">An open-source JavaScript library for vector and matrix math in
two and three dimensions.</gitem>

<gitem term="per-vertex lighting">Doing lighting calculations only at the vertices of a primitive,
and interpolating the results to get the colors of interior pixels.  Per-vertex lighting is
the standard in traditional OpenGL. Per-vertex lighting without specular reflection is
Lambert shading.</gitem>
<gitem term="per-pixel lighting">Doing lighting calculations at each pixel of a primitive, which
gives better results in most cases than per-vertex lighting.  Phong shading uses per-pixel lighting,
with normal vectors interpolated from the vertices.</gitem>

<gitem term="polygon offset">A 3D graphics technique that slightly increases or decreases the depth of
the pixels in a primitive as it is rendered.  Polygon offset is used to avoid having several
objects at exactly the same depth, a situation that is not handled well by the depth test.</gitem>

<gitem term="procedural texture">A texture for which the value at a given set of texture
coordinates is computed as a mathematical function of the coordinates, as opposed to an
image texture where the value is obtained by sampling an image.</gitem>
<gitem term="Perlin noise">A technique invented by Ken Perlin in 1983 that is used in the computation of
natural-looking procedural textures.  A Perlin noise function has numerical inputs (usually 2 or 3)
and produces an output number in the range -1.0 to&nbsp;1.0.  The output is pseudo-random, but
has some regularity, with features that are similarly sized and regularly distributed,
and with variation on several scales.</gitem>
<gitem term="bumpmapping">Using a texture to modify the normal vectors on a surface, to give
the appearance of variations in height without actually modifying the geometry of the surface.</gitem>

<gitem term="framebuffer">In WebGL, a data structure that organizes the buffers for rendering an
image, possibly including a color buffer, a depth buffer, and a stencil buffer.  A WebGL graphics context has a
default framebuffer for on-screen rendering, and additional framebuffers can be created for
off-screen rendering.</gitem>
<gitem term="renderbuffer">In WebGL, a buffer (that is, a region of memory) that can be
attached to a framebuffer for use as a color buffer, depth buffer, or stencil buffer.</gitem>
<gitem term="render-to-texture">A technique in which the output of a rendering operation
is written directly to a texture.  In WebGL, render-to-texture can be implemented by
attaching the texture as one of the buffers in a framebuffer.</gitem>
<gitem term="depth mask">In WebGL, a setting that controls whether depth values are
written to the depth buffer during rendering.  When the depth mask is set to false,
the depth value is discarded and the depth buffer is unchanged.</gitem>
<gitem term="color mask">In WebGL, a setting that determines which "channels" in the color
buffer are written during rendering.  The channels are the RGBA color components red, green, 
blue, and alpha. A color mask consists of four boolean values, one for each channel. A false
value prevents any change from being made to the corresponding color component in the color
buffer.</gitem>

<gitem term="WebGL extension">An optional capability in WebGL that is not available in all
implementations.  The WebGL API has a function for checking whether a given extension is available and, 
if so, activating it.</gitem>
<gitem term="anisotropic filtering">A technique for more accurate sampling of texture images, in the
case where a pixel on the surface that is being textured corresponds to a non-rectangular region in the
texture.  Anisotropic filtering is available as an optional extension in WebGL.</gitem>
<gitem term="deferred shading">A multi-pass rendering technique where a first pass processes the geometry and
saves relevant information such as transformed coordinates, normal vectors, and material properties.  The
data can be stored in textures, which are called "geometry buffers" or "G-buffers" in this context.
Lighting and other effects can then be computed in additional passes, using the pre-computed
information from the geometry buffers instead of re-computing it for each pass.</gitem>

<gitem term="ray tracing">A recursive rendering algorithm that uses ray casting.  A ray is cast
from the viewpoint through a point in the image and into the scene, to determine what is seen at
that point.  To determine the color that is seen at that point, further rays are cast
from the point, including a reflected ray (if the object has specular reflections),
a refracted ray (if the object is translucent) and shadow rays towards light sources (to determine
whether the object is illuminated by that light).  Finding a color for a reflected or refracted
ray can use a recursive application of the ray tracing algorithm.</gitem>
<gitem term="shadow ray">In the ray tracing algorithm, a ray that is cast from a point on object in the
direction of a light source to determine whether that point is illuminated by that light source
or is in shadow.</gitem>
<gitem term="ray casting">The process of following a ray (that is, half of an infinite line) starting
at a given point and extending in a given direction, in order to find points of intersection of
the ray with objects in a scene.  Usually, only the intersection point that is closest to the
starting point of the ray is of interest.</gitem>
<gitem term="barycentric coordinates">A coordinate system on a triangle in which a point is written
as a linear combination of the vertices of the triangle, that is, a*A+b*B+c*C, where A, B, and C
are the vertices and a, b, and c are numbers.  Any point in the triangle can be written in this form
where the coefficients a, b, and c have values in the range 0 to 1 and a+b+c is equal to 1.</gitem>
<gitem term="IOR">Index of Refraction.  A property of a medium, such as air or glass, that transmits light.
The refraction, or bending, of light rays that pass from one medium to another depends on the ratio of
the IORs of the two media.  The index of refraction of a medium depends on the speed of light in that
medium.</gitem>

<gitem term="path tracing">A rendering algorithm based on the idea of computing all the paths that
light could have followed to arrive at the position of a viewer from each direction.  Since that
is literally impossible, the algorithm traces a random sample of paths and averages the results.
As the number of samples increases, the average converges to a very high-quality image.</gitem>
<gitem term="BSDF">Bidirectional Scattering Distribution Function.  A generalization of the
idea of "material" in 3D graphics.  A BSDF gives the probability that a light ray that arrives
at point of space from one direction will leave that point heading in a another direction.
The probability is a function of the two directions, the point, and the wavelength of the light.
One kind of scattering is reflection of light from a surface.  For that case, the term
BRDF (Bidirectional Reflectance Distribution Function) is used.</gitem>
<gitem term="subsurface scattering">A lighting effect in which light enters a slightly translucent
object, is reflected internally one or more times, and then exits the object at a different point.
Subsurface scattering contributes to the appearance of materials such as jade, milk, and skin.</gitem>
<gitem term="ambient occlusion">A rendering technique that takes into account the fact that ambient light
will illuminate different surfaces to varying extents, depending on the degree to which ambient light is blocked,
or "occluded," from reaching each surface by other geometry in the scene.  
Ambient occlusion is an improvement on basic ambient lighting, but, like ambient light itself,
it is not an actual physical phenomenon.</gitem>


<gitem term="PBR">Physically Based Rendering.  A general term encompassing a variety of techniques
for rendering materials that look more physically realistic than the materials traditionally used
in OpenGL and similar graphics APIs.  The idea is to implement the actual physics of light
and material more directly.  PBR has become common in real-time graphics such
as video games.</gitem>

<gitem term="ES6">A version of JavaScript implemented by almost all modern web browsers.  More formally
known as ECMAScript&nbsp;6 or ECMAScript&nbsp;2015.  ES6 introduced a large number of new features.</gitem>
<gitem term="Direct3D">Microsoft's proprietary API for 3D graphics on the Windows operating system.</gitem>
<gitem term="Metal">Apple's proprietary API for 3D graphics and computation on MacOS computers and iOS devices.</gitem>
<gitem term="Vulkan">An open-source cross-platform API for 3D graphics and computation, designed as a
more modern and efficient replacement for OpenGL.</gitem>

<gitem term="GLTF">GL Transfer Format.  A file format for 3D models.  A GLTF file can
contain complete 3D scenes, including objects, materials, lights, and even animations.
The GLTF specification comes from the Khronos Group, which is also responsible for
OpenGL, WebGL, and Vulkan.</gitem>

<gitem term="VAO">Vertex Array Object.  In WebGL 2.0, a region of memory, typically on the graphics card,
that holds a collection of attribute settings such as enabled state and values of vertex attribute pointers.
All of the settings can then be selected simply by binding the VAO.</gitem>
<gitem term="instanced drawing">The ability to render multiple versions of a primitive
with a single function call.  Each copy can have its own values for certain attributes, such as
color or transformation.</gitem>

<gitem term="WebGPU">A new JavaScript graphics API, similar to WebGL, but designed to let web programs access
modern GPU capabilities such as compute shaders.</gitem>

<gitem term="global illumination">The goal of 3D rendering algorithms that take into account all the interactions
of light in a scene, including indirect illumination by light that bounces off other objects.</gitem>

<gitem term="displacement mapping">A technique used to modify a polygonal mesh by
moving, or displacing, the vertices of the mesh.</gitem>

<gitem term="height map">An image in which the grayscale value represents a height,
or elevation.  Height maps can be used in displacement mapping to specify the
amount of displacement.</gitem>

<gitem term="HDR image">A high dynamic range image.  An HDR image has more color information
than the usual eight bits per color channel per pixel.  This makes it more suitable to
uses that require calculation with the color values.</gitem>

<gitem term="promise (in JavaScript)">In JavaScript programming, a promise represents a result
that might be available immediately or at some time in the future.  A programmer can provide
a function to be called if and when the promise is fulfilled (that is when the result becomes
available).  A programmer can also provide a function to be called when the promise is
rejected (for example, if some error occurs).  Promises are asynchronous since the function
that handles success or failure will be called at some unpredictable time.</gitem>
<gitem term="async function">In JavaScript, an async function is one that can use
an "await" statement to wait for the result of a promise.  When an await statement is
executed, the execution of the async function is suspended until the promise has either
been fulfilled or rejected, giving other JavaScript code a chance to run in the
meantime.</gitem>
<gitem term="vertex buffer">In WebGPU, a vertex buffer is a GPU data structure that
holds values to be used as input the vertex shader.</gitem>
<gitem term="WGSL">The WebGPU Shader Language, the programming language in which 
shaders for use in WebGPU are written.</gitem>
<gitem term="bind group (in WebGPU)">A data structure that can hold resources
such as buffers, textures, and samples, for input into a pipeline.</gitem>
<gitem term="index buffer">In WebGPU, an index buffer is a GPU buffer that holds
vertex indices for use with the drawIndexed().  A vertex index gives the position
of a vertex in the list of vertices of a primitive.</gitem>
<gitem term="indexed drawing">In WebGPU, drawing a primitive using the
drawIndexed() function.  With that function, vertices are not generated
in the order in which they are listed.  Instead, a list of vertex indices
in an index buffer determines the order of the vertices.  Indexed drawing
is used to render indexed face sets.</gitem>
<gitem term="alignment (in WGSL)">Restrictions on the legal location of
a value in memory, depending on the data type.  For example, the address
of a vec3f variable in WGSL must be a multiple of 16.</gitem>
<gitem term="storage buffer">In WebGPU, a general purpose buffer on the GPU,
which can be used in compute shaders as well as in vertex and fragment shaders.</gitem>
<gitem term="multisampling">A kind of antialiasing where the fragment shader is
evaluated at several points in each pixel, and the results are averaged to get
the color of the pixel.</gitem>
<gitem term="address space (in WGSL)">WGSL memory is divided into address spaces.  
From the WGSL specification: "Each address space has unique properties 
determining mutability, visibility, the values it may contain, and 
how to use variables with it."</gitem>
<gitem term="NDC">Normalized Device Coordinates.  In WebGPU, refers to the default 
xyz coordinate system in which x and y range from -1 to&nbsp;1 and z ranges
from 0 to&nbsp;1.  The x and y in NDC map linearly to device, or pixel, coordinates
on the viewport.</gitem>
<gitem term="compute shader">A stage in a GPU pipeline that does purely computational
work, rather than participating directly in graphical rendering.</gitem>

</glossary>
